Chapter 15

Speaking

1953–1961

Wall Street–Fordham–Other New York Meetings–New England States–South–Mid-West–Mountain States–West Coast–Canada

Wall Street

Here is the center of exploitation of the world. Actually, Wall Street begins at Trinity Church and ends at the American Sugar Refining Company at 120 Wall, where it runs into Front Street. As Eric Gill would say, metaphysically and commercially Wall Street extends to Times Square, St. Patrick’s, Fordham, Columbia, and to all the places where the Sermon on the Mount is ignored or watered down, and where the devil is worshiped.

Here in New York City, I spoke for the season in 1954 at Broad and Wall Streets. The law in this state is to have a fairly large American flag. I also had a standard with a cut of St. Francis, as drawn by Eichenberg, with the current CW attached to it, and I stood on a small aluminum step ladder. I kept this paraphernalia at the I.W.W. hall, lower down on Broad Street. Once, I had the flag upside down, and a woman made a complaint to a cop; and once an inch of it touched the ground, and I was ordered to lift it higher. But one cold day, my nose dripped, and I could not get at my handkerchief without getting someone to hold my flag and sign, so unknowingly I used the flag for a handkerchief. My audience must have been entranced, for no one noticed it. A CW girl standing by told me afterwards about it. Sometimes I would have the competition of “The Bishop,” a husky Southerner in a homberg, who arrived in a limousine and denounced “The Whore of Babylon,” meaning the Catholic Church. Sometimes I got his crowd away, and sometimes he diminished mine. After years when I was not speaking, but was selling CWs nearby and would walk by, he would take a paper from me and tell his crowd, “You know what I think of the so and so Pope, but this CW is a good paper, and my friend Hennacy is what I call a good Catholic who goes to jail for his ideas.”

Patricia Rusk and I had visited John Moody, of The Moody Investment Service and Moody Manual of Business. He had known Peter in the early days, was a convert, and had been a Single Taxer, which was quite radical then. I had told him that time belonged to God and not to bankers, not even 1%. He bought my book, and later wrote to me saying:

I pray for your success every Tuesday when you are speaking on Wall Street. You are getting under the sculls of people. I hear about it. God bless you.

Another time a man said to me, “For 41 years I was a Catholic and now I left the damn church.” I replied: “That’s fine. It wasn’t for you. For 51 years I was not a Catholic and now I joined the Church, and we are both happy.”

Once a man said to me, “What are you first, a Catholic or an anarchist?” Some months before, a Protestant had asked how I evaluated my ideas, and I had put being a Catholic fourth. In October of 1954, I was confirmed at Newburgh by Bishop Flannery, (Administrator) of St. Patrick’s Cathedral, along with many others. I had given his secretary a copy of my book, and four years later I discovered it was on his desk. Whether he had waited four years to read it, or read it again after four years, I do not know. I never spoke to him personally. I had not noticed anything special at this confirmation. But now, I guess, my confirmation caught up with me, for I answered:

I am Catholic and go to Mass and Communion daily, worthily I hope.
To live poor, for the world’s baggage bogs you down.
To love your enemy, not everyone but your enemy.
To bring this out in small groups of like minded people.
To be a worker and not a parasite, and this cuts out all Wall Street.
To be an anarchist, for if you live a dedicated life and vote for this and that politician to return evil for evil in courts, prisons and war, you deny Christ.
I do not smoke, drink, eat meat, or take medicine, for if tomorrow “come the revolution,” I can’t “revolut” if I am tied to an aspirin or a cigarette.

At Fordham

I spoke there seven times, but not until I had stood outside the gates for some years, selling CWs and getting acquainted. I was finally invited to speak to The Economics Club, the Suarez Society, and Fordham Political Union on “The Position of a Political Anarchist in the Catholic Church.” I had to tell them that the term “political” was a misnomer. I told them,

…that when I spoke to Protestants, they asked why I had joined the worst church, and when I spoke to Catholics, they asked how they let a guy like me in. I replied to the Protestants that of course the Catholic Church was the worst church; that they would be just as bad if they knew how, they were jealous. And to the Catholics I said that I was baptized by an anarchist priest, Father Casey near Minneapolis, the only one in this country (there was one in Yucatan and one in Canada, but they were too far away), and that you didn’t have to be a Democrat or a Republican to be a priest. And when I was baptized, I had had to read the Catechism. The Fourth Commandment said to honor and obey your parents, and from this it followed to obey the civil authorities.

“What kind of a Church am I getting into; have I got to mind the cops?”

“No,” said Father Casey, “That’s just for people who don’t know any better.

We know better, we have to do better. There’s likely a little corner in Heaven for Catholic hangmen (they don’t know any better—no one told them)—right next to the bingo players. But there is another place where Saint Francis, Saint Martin of Tours, and others are. If we want to see them, we have to try to be like them. This is what this commandment means today: when Jesus was asked what to do with the woman caught in sin He said: “he that is without sin among you first cast a stone at her.” And His teaching was to love the enemy, forgive seventy times seven; turn the other cheek. So today, if you vote for anyone who makes a law saying five days, five years, life, or death if you do something or if you don’t do something; or if you vote for the judge who pronounces the sentence; or if you vote for the governor or president who appoints the hangman or the jailers, then these men are your servants; they are your arm to throw the stone, and you deny Christ. Now, you folks don’t have to be in a hurry to be an anarchist, for I was 59 years getting to be a Catholic. But I am sent here to waken you up, and you can’t say you never heard it; you will have to sweat a little from now on; you will have to approximate the anarchist way if you want to be a real Catholic, or a real Christian.

And the Fifth Commandment says Thou Shalt Not Kill, but the Catechism says it is permitted to kill in a just war, capital punishment, and self defense. Father Casey said that of course there was no just war; that capital punishment denied the Sermon on the Mount, and that I had defended myself much better when I shook hands with the man with the knife, than if I had used a knife—that I couldn’t use knives and guns like other Catholics, for I knew better, so I had to do better. Now of course, on the subject of war, the Holy Father has said that a Catholic cannot be a conscientious objector in a just war. And there are no unjust wars for the Catholics in any certain country. They are supposed to obey their rulers. It is the other country that has the “unjust” war. So in Italy, Catholics killed for God and Mussolini, and in Ethiopia they killed for God and Haile Selaissie, And in Germany, for God and Hitler, and in this country, for God and the man who said “I tell you again, again and again, that no boys will be sent across to war.” The fact is that the true meaning of the word “Catholic” is “universal,” and God does not have any country, for we are all brothers. Once, a Sunday School teacher was reading from the Bible, and she read the passage where “God spoke unto Joshua saying kill all the Ammonites, Jebusites, Moabites, and suffer not a one to live.” A little girl raised her hand and said:

“Teacher, that must have been before God got to be a Christian.”Life magazine a few years ago had an old English woodcut showing the hanging of pickpockets. This public Spectacle was supposed to deter pickpockets, but at this public hanging the pickpockets worked the crowd. When I was in prison in Atlanta I met many counterfeiters; they were not the best ones, they were the second best, for the best ones were out making money—I mean “making money.”

Then I told of my life in prison, of my anti-tax activity. I spoke later, half a dozen times, to classes, and as I travel over the country, I find former Fordham students who greet me.

A priest from a ritzy Bronx church asked me to speak at a Communion breakfast, just before St. Patrick’s Day. I suggested that Dorothy speak, as I would be too radical. He replied that he wanted me to jolt the “lace-curtain,” complacent Irish in his parish. It was a very ritzy breakfast in a hotel, with an Irish audience of police, FBI, etc. character. Naturally, few agreed with me. When the meeting was over the priest said: “Mr. Hennacy is an anarchist, and he is a Catholic, and maybe a better Catholic than I am. It is good for you to hear him, and that is why I brought him here to waken you to the possibilities of what our Gospel might mean to us.” I spoke in classes in Catholic high schools, and to the Information Center on Staten Island, and to the Newman Clubs at Brooklyn and Brooklyn Technical. Here the priests made it plain that they did not agree with me, but wanted the students to hear what I had to say. A meeting at the Walter Farrell Guild, where liberal Catholics hold forth, was very interesting. The liberals, who are for good capitalism, good wars, and the impossible task of trying to make sense out of “workers councils and employers councils” and no class struggle between the two, per the Pope’s encyclicals, no doubt find the forthright radicalism of the CW aggravating, and seemingly unreasonable.

May the first, in 1958, was a busy day for me, as I spoke, wearing a red ribbon, to the Bronx Science High School, which is one of the two best schools in this country, according to Time magazine of that week. Here, the students were enthusiastic, and I was to meet some of them later in picket lines. Then a busload of students came up from Drew University, for the third time in as many years, and I spoke to them, and at midnight I attended a committee meeting against atomic tests.

Nightbeat is a program on television where John Wingate interviewed two people for half an hour each. This was not previewed. His secretary read my book, and interviewed me. I never saw Wingate until the minute I entered the television room, when he said to me, “My last question will be about Cardinal Spellman. Will you answer it?” I replied that I would. Mr. Wingate picked out of half a dozen definitions in the dictionary on anarchism, the one which mentioned “chaos,” and gave a statement from an anonymous theologian that a Catholic could not be an anarchist. I gave my definitions of anarchism and explained my application of it, and of course, there are all kinds of theologians, and none of them bind me to disobey my conscience; and besides, I was baptized by an anarchist priest. Mr. Wingate good-naturedly chided me on my vegetarianism, pacifism, and refusal to take medicine. He asked me if I believed in the infallibility of the Pope. I said I did when he was infallible, and when he wasn’t, he was talking through the Pope’s hat. I explained that we respected Spellman as a Cardinal, but were not bound to agree with any of his patriotic and anti-union ideas; that he had a lot of patience with us, and had never picketed us. And that I was bound to obey my conscience above any Church authority. Stuart Cloete, the novelist from Africa, followed me on the program. As we were waiting, I traded books with him. He had whiskers, and most of his time was spent in a defense of wearing them. The night before Christmas, Mr. Wingate’s secretary phoned, and asked if I would be on their Christmas program. A Baptist minister from New Jersey, who had a Christmas party in July to get clothing for an Indian mission in the West, explained his novel scheme. Some Salvation Army lassies explained their procedure. A chorus of Negroes from a Harlem Church sang. I suppose I was to represent the Catholics. Mr. Wingate went over all of my wild ideas and goodnaturedly kidded me about them. I replied in like manner. Christ and the Sermon on the Mount is my guide to determine truth. For years I have met people on the street who saw me on these programs, and stop and ask me questions.

For several times in the fall, I spoke at a Socialist picnic at Massepaqua Long Island, along with Earl Browder and Norman Thomas. I knew Earl in the old days, when he was released from Leavenworth as a CO in World War I. He gets further and further away from radicalism. Norman is always a good speaker and fighter for what he believes, but he gets less and less radical as he grows older. It was up to me to speak of the old days of Debs and Mother Bloor, and to dare them to come alive.

Father Meyer, at the Episcopalian Henry Street Settlement on the Lower East Side, is a friend of ours. He gets his money from the corrupt Trinity Church, but he puts it to good use. If any of the kids in the gangs are fighting, and one of them touches his hands on Fr. Meyer’s Church, that is sanctuary. His work with the gangs is the best that has been done by anyone. He has spoken here at the CW twice, and Dorothy and I have been down to his Church speaking to his young folks twice.

In the New England States

Holy Cross Seminary, at Worcester, Mass., is a conservative Jesuit college. A student from there had bought a CW and my book from me at 43rd and Lexington, and wrote for me to come there. I got there at 5 p.m., and he said, “You very nearly didn’t have a meeting.”

“How come?” I asked.

“At 1 p.m., the Dean called me in, and said, ‘I find that the Catholic Worker is subversive, and Hennacy is the worst one. The meeting is cancelled. I’ll put a guard at the gate and not allow him on the campus.’ ”

At 2 p.m. the student received a letter from Bishop Wright, saying, “I hear our mutual friend Ammon is speaking tonight. I would like to attend his meeting but cannot do so for I have a meeting of my own. Have him call this phone number at 9:30 and I’ll see him in the morning. God bless Ammon and the Catholic Worker.”

The student showed this letter to the Dean, and he said, “Have your meeting.” The room was crowded, and I was answering questions in the students’ rooms until 1:30 in the morning.

About the same time, a Methodist and a Lutheran student, who had heard me in the Midwest, and who were now studying to be missionaries in foreign countries, asked me to speak at the Hartford Theological Seminary. When I got there, the students told me I very nearly didn’t have a meeting. It seemed that the professor in charge of meetings in the building where I was supposed to speak was afraid of the word “anarchist,” and asked my friends if they could get me to speak without using this dreadful word. They said that was one of my especial words. This professor conferred with the president, and he did not wish to take the responsibility, so the board of trustees decided that if I said I was a “Catholic anarchist,” and not a Protestant one, I could have a meeting. So for once, I hid behind the Church.

At Dartmouth, the Christian Union turned out to hear me with much interest, but the Catholic youth who had suggested my coming got frightened, and when he heard that I was speaking to the class of a Catholic prof. in the morning, he notified the young, conservative Catholic Chaplain, who tried to stop my talk to the class. I spoke. But later, the Bishop of New Hampshire would not allow me to speak in that state. He died, and I have no contract with that state since; and it is just as well, as it has a bad reputation in jailing Rev. Uphaus.

Prof. Bourcier, of Middlebury College in Vermont, had inv1ted me to come there and speak, but the authorities thought I would be “too controversial.” He ordered four of my books and gave them to these men to read, and I was invited to speak, having fine meetings with hours of questioning at the College, and a large meeting at St. Mary’s parochial school. I had stayed at the home of the priest that night, and in the morning he looked up the definition of anarchism which meant “chaos,” but after my explanation of it, he phoned to the grade school and had me speak to classes there. I had also spoken to Trinity College in Burlington, and to nearby St. Michaels, as well as meetings at Brattleboro and Putney College.

I spent a night at the home of a Quaker, Herbert Leader, in Burlington, Vt., and he told me I was to speak to some classes at the U. of Vt. the next day. The first one was on labor history. I sang I.W.W. songs, told them of Mother Jones, Debs, and Joe Hill, and answered questions for a long time. The next class was in sociology, where a student gave a review of an article by Protestant ministers who had visited Moscow. I had heard these ministers here at the CW, and gave further information and, also, the report of a Catholic priest who had been imprisoned by the Communists in China for six years, and who emerged more friendly to the Communists than to the usurper Chiang. Too many priests there are agents of “American imperialism,” and it cannot be expected that the Chinese would like them. The next class was a two-hour seminar on social work, so I was at home describing my life as a social worker, and life now on the Bowery. That night, I spoke to a large meeting of students on CW ideas. I was interested in St. Albans, as this was the town where Morgans Raiders held up and robbed the local bank after their escape from Plattsburg prison in the Civil War time. Raider Morgan had been captured near my home town of Lisbon, Ohio. Later, Joanna Sturm and I saw a movie based on this St. Albans robbery.

New England Town Meeting

With my farmer vegetarian friends Bob and Ann Stowell I visited the Town Meeting to which they belong at Cabot, Vt. A preliminary meeting had been held where anyone who desired questions to be discussed could present them, so that each voter now had a printed booklet on the 28 motions to be voted on that day. There was much discussion of an increase in tax for roads. About two-thirds of the town population were there, and there were more women than men present. Only those who paid a $10 poll tax could vote at the meeting, although this did not prevent them from voting in state or national elections if they did not pay their town poll tax. The Moderator is only paid for one day of the year at this meeting. He had been elected for years, and was an employee of the local cheese coop. He was voted out because he took the unpopular side of desiring a centralized school for three towns, which would cost $10,000 interest. It was defeated by 168 to 7, and a prosperous farmer became Moderator. The five Catholics present voted for free taxes for five years for the local Masonic Hall; they might as well be good-humored about it. Men are elected to run the town, not according to political party, banjo playing, or baby kissing, but because all these folks know each other, and there is no passing the buck if you are found inefficient. As an anarchist, I could stand for this decentralized administration of things, not the legislation of morals.

A man by the name of Francis had a meeting for me, at his house, for Amherst students and friends. A neighbor, whose first name was Francis, received the CW, and by mistake it was delivered to my non-Catholic friend Mr. Francis, who liked it, and invited his neighbor. At Harvard, Yale, Boston U., and Springfield College, I had interesting meetings. I spoke to classes at the U. of Connecticut at Storrs, having come there on the invitation of the Newman Club, but the priest got scared and cancelled the meeting a few hours before it was scheduled. In Provincetown, I went to visit my friends, Lee and Vicki Pagano, and my two godchildren, Pier and Jackie, and spoke to resident artists and friends, among them the old time radical Harry Kemp, who became a Catholic before his death. Somehow, I spoke to a businessman’s club at the Agawan Catholic Church and, after a couple of hours, most of those present understood me, even if they did not agree with me. I also spoke at Brandeis College on that trip.

In February of 1957, I accepted the generous invitation of Dr. Paquette, of Waterville, Maine, to extract 19 roots and make an upper plate. I had gone around for years with one tooth in front, figuring that the education of my daughters and the printing of my autobiography was more important than my looks. Seems that most of my teeth were chalky, and broke off, all of these years. After X-rays, I had these roots extracted in four sessions—at my insistence, without the aid of any drugs. It did hurt a little and I could not help a tear now and then, but I had inadvertently chosen a skillful dentist, who did a minimum of gouging, and who had a sure grip on the forceps. I found I could say “Mississippi” without any lisping. In fact, I spoke to two meetings the first night, and meetings every other night, while this dental work was going on. I spoke to my first Lions Club, telling them what I have mentioned before, that “the early Christians were thrown to the lions rather than put a pinch of incense on the altar to Caesar, while the modern ones join the Lions Club.” I spoke to some students at Colby College. Father Gower, of the local Catholic Church, had me speak to some laymen, and a tape recording was taken of my talk. My message was so radical and so new to these good men, that I had to spend two other nights explaining and answering questions, with the help of Father Gower and a retreat priest from Augusta, until they were convinced, and in all good humor felt that a Catholic could also be a radical. This layman came down to the CW for a week, later, to get better acquainted with us. I also spoke to a social worker group at Gould Farm, Gt. Barrington, Mass.

The Canterbury Boys School is a ritzy place, founded by Havemeyer Sugar, at New Milford, Conn. There is a priest there, but the teachers are lay people. I have seldom been so enthusiastically received by an audience, although nearly all that I said was new to the boys. They crowded around and bought twenty of my books, wanted to know “if I believed in unions,” etc. Later they sent a large donation to the CW. In later years, I have met them as I was talking in other colleges, or was selling CWs on the streets.

An anarchist instructor invited me to speak at Brown University and a Monsignor came to the meetings.

Speaking in the South

There are very few Catholics in the South outside of Louisiana, and the tendency is to try to appear patriotic and regular, for they are in a disliked minority. For years I had written answers to the capitalistic letters that Bill Stevens, a convert, had written to us from Charlottesville, Va. Finally, he met me at the bus when I was on my way to Florida, and we became acquainted. He had a page-long introduction to my book inserted in it when he gave it to the public library in his home town. It read in part:

Hennacy’s mother is a Fitz-Randolph. He loves Thomas Jefferson, Francis of Assisi, Tolstoy, and Gandhi. His “bomb” is the Sermon on the Mount; his “persuader” instead of the hydrogen bomb, which he abhors with a passion, is the Palm Branch, a durable weapon … Hennacy puts the phony gliberal in his place and gives a clear perspective to true Convervatism (of the individual).

Numerous friends had me speak at Norfolk. Bill and Gay Houston had me speak to student friends at Morehouse University where he was then teaching, in Atlanta. Francis Coyle had me speak to classes at the University of Georgia, but the meeting at the Newman Club was cancelled as being “too controversial.” This was at Athens. At Chapel Hill, N.C., Ronald Gosslein had me speak at the home of a radical professor, and I met the Catholic Chaplain, who was liberal. Dick Bayer, of the Charlotte N.C. News, had me speak at the Unitarian Church in nearby Monroe. Mrs. Williams, a Catholic, had asked her priest if she could come to the Unitarian Church to hear me. Her husband, head of the NAACP, and later publicized as one Negro who would use a gun instead of the pacifist method against white aggression, accompanied her. I saw the bullet holes in their car where the White Citizens Council had shot at them. I had written to all six of our subscribers in Nashville, Tennessee, telling them that I would be through their town on a certain day, and I would like to meet them. A professor at Vanderbuilt University, who was not a pacifist but who liked the CW for years, phoned me at Tell City, Indiana and planned a meeting for me, where I spoke to his class in theology. Some subscribers from the Methodist magazine Motive in that city, who liked us, came to this class. No Catholic took the paper in Nashville, and the Catholic Chaplain was aggrieved because someone of the CW had spoken in classes, instead of a patriotic Catholic.

Mr. and Mrs. Doering teach at a plush boys school north of Birmingham, and had written to me to come and visit them. A fellow teacher asked me to speak to these white, Protestant boys, and I spent all of my two days answering questions. Later, I discovered that, on the last afternoon, a police van from Birmingham was outside, and they were getting ready to defend me. I had been talking about jails all along, so it seemed natural for the police to be after me again. But nothing happened. I stayed two days at the Divine Word Seminary, at Bay St. Louis, Mississippi, an integrated school where a Negro, Father Perry, is the head, and where white and colored students live together. The only manner in which the state punished them was not to allow them any surplus commodities. Father Perry is one of the finest priests whom I have met. In New Orleans I spoke at Tulane, Notre Dame, Xavier, Sisters of the Blessed Sacrament, and the Caritas group. I met a seminarian who said that I had argued with him for years on Wall Street, until he had quit his “unholy” job, and come here to study to be a priest. At Dean Stephen Ryan’s, I had the pleasure of meeting Father Fichter, known all over the country as a courageous priest. At Lafayette, Fr. Sigur and Dr. Ward made me welcome, and I met many interested students and faculty members at this large Southwestern University. The diocesian paper here, and the local paper, and also the New Orleans paper gave me a fair story. In New Orleans, I spoke to Protestants who had read the CW for years. The wife of one of these ministers asked me, “What can I do with those War Bonds my folks gave for my children? I can throw away the guns and turn off the gangster shows on television, but I can’t throw the money away.” I remembered a friend of mine who, at Christmastime, had a date with a Southern divorcee. Just before coming to her home, he had received a telegram from his friend Joe that he was sick and had lost his job. He mentioned this to the woman, and she said, “Mr. Pat, your friend will have a miserable Christmas. This will never do. Here, send this to him.” And she went to the large family Bible and gingerly took out a $50 bill and gave it to my friend. “I keep this money in the Bible to perhaps purify it, for it has the picture of that Yankee Grant on each bill.”

My answer to this woman was to cash the War Bonds, thus not being guilty of receiving any more bloody interest, and place the money in not too large or too small bills in the Bible, and as occasion offered for any especial personal need of others, to give it out, but not to organizations. If any remained when the children grew up, it would be for them, and if it was all gone, then it had already served a good purpose.

In Oklahoma City, I stayed at the home of Byerly’s, Quakers, and had a fine meeting at the Catholic Secular Institute where priests, nuns and visiting students from Norman attended. The diocesan paper, The Courier, gave me a fine write-up, saying that I had “a firm theology all [my] own;” a fine picture on the front page with the inscription “A visit with an anarchist,” and one on the inside with two nuns. Here, a Carmelite brother wanted me to answer the article in the October 1959 Homiletie and Pastoral Review by Father Leslie Rumble, entitled “Catholic Pacifism Repudiated,” supposed to be an answer to the Morals and Missiles by English pacifists. Father Rumble said that Christ never implied anything against war in His teachings in the Sermon on the Mount, or elsewhere. Denying Christ, he quotes the theologian to the Cardinal of England as saying, “if asked, the confessor must declare conscientious objection to be wrong and sinful.” For Father Rumble to declare Catholic pacifism “abnormal,” and his declaration in favor of war normal, is to forget Benedict XV who, in his Peace of God, 1920, said, “The Gospel command of love applies between states just as it does between individual men.” Father Rumble commits the same mistake in 1960 as happened at the time of Joan of Arc, when those in the employ of the English exploiters and rulers, and who spoke for the Church, burned her. To follow Father Rumble is to place the Church where Communists today say it is: on the side of oppression, exploitation and war.

I was welcomed by radicals and Catholics at Las Vegas, N.M., and spoke to classes at Highland University there, first going to early Mass at Montezuma Seminary, where hundreds of Mexican seminarians are studying. I had been in Santa Fe many times visiting my daughters, and after I was a Catholic, I became acquainted with the Medical Missionaries, the good nuns who delivered babies, within a radius of forty miles, for free, for the poor Mexicans and Indians. Dorothy had spoken there, and I spoke to them at a meeting where Quakers, anarchists, and pacifists came. Carmen lived next door to them for some years. Someone got to the Bishop with the word that the CW was Communist, and he sent word that I was not allowed to speak to the nuns, so twice I have visited with them, but have had meetings at private homes of interested Catholics. This is the Bishop who became so excited about a girl appearing in a beauty contest, but who says nothing about the atom bombs being made, for years, in nearby Los Alamos. I have reviewed several books in the CW dealing with the history of Santa Fe and the Indians, and am glad that my daughter is married and living in this beautiful city 8,000 feet high, with the clear air, and the Indian traditions.

When living in Albuquerque from 1942 to 1947, I had met with Protestant pacifists, but had not known any Catholic pacifists. The Newman Club, at the University of New Mexico, run by the Dominicans, is a beautiful place. Just as I was announced, the bells tolled reporting the death of Pius XII. I had to tell over and over again my realistic approach to pacifism and war, which is that, as Gandhi said, “it is better to kill a tyrant than it is to knuckle and obey him, but it is much better to make him your friend.” And, quoting Forrest the Southerner, “he who gets there fustest with the mostest wins.” If we are not pacifists, then to talk of us disarming is foolish. As long as we are exploiters, we must guard our loot; only when we give up our capitalism and imperialism and our loot can we talk of acting like Christians. Ed Abbey, author of The Brave Cowboy, about two anarchists in an Albuquerque jail, drove me to Carmen’s in Santa Fe that night, after the meeting.

It is very seldom that a prophet has honor in his home town, and I consider Phoenix one of my home towns. When I was a pacifist and not a Catholic, there, for six years, I was a scandal to the bourgeois-minded pacifists and Quakers, although they liked me in private conversation; but I was always getting arrested, it seemed. And when I came back as a Catholic of six months, my Catholic friends and priests liked me, but it was too sudden for them to sponsor me at public meetings. So it was not until 1960, when I was back after my release from Sandstone prison, that Bea Trudelle had a meeting in a northern suburb for me, at a dancing studio. And, through a labor-minded lawyer, I was asked to speak a few words at the Catholic Labor group at the ritzy St. Francis Xavier Church. But no one knew I was coming, so it did not excite anyone. My very dearest friends are in Phoenix, but that does not mean public meetings. There is no rational way of explaining why the Mayor of Phoenix, Jack Williams, should have me speak on his radio station and give my radical ideas without censorship. And later, when he refused to run for mayor, he still had me on the air. He does not agree with any of my ideas, but he liked the Old Pioneer, and stood up for me even when I was going to jail, and he was only a commentator, and did not own the station, and was not mayor. Likewise, Don Dedera has given me a good hand in his column, quoting me as saying, “ ‘A man has two means of protection—the Bible or the gun. No man or country can hold a Bible in one hand and a gun in the other …’ [Hennacy] is a Christian Anarchist. Through penance and exposition, he is trying to do away with the atom bombs.” The Allen family, in Tucson, with their ten fine children, always had meetings for me when I came that way. Friends at the Arizona Ranch School had me talk to their boys. Father Fowler had me speak at St. Joseph’s Academy. Dick and Byrd Sweitzer, Tom Bahti and Elizabeth Baskette are fellow “Indian lover” friends of mine there, while Phil Burnham and Mike Cudihay always make me feel at home.

The West Coast

Over the country it is tic-tac-toe as to where the CW is welcome and where it isn’t. In San Diego there is lots of Navy, and Bishop Buddy likes the Navy, so we can only speak in a home now and then, although I did speak at San Diego University to the class of a prof. who had been fired from a Catholic College because he had as reference some book, in his English class, that no one but a Jansenist would disapprove. Although, when I visited Frank Scully—the man “who has one lung, one leg, and one idea: Frank Scully”—an old time friend of Dorothy, he wrote a column about me in the San Diego diocesan paper. In Los Angeles, it was Cardinal McIntyre who told Dorothy that she was doing God’s work, and never to give it up. I spoke to a crowd there at the Little Theatre on June 9, 1954 (the saints day of two fine martyrs, Primus and Felician, who wouldn’t give in, although told by the soldiers that each one had weakened.) Father Bruscher introduced me here at Loyola, and I have spoken to Quakers and to small groups many times when I go to Pasadena to visit my daughter Sharon. At Stanford and Santa Clara, the Steinkes always arrange meetings for me, and many students are interested, despite the conservatism of the authorities.

In San Francisco, years ago, Archbishop Mitty said that a Catholic can’t be a conscientious objector, so I visited Arthur Duffy and George Lillis—doing a six months sentence because of the letter sent to court from the Chancery Office. Individual priests are friendly, here and there, and I have spoken in meetings at Catholic bookstores, and in private homes, and at St. Albert’s, the Dominician seminary in Oakland, in Berkeley at the Newman Club, and at Wheeler Hall at the University, and before Quaker and pacifist groups many times. I have spoken on KFPA many times, and, for a time, I prepared a tape every two weeks here in N.Y. City of what I thought about the world and sent it to them, and they broadcast it. A most interesting meeting was at the Cloven Hoof, in the “beat” section. When I have finished getting acquainted with the Mormons around Salt Lake City, I plan to go to San Francisco for good, so I will be glad to see Vic and Emma Hauser, George Reeves, Warren K. Billings, Gordon Koller, Byron Bryant, Bob Pickus, and their friends there, again.

I had some fine meetings in the old gold rush country at Marysville, and a good write-up in the Yuba College paper there. Likewise in Corvallis and Eugene, in Oregon.

Portland is the one town in the west where we are welcomed by Catholics, Quakers, and liberals. The Blanchet House, where 1,800 people a day are fed, was started by young college students awakened by the CW. I spoke there in 1954, but in my two later visits, the leader was not interested in our radical philosophy for the men, but was cordial to me personally. At Catholic Portland University, three classes at Lewis and Clark, and two exciting meetings at Reed, and several Quaker meetings, I ran the whole gamut of possible questions. One cordial Jesuit priest heard me glve the very radical CW position as I spoke to Quakers at the YWCA. Wanting to pour oil on the troubled waters, he said:

On the subject of pacifism, anarchism, and war, it could be that you are right and it could be that you are wrong; and it could be on these subjects that the Church is right, and it could be that the Church is wrong; isn’t that the way, Mr. Hennacy?

“No, I am right and the Church is wrong,” and I added, “Father Feeny in Boston said that no one but a Catholic could go to Heaven. That is the line in Spain, but not in Boston, so he was excommunicated. On points of faith like Heaven, Hell, Purgatory, I will not argue; I accept what the Church teaches on Faith. But on being true to that radical Christ whom I found in solitary, I will obey Him rather than any Church authority.”

Out at Mt. Angel, Mayanna Manion and her large famlly have always been our friends, and they plan meetings for us, and the good nuns there are our especial friends always, having us speak to their classes. Reuel Amder, young non-church anarchist, and John Little, school principal in the country, are our good friends for a long time.

Seattle has an old I.W.W. tradition, so I spoke one night for the “wobs” at Washington and Occidental, where men had been killed years ago to prove the right of free speech. I came as near being beaten by a drunk that night as I ever did. He was just drunk enough to be nasty. The Salvation Army was playing on an opposite corner, and this was old time “interference,” as the wobs would say. I spoke at a liberal Church of the People and at the Unitarian Church, and to small groups of pacifists in their homes. Velde (of the Un-American Activities Committee: a good name for them) was coming there soon, so a meeting at the University was cancelled. The hierarchy there seem to be afraid of us, although numerous priests are friendly. Our old friend Isobel MacRae always had a meeting for me, and Jean David, the French Professor who knew Peter, always greeted me gladly. Bob Casey, a union seaman who does not follow us all the way, but who takes my books in ports over the world, planned several meetings at forums there, in 1960. And the diocesan paper gave a fair write-up of what I believed in. My old friend Ed Lehmann, who fought in Spain, lives here, and June and Farrar Burn live way out in the Sound, on their island. Last time I stayed with Sue and Mike Miyake, Dorothy’s niece and her husband.

I had spoken to a Catholic group, and a young priest got up and unmercifully denounced me as being devoid of any understanding of Christ’s teaching. I am not mad at any human being so far, and I am not going to start now being angry at a priest. I answered him firmly but kindly. The next day, he wrote the following letter to me, which was later printed in the CW:

I realize that after all you have been through you must be inured to most kinds of insults and misunderstandings of your character and aims. But I am afraid that what I said last night, that you don’t seem to go all out in accepting your Catholicism, might have cut into the sensitivity of even a man of such high ideals and contempt of human opinion as you are, since it was an accusation I don’t suppose you hear too often, and since it denies what you really are doing to your fullest capacity. If this was the case I hope you will accept my apology.

I also hope that you will accept my congratulations. It takes more courage than most of us can muster to accept, with no compromise, what we know is the complete Spirit of Christ’s teaching. Christ didn’t think too much of those who insisted on the letter of the law but didn’t live the spirit. As you said last night, there must always be at least one to tell the emperor that he’s naked. Maybe others will try to shut him up or embarrassedly ignore him, but they are still glad that he did say it, and do not realize that there is still some hope for the survival of truth if there is at least one man living it.

I will pray that God will continue to give you the grace to fulfill your mission of shocking men from their immersion in the letter of the law to a realization of the full spirit of Christ’s law, even if they can only live up to that spirit in a mediocre way. Since we are men, and not apples, one good man can make a whole barrel, the whole world better.

Sincerely in Christ,

Mountain States

In Spokane, Sister Bernice had me speak twice to teachers and students at her Marycliff High School. And at Gonzaga College, seminarians met me at the bus, and had me speaking about every waking minute at their college. Just one student who has nerve enough to speak up is enough to get a speaker to come to give the message and answer questions. I will not go to any group unless it is known ahead of time that I am an anarchist and a pacifist. If they are afraid of these words, they are not ready to think or to learn. I wouldn’t waste time on them.

Brother Martin Gaines has a House of Charity, where he feeds many people and houses them. He is the “Lord’s beggar,” getting practically everything by asking for it from all kinds of people. He is a pacifist, a convert, who heard me in 1954 at St. John’s in Minnesota. We had a meeting also at a home of Catholic friends of his, and I spoke to the people at his house. I’ll be nearer him when I am in Salt Lake City, and count him as my good friend.

A lone printer from Brooklyn takes the CW in Boise, Idaho, and he asked me to speak to a few friends at his home. This town, hid away in the mountains, reminds me of Santa Fe. I will have much more to write, if there is a second edition of my autobiography, about Salt Lake City, but I will begin now to tell you of my interest in the Mormons.

In Phoenix, I noticed 3,000 Mormons going out on a Saturday to pick cotton for the Church. I had read the book of Mormon, and saw more blood in it, to a page, than is in our Old Testament. I had written to the heads of the Mormon Church, in the Second World War, and asked them if a Mormon could be a conscientious objector. The answer was “they could be, they wouldn’t get the idea around us.” There was a fellow by the name of Bryan in Springfield, Mo. prison as a conscientious objector who, it is said, was some kind of a Mormon. The Mormon Church has always been bloodthirsty and conservative, but in their early history, as told in books by Vardis Fisher and others, they had a “United Order,” and today they help each other rather than have the welfare state do it. They also tithe, and do not take collections in their churches. And their meetings are very interesting. I have good Mormon friends in Flagstaff and Tucson. When I was selling CWs at 43rd and Lexington, a woman told me of a Sister Mary Catherine, a Carmelite nun, whose folks were polygamists, and whose relatives are the Romneys, Apostles in the Church. I corresponded with her, and she read my book, and she reads the CW; and I visited her in Salt Lake City. A Jewish man by the name of Herbert Rona became a convert to the Mormons. An atheist gave him a CW, and he wrote to us saying that he was a pacifist. He had me speak at his home and ex-Gov. Bracken Lee, LeGrande Richards (one of the 12 Apostles), Professor Bennion, and Judge Anderson—all Mormons—came to a meeting at Rona’s house where I explained my radical ideas. I also met a leader of the polygamous Mormons (who are out of the Church), and found that he was a pacifist, did not vote, and was a vegetarian. He had done time for having half a dozen wives and still has them.

I also know radical priests in Salt Lake City. I like to work in orchards, so by the time you are reading this, I will be out there in farm and orchard work. How much of regular Mormon (or polygamous Mormon) is worthy, and how much is phony, you will hear about as I live among these good people. The Catholic Bishop, here, has been very conservative, for the right-to-work law, and outdoing the Mormons in being conservative—at the same time subverting them by bingo, which Mormons are not allowed to indulge in. I do not know the attitude of the new Catholic Bishop.

While I am living among the Mormons, I will do them the courtesy to abstain from tea or coffee, meanwhile fasting my regular day a week as penance.

Ed Heustis is a union sympathizer in Anaconda, and a CW reader for years. He had me come there and, after some questioning by the local priest, I spoke at the Catholic Central High School. I would like to visit and speak in Butte, Helena, Billings, Deer Lodge, etc. later.

Once I had thought of living in Denver for a time, but the conservatism of Catholics there does not appeal to me, and there is no especial attraction to that city. I have spoken to pacifists half a dozen times in their homes, and have gone to nearby Boulder to speak to Quakers. Cheyenne is the home of a wonderful woman with a wonderful family: Mrs. Robert Leybourne. I had sold her sister a CW in Phoenix ten years ago, and she had bought one for Mrs. Leybourne, and she had become one of the six subscribers in Wyoming. When I was fasting for 40 days in Washington D.C., and picketing, Mrs. Leybourne thought that if I had been in Cheyenne, I would have been picketing the dedication of the missile base there, the next day, but I couldn’t do it, for I was busy in Washington. Someone ought to do it; maybe she ought to do it. So the next day, she takes her six children, and, four months pregnant with another, and shivering, they ride in their station wagon, saying “Hail Marys” the 30 miles to the missile base, where she parades with a sign saying “Missiles are for Murder.” The cops came, but she didn’t budge. She did not know that some Quakers and pacifists had planned to come there from other parts of the country and picket, and go to jail, so when they came, her home was the headquarters for activities. I visited her and the children—one girl is named Dimity and another Felicity—and I had a meeting of pacifists at her house. She introduced me to the Bishop, who knew of her activities and did not scold her. Her father had been an old time I.W.W. and she is Irish, and I suppose that helps—but she did the thing, while others talked or wrote letters to Washington, D.C.

In Kansas City, Bob Hoyt, of the ill-fated Catholic daily, had me meet friends in a huge, antiquated stone house. These were all liberals, but they were cordial to the CW. In St. Louis, I have spoken several times, as I crossed the country, at the Catholic Center near the University, and always have had spirited meetings. The German influence of state worship is prevalent here, and our anarchist approach is not liked. Minneapolis and St. Paul have long been a center where the CW is popular among priests and students. Radical students at the University always plan a meeting for me; and also at the home of Orin Doty, who was in jail as a CO; and at Maryhouse, where women live together and do charity work. A Baptist College greeted me gladly, but at the same time, the Sisters at a Catholic high school, who had invited me, even when I had been in Sandstone prison, reluctantly had to cancel the meeting, because the priest in control disliked us. The present Bishop in St. Paul denounced the coming of Khrushchev to this country, and does not seem to be as tolerant as his predecessor. The Wanderer is a right-wing Catholic weekly that carried articles denouncing the CW and Dorothy, saying that she had gone to prison in Nevada demonstrating against the atom bomb. None of us went to prison there, and she had no part in that demonstration. I visited with the editor for half an hour and convinced him that, when his paper said “it is rumored that Dorothy Day is a communicant,” he was doing an injustice to a great and noble Catholic. (Later they had a long editorial against Dorothy and me, and our support of the Cuban revolution.) I have spoken three times at St. John’s Seminary, near St. Cloud, and have always had a good response from the students. The reporter in the St. Cloud paper printed an interview with me that showed a great understanding upon such a short acquaintance. J.F. Powers, the short story writer, lives in St. Cloud, and I value visits with him. He and George Collins are the only two Catholics whom I know of that refused to register for the draft in World War II. They did time in Sandstone prison. I spoke at Father Casey’s in Hutcheson, and later at Belle Plaine, and to the parishes of several radical priests in small Minnesota towns. I answered questions to a large group of seminarians at St. Mary’s, in Winona. In Duluth, I met with the Finnish I.W.W. folks, who publish a daily paper. Across into Wisconsin, at Ashland, I was welcomed by a Jewish professor at Northland College, where I spoke to classes, and by John Chapple, a right-wing extremist long before the days of McCarthy, who is a Catholic convert, and friendly to the CW for what might seem odd reasons. We disagreed on Russia but, it seems, had the same enemy: the welfare state.

“Mamma, can that man who was in prison because he didn’t want the world blown up, sleep in my bed?” asked five-year-old Jeffry Lippink in Two Harbors, Minnesota, where I was speaking in their home the second night after my release from Sandstone prison.

“Yes, Mr. Hennacy can sleep in your bed,” mother replied.

“Then I’ll help ’gainst the war, won’t I?” Jeffry answered.

In LaCrosse I had spoken at Viterbo College, in 1954, and at the Methodist Church, where my friend Winslow Wilson was pastor. He was the first one I heard of who refused to register for the draft in 1940. Although he was already exempt as a minister, and his wife was seven months pregnant, he refused to register, and got two years in Sandstone prison. I collected small sums and sent them to his wife. Later, he became a subscriber to the CW, and I have spoken to his folks several times. He is now superintendent of the district in Madison. I treasure knowing him and his fine family. In Milwaukee, I have spoken in journalism classes of Dean O’Sullivan’s, in their library, and across the street at Cardyn Center. Also, at the Newman Club, at what was formerly State Teacher’s College, but is now University of Wisconsin, Milwaukee. Also to small groups in houses, and always to my Communist friends, under the auspices of their leader, Fred Basset Blair. There is not much of a pacifist grouping now among Protestants there, but I spoke to them once, since becoming a Catholic.

Friends in the Ford Foundation wanted us to apply for a grant, saying that we could receive money each year for five years, with no strings. Dorothy wrote, refusing any of their money, as it was “blood money,” being taken from the workers. She remembered the first president of the Ford Local, who was beaten by Ford thugs. Now of course, Ford, and even Rockefeller, are respectable. But the point is, they are not sorry they are a part of the war system and capitalist exploitation. About the same time, a man from Massachusetts wrote that he wanted to send the CW some money, but he was a tax man, and perhaps Hennacy wouldn’t like it. I wrote to him, saying that if St. Peter and St. Andrew had a day off from preaching, they could go back to their old job, which was fishing, but St. Matthew couldn’t go back to his old job—that of being a tax man, for it was wicked. Now, if this man could continue being a tax man, unlike St. Matthew, then he should give his money to the Bishops and St. Vincent de Paul—they were not particular, but we were. If he was sorry he was a tax man, and as a penance wanted to give us something, we would take it. We didn’t get it. I told this to Father George Dunne, a Jesuit, and he said I would make a good Jesuit. And I mentioned it at Marquette, and Dean O’Sullivan said that the Jesuits would have gotten the money.

When Bishop Meyer was in Milwaukee, I was not allowed to speak openly in churches or in societies having a Chaplain; but in 1960, when Bishop Cousins came from Peoria, and was Bishop in Milwaukee, I was allowed to speak both at the Cardyn Center, where I had a meeting for many hours, and at St. Francis Seminary, where I met the President and answered questions from the students for hours.

Of course, in Chicago, Nina Polcyn, of St. Benet’s book store, always welcomes us. I spoke at the University of Chicago, and to Quakers and small radical groups, but not to any churches, or to Catholic colleges. The CW here works closely with other pacifists. The new Bishop in Peoria canceled my meeting as being “too controversial.” I spoke at the Universalist Church. At Notre Dame, I had spoken at the home of Prof. Willis Nutting, and to a small meeting at the University Library, sponsored by Father Leo Ward. In 1960, he had me speak at a larger meeting there, and the next day, to his classes and those of another professor. One student quoted Christ chasing the money changers out of the temple, and wondered what I thought about it. I said that if He came back here, He sure would upset some of the plush around here. I was pleased to meet Prof. O’Brien, head of the teaching of courses in criminology. He had formerly been head of all the prisons in Indiana. We did not disagree as much as one might think. In Bloomington, some students had me speak at a luncheon, informally. Someone at the next table heard part of my conversation, and gave a garbled account of it next day in the college paper.

I had been through Indianapolis many times but did not know anyone there, until a young priest from Purdue had me speak at Marian College to several classes of students. All of the priests I met were cordial except one, who said he would not have allowed me in his diocese if he were Bishop. He said that a true Catholic should obey his Bishop, who was “Christ on earth,” regarding a “just” war, and even if the Bishop was wrong, the sin would be upon the Bishop and not upon the one who took error as being truth. I had not heard this echo from the Middle Ages for some time.

At Joe Zarella’s, in Tell City, Ind., I met cordial priests from St. Meinrad’s. At Purdue University, I had as fine a welcome as I have received from a Newman Club. Here three young priests work with the students. At a Communion breakfast, and later with a tape recording for the local radio, I was able to help their fine young folks realize something about “Christ the revolutionist.”

In my home state of Ohio, I am always busy speaking to colleges. Antioch College is radical, and at my first visit, the Catholic priest in the town was very cordial. My meeting with the students here is always interesting, for they are intelligent and full of questions. The Catholic students have had the idea of fighting Communists without knowing what it is all about. I met with them alone. The College Record said, “Whether his doctrines are right is largely immaterial. But the man is right, and therefore dangerous, because of the way he treats his opinions. He makes issues out of them. He heckles bureaucrats. … For all I know, Hennacy may have found a teammate or two this weekend. At any rate, if President Gould meant what he said last fall—‘let me say as strongly as I know how that there are no subversive activities at Antioch,’ then somebody outfoxed the President. Tartly candid, unreconstructed Ammon Hennacy is a subversive activity. And his subversiveness is both impossible and disreputable for a court or prison to combat, let alone a college …”

I spoke at Oberlin College to a large meeting. Forty years before, I had put out anti-draft literature on their campus. I have always been welcome at the Grail, where these fine girls learn the homemaking arts. In Columbus, my especial friend is Dr. Wm. Mitchell, who founded a home for spastics, later turning it over to an Order. He had me speak to them, and introduced me around the Chancery office. The Bishop was away that day. The good Doctor had written and published booklets at his own expense favoring McCarthy, and had come to the CW giving us money for helping the poor “but not for that radical Hennacy.” I became acquainted with him and, although we disagree on some things, we each appreciate the integrity of the other. On the 5th of April, 1947, I spoke to the Newman Club at Ohio State University, there. This was exactly 40 years from the night I had been arrested for opposing World War I. In Cleveland, I spoke at the Unitarian Church, one night, while a meeting of Gov. de Salle’s Democrats was supposed to be going on, but they were late, so the Democrats came in and wanted to know what this “anarchist-no-voting” meant.

I have spoken to Father Hugo in Pittsburgh several times on the phone, but have never met him. Now that my friend Bishop Wright is in Pittsburgh, I hope to visit that city more and more. In Philadelphia, I have spoken several times to the Quaker colleges, and at Pendle Hill. Also, to a coffee house of my friend Bill Basnight. At the Christian Brothers’ La Salle College, I was introduced to a huge meeting of students by the Brother who said, “This man has been cleared; this man has been cleared.” The students had signs like at a political convention saying “Welcome Ammon Hennacy.” They asked stimulating questions for hours, afterwards. That night, I met with professors and friends until 2 a.m., among them John Stokes, former conscientious objector, and now a wealthy manufacturer and Catholic convert. Later, I spoke to his conservative Catholic friends at his home. He has developed Mary’s Gardens, offering seeds and flowers named for Our Lady.

In Washington D.C., I spoke to St. Peter Claver House, and to small groups of students attending Catholic University, friends of Peggy Reeves. In Lancaster, Pa., I spoke twice, being invited by Kitty Shenk, a former Catholic, but now a Unitarian, who had me speak at her church, and to Catholic groups; and also to the Evangelical and Reformed Seminary. The college paper said the next day: “Anarchist fascinates, bewilders.” I also played Hopi records and spoke to the children of the “hook and eye” Amish in their school. They looked at me, puzzled, for their founder was Jacob Ammon. Friends in the local York paper had me speak to Catholics and others there. One stormy night, I spoke to students at the Lutheran Muhlenberg College at Allentown, Pa.; and another time, at Drew University in New Jersey. I spoke to the Newman Club and to an economics seminar at Rutgers before being invited to speak at an assembly, dressed in a gown. I spoke at Cornell, but the Catholics were abashed at my radicalism, the other students being more cordial. In Rochester, at the CW house, I spoke to small groups several times.

In Canada, I visited for a few days with Tony Walsh, at his Labre House in Montreal, and was introduced by Murray Ballantine when I spoke. I become acquainted with Karl Stern, the psychiatrist, whose book Pillar of Fire I had read years before I became a Catholic. In it, he said that when he joined the Church, he brought with him “all that was good from Gandhi and Tolstoy.” I also visited the Little Sisters of Charles de Foucauld, who work in factories and live among the poor. Later I met women of their group in Chicago and Washington, D.C. They are not as radical as we are, but they understand and are sympathetic. I spoke to a small meeting of the Newman Club at McGill University, staying at the home of a Quaker, David Kirk, whose wife had the same great-great-—grandfather as I on my mother’s side. They have adopted several children of varying nationalities. Going on to Combermere, I visited a day at Catherine De Heuck’s headquarters, and spoke to those living there. A young Belgian seminarian invited me to speak to the White Fathers in Ottawa. They are missionaries who work in North Africa. I was surprised to receive a letter from the Father in charge, later, appreciating my visit, for I had not thought that my extreme radicalism would go over there. Later, the young Belgian, now a priest, stopped at the CW on the way to his field. The next day, I spoke to students at the University Seminary in Ottawa, and this being the Pope’s birthday, they had the day off, so I was busy answering questions every minute.

In Sudbury, Ontario, I was guest of Vicky Smits, a young housewife who emigrated with her husband Joe Holland nine years ago. Joe works at the Frood-Stoble unit, where he blasts 700 tons every eight hours. The shoemaker says there is nothing like leather. Here, the nickel center of the world, there is nothing like nickel. The big name there is INCO (International Nickel Company of Canada.) Another name that also looms big on the horizon of Sudbury Basin, of the 130,000 acres where John Foster Dulles was once Chairman of the Board of INCO, is Local 598 of the Mine, Mill, and Smelter Workers, established in 1943 after a score of years of lockouts and violence, and now numbering 14,000 workers. There are at least thirty nationalities in this growing town, which is not far from the uranium mines at Blind River and the gold mines at Virginia. In this latter town, until recently, native-born Canadians received the highest wage, then immigrants, then Indians, all doing the same work. When the union convention was held in Sudbury, recently, the Chamber of Commerce aroused dissident racial minorities against “the Commie union” and picketed the union hall. My hostess, Vicki, picketed the pickets with a sign: “Our Leaders are Tops.”

My visit was complicated somewhat by the situation of 70% of the members of this left-wing union being Catholic, and of the opposition to the union from all the clergy, both Catholic and Protestant. Vicki had planned my schedule, as she had lived in different parishes and knew several priests. First I spoke to a group of men employed by INCO who were anti-Communist, at St. Anne’s Church. Father Regimbault there disliked both capitalism and communism, and like Father Murphy and Father Kaptean, with whom I spoke later, believed in unions. That night, and at a Communion breakfast on St. Patrick’s Day at the same Church where I answered questions for hours, it was difficult for them to gain an understanding of the pacifist anarchist ideal, as they had the idea that anarchists and radicals acted like a goon-squad from Mine Mill that had beaten up a Steelworker organizer brought in to rival Mine Mill. I tried to bring the message that, as the Quakers reply to the assertion that you can’t trust Communists: “No one said we should trust Communists, for we should trust God and love the Communists.” I tried to arrange a meeting between priests and the heads of the Mine Mill. The union men were willing, but the priests would not talk to nonbelievers. The clergy had tried to prevent the showing of Salt of the Earth, the story of a strike at Silver City, N.M., and had told Catholics that they could not receive Communion if they sent their children to the summer camp of the union. The Church did not provide any summer camp for the children in this desolate area, where the copper fumes kill nearly all vegetation. I visited the camp with Weir Reed, the camp director.

On a tour of the smelter at Copper Cliff, I saw as much as a visitor is permitted to see: the mixing ore and its roasting in the gas oven. The fumes did not allow us to go very near the room where the refuse was being skimmed off, or near the kilns where men entered to clean out the accumulated sooty refuse. The guide said that his brother had refused to go in a kiln when it was too hot, for he had already had an ear burned, but the foreman went in, and to escape the heat had madly rushed out and fallen several stories, and was killed. Helmets, boots with steel over the toes, aprons and gloves, and gas masks cannot always prevent a splash of metal from injuring workers. Some mining is a mile underground.

I was in Arizona when Salt of the Earth was being filmed at Silver City, N.M., and I sent money to help the women pickets. The injunction was against the men, so the women picketed, and finally won the strike. The film was not allowed a public showing in most of the U.S., so I despaired of seeing it. Reid ran the picture, with me as an audience of one. Jencks, who played an important part in the film, is currently being hounded by the authorities, not because he may have signed a non-Communist affidavit falsely, but because he put up such a great fight against those who make wars and profit out of wars. The picture showed that it was radicals who were brave enough to be beaten up and to organize unions when the going was hard. I spoke to a meeting of the union, where I met old time I.W.W.’s. To both Communist and Catholic audiences I say, “In Russia and the Iron Curtain Countries the enemy of the free worker is the bureaucrat and the Communist; in this country the enemy of the worker is the bureaucrat and the capitalist.” I spoke also to a group of women, the auxiliary of the local Lions Club, and to enthusiastic students at Sacred Heart College.

Speaking Tour 1961

Leaving New York City, January 2nd, I spoke to a group at the Catholic University of America, gathered together by Father Robert Hovda. I visited with my friend Bob Hoyt, of the Knight newspapers. He attended the new Catholic Church at McLean, Va., built like that in Holyoke, Mass., in a circular manner, with built-in, plate glass, soundproof rooms for women with crying babies … the priest here, along with most I met in or near Washington, was not a bit interested in social problems, least of all in my radical approach to them. Bob’s young boy had been told about my being a vegetarian and working a garden the year around in Arizona, and proudly showed me some plants he had set out in their small garden.

Several times, when I had been fasting in and around Washington, D.C., I had my last meal with Bob and his boss, Ed Leahy. This consisted of onion soup, in the National Press Club restaurant. Ed had written up episodes of my argument with the tax man in the string of Knight newspapers over the country, stressing in a humorous way that I was still fighting windmills, and the tax man did not seem to know what to do about it! “The Bureau of Internal Revenue in Washington doesn’t like to be asked about Hennacy. A spokesman declares that the case of the Phoenix non-taxpayer has not come to their attention at the main office. But if Hennacy’s writing arm holds out, they’re going to have to put him on the docket eventually.”

I had a standing-room-only session at the big Unitarian Church across from the Mormon Church, and met with a small group of pacifists also. I also met with some AFL-CIO officials, and was glad to meet I.F. Stone, whose dynamic weekly debunks much that goés on in this city of politicians. I always visit Stewart Udall and some of his liberal Democratic Congressman friends; Senator Gene McCarthy; and Ed Leahy and Bob Hoyt, of the Knight Newspapers.

A lively group connected with Rev. Ballard’s Naturalist Vegetarian Church in Baltimore was something new for me. Then I went to Philadelphia and addressed a Quaker Day School, after which Patricia Rusk drove me back to Baltimore for a small meeting at Goucher College. An exceedingly interesting meeting at St. Johns University at Annapolis showed me that I should have planned a stay of two days there in order to answer all of the questions propounded by those freewheeling minds. A teacher drove me hurriedly to Woodstock Seminary where the seminarian Czyparek, our friend from New York City, tramped with me to a cabin in the woods, where, before a huge fire of logs, we discussed radical ideas for hours. It had taken several years of speaking a few words, as I was selling CWs at 14th Street, before this seminarian finally became an enthusiastic CW fan.

Mike Strasser obligingly met me at 4 a.m. at the bus in Pittsburgh, and I spoke to a group where Eddie Egan teaches philosophy in a Catholic school. Father Rice, who picketed with us in the Depression, spoke to me on the phone, and the priests at St. Vincents at Latrobe came and got me for a large meeting. One student had made a bet that he could get me angry, so when the time for questions came, he insulted me and dared me to hit him. I told him to come up and strike the first blow and then I would turn my cheek for the second blow. Later we were good friends, when he told me of the wager. Their school paper had a good writeup of the meeting.

Russ Gibbons, secretary of a national group of Catholics interested in civil liberties, had planned meetings for me at Rosary Hill College, to a Newman Club at another college and to the Knights of Columbus in the suburb of Hamburg. I was challenged by questions from many who had never heard the radical message before. Nicole d’Entremont gave a very good account of my ideas in their paper Ascent. And at the K of C meeting, the head of the Democratic party in Buffalo, an Irishman by the name of Crotty, exchanged witticisms with me, in all good humor.

I had been invited by a student to speak at one of the two seminaries in the world established by the Popes, the one in Worthington, Ohio, outside of Columbus, but some minor official there became frightened and cancelled it. The student appealed to the head priest, and he knew of the CW, and said it would be good to liven them up with a few unorthodox ideas. I never saw so many red sashes outside of a May Day parade. I told them that there was little opportunity in their closed world for them to know what was going on. That I was part of a revolutionary movement like that of the early Christians, and that God had sent me to make sure that they didn’t go asleep on their job. That what I said was going to get worse, so they had better play sick and leave if they couldn’t take it. Although the questions are nearly always the same, as given in my chapter on questions and answers, they came fast and furious at this meeting. Dr. Bill Mitchell, my McCarthyite friend from Columbus, took me to his home after the meeting.

In Chillicothe I visited my old time friends where they now lived on a farm. Two priests of the Glenmary Order of Home missioners, who had corresponded with me, came over for the evening and invited me to speak to their Order near Cincinnati, where also some nuns came to the meeting. Then I had a day in Portsmouth with my old pal of Atlanta prison days, Fr. John Dunn, and went on to Cincinnati, where I visited my brother Frank and spoke to a meeting of Quakers and Peacemakers. I was glad to see my friend Maurice McCracken again, who had been deposed from his Presbyterian ministry for not paying taxes for war. And, of course, Ernie Bromley and family, leading Peacemakers. A new group of girls were at the Grail, where I spoke to them at length.

I have always found a welcome at Antioch College, and visited at the home of a pacifist who refused to pay his income tax, so his $9,000 home was sold by the tax man for the around $500 tax that he owed. No one else bid on his house, so he bought it back, and of course paid the taxes. Earlham College, at Richmond, Ind., had invited me to speak, but cancelled the meeting. This is a Quaker College that has R.O.T.C., so I did not expect much from them. I arrived at Purdue in the midst of exams, so only met a few students, and had a meeting at the home of a Catholic family. Fr. Frazee, at Marian College in Indianapolis, greeted me gladly, and I answered questions practically all day as the students crowded around. One student had heard me answer the same question three times, so the fourth time it came up, he answered it boldly before I could get a word in. The Athletic coach wanted me to tell the teachers at the table at lunch about my fasting and being a vegetarian. He said he had a difficult time getting them to walk short distances, rather than riding in cars. Again, in Milwaukee, I spoke at Marquette University and to the Cardyn Center nearby, and visited many old time friends. And of course, at the Catholic Center at the University in Madison I am always welcome. Likewise, at the University of Minnesota; and at the homes of pacifists I had interesting meetings.

I arrived at midnight in Winnipeg, and was met by a young Catholic who put me up at a downtown hotel. This is the only city in North America where the Communists have members of the City Council and the school board. In these Provinces, the government furnishes the buildings near the regular University for the Catholics and for the Church of England, and they pay a small token rent and teach their religion, philosophy, etc. They make no effort to compete with the regular College in the physical sciences. I was busy all day with meetings. Father Forsythe drove me downtown to the Communist Party headquarters, where I introduced myself. A young Communist vegetarian was eating his lunch and invited me to eat with him. Later I met the Communist officials, and told them of the CW.

Parochial Schools

This reminds me of the whole idea of aid to parochial schools here in the United States, where there is supposed to be a separation of Church and State. When Al Smith ran for President, he said, but to little avail, that he believed in the Catholics running their own schools without the help of the state. President Kennedy ran on the same platform. Until his election, the National Catholic Welfare Conference, the spokesman for the Church, did not have the nerve to come out and ask for money from the state. It is well known that, outside of Cardinal Cushing, most of the hierarchy are so conservative that they would rather have a wishy-washy man like Nixon as President, than a liberal. And it was this kind of Catholic in Congress who killed the President’s effort to help the public schools. Catholics say that it is unfair for them to pay taxes for public schools and then pay for their own parochial schools. This is no more unfair than to make a bachelor to support big families of children. Nor than here in Utah, where no Mormon in good standing is on relief, for the Mormon Church takes care of their own; Mormons pay a tithe for this and also taxes to feed the Gentiles. If Catholics would lay off their gambling, drinking, and smoking they could have enough to run their schools. The following is from Time magazine of August 25, 1961:

Msgr. George W. Casey, 65, is a Boston Irish Catholic who looks on the folklore of Boston Irish Catholics just about the way that a small boy with a pin looks on a cluster of balloons. In his lively column for the Pilot, weekly newspaper of the Boston archdiocese, Father Casey has lampooned South Boston’s “convivial, congenital, incurable” Irish for boozing it up on St. Patrick’s Day, criticized parish priests for being “tyrants,” and even suggested that nuns wear modern clothes—all to howls of Hibernian protest.

Last week, Columnist Casey’s latest shock was front-page news in Boston. He blandly urged U.S. Catholics to abandon parochial grade schools and concentrate instead on high schools and colleges. “Since it is quite clear by now that Catholic schools are not going to get any financial aid from the federal government.” Father Casey argued, “We should move our resources to the front of greatest challenge.” Casey challenged the assumption that primary grades are the best time and place to carry out the chief mission of Catholic schools, “preservation of the faith.” While “neatness, sanitation, table, manners and so on can be ingrained in these early years, it is not evident that doctrine and abstract ideas can be.” More important are the crucial years of high school: “Let us have priests and the Sisters around in the grades where boy meets girl, and where both meet the Reformation, the Inquisition, Communism, Darwinism, Freudianism, and all the other religions and philosophies. They are much more needed there than where the boys and girls meet spelling, times tables, and long division.”

Sending Catholic children to public schools, argued Casey, will help “avoid most of the less pleasant byproducts of separation and inbreeding.” Moreover, “we will all be relieved of the financial strain that so distorts our devotions and parish programs. The parishes will not have to erect the enormous bingo signs that disfigure all the church lawns in certain areas, or run a lot of novenas for palpably profit motives. Sunday Mass will not take on the quality of a fly trap designed to hold the people until three collections are taken up.”

In Saskatoon, the Catholic lady with whom I had corresponded for years had to be out of town for some weeks, so my contract was with the Doukhobors. Koozma Tarasoff had visited Russia and asked a Greek Orthodox priest about conscientious objectors and received the reply that he didn’t know anything about them, and besides, all Christians should fight for their country. He had met some Doukhobors who had picketed against militarism and had been sent to Siberia for a year. When they returned they lived in a colony with other Doukhobors. The understanding being, with the government, that if they kept by themselves they would not be bothered for military service. They told Koozma that they would like some of the “wild” Doukhobors of Canada to come and picket, and go to jail, and liven them up. My friend A.J. Muste met Baptist pacifists who had done alternative service in Moscow. How many were killed during the Stalin regime, there is no means of knowing.

Here, in the vicinity of Saskatoon, thousands of Doukhobors lived in the early 1900s. They were persecuted, and many fled to British Columbia. Now thousands of them live in a prosperous manner, own individual farms, sing their songs, and practice their religion, which might be described as similar to pacifist Unitarians, but with the Russian tradition. I spoke at an annual dinner they had, and happened to sit next to a young couple who lived up to the non-smoking, vegetarian ideal of the early Doukhobors. Outside of my talk, which was revolutionary, the tone seemed to be to be a part of the Canadian culture. I also spoke at a meeting in one of the Doukhobor meeting houses, where the older folks came on a Sunday afternoon. I addressed a meeting of liberals on pacifism and anarchism, and had a small meeting with students at the University. Koozma is now married and lives in Vancouver, and has written a 1,000 page book on the history of the Doukhobors. He is getting his M.A. degree there.

In Edmonton, Prof. Rose of the English Department welcomed me, and he had planned with the Christian Student Council to sponsor meetings which were well attended; and good reports in the Gateway, the student paper, followed, especially one by Bentley LeBaron who analyzed my ideas as (1) individualism, (2) intelligence, (3) spiritual power, (4) pacifism, describing my ideas more coherently than I did, I expect. I also spoke at the Unitarian Church. Looking at the map, it is not so far to Fairbanks, Alaska, and sometime I hope to be invited to speak there. I had corresponded with Jim Milord, who teaches at Hobbema, on an Indian Reservation fifty miles south of Edmonton, so I was glad to spend a couple of days with him and his charming family. These Indians have oil royalties which have demoralized them. I listened to a speech contest, and made friends with a young health-minded Indian boy.

I spent a week with Helen Demoskoff, Pete Maloff, and other Doukhobor friends. I visited Doukhobors in Grand Forks, where a Russian paper is printed, and was greeted kindly by the editor, who reads the CW.

In Spokane, my friend Brother Martinat, at his House of Charity, took me 35 miles to the top of a mountain which a Catholic Msgr. had bought for him, this being a 500-acre tract where alcoholics from the city could build shacks, raise their food, and be so far away from a saloon that they stood a chance of reforming. We tramped for half a day midst magnificent pines, over streams, and to the high plateau where there is room for 100 cabins or more. In this society, that is the only way to help the alcoholic, for if he is in the midst of temptation, he will generally succumb, and drag down with him his weak friends. I spoke to a whole gymnasium full of boys who were anxious to get out and play. I only had fifteen minutes, but I made one of the best speeches of my life. I suppose it was the challenge of these kids, and the short time at hand, that made me do my best. Due to a misunderstanding, I was not able to make the meeting at Carroll College, at Helena.

Salt Lake City

Arriving here on April 6th. I thought I would look around and see what the prospects might be for work when I came back in May. I went on the bus a few miles north to the town of Bountiful, but found very few people at home. Then I realized that this was the 131st anniversary of the founding of the Mormon Church, and that most people were at the semiannual conference in Salt Lake City. I got a few leads for work, later, and after three hours of knocking on doors, I came to the Stake Farm, where Mormons in that vicinity produced milk for the needy. I asked if there was any work I could do, and I was put to work digging post holes and setting posts for the next seven hours. Men were coming and going, putting in as much time as they had in repairing a chicken house. A young married woman lived in a cottage. Her husband had lost his job because of illness, and so he was employed at a nominal wage on the farm, and the rent was charged up to them, to be paid when he got regular work. I spoke later to the wife of the farm manager, and she was very critical of high-up Mormons. She told me of a “good Mormon” up the road, whom I contacted when my work was done. He had a chicken ranch and cherry orchard, and told me if I was back here in cherry picking time, he would have work for me. He had gone away from Mormon country, when he was young, for 15 years, but now was back for good. He had seen the world, and did not think much of it. In May, Mary and I were taken by a contractor to pick cherries at his place, and I was glad to meet him again. Prof. Wormuth, of the Political Science Department at the University, whom I had met while selling CWs at the New School in New York City a few years before, invited me to speak to his class. He told me that, of the 50 students, all were Mormons but three. I told them of being bothered by the KKK when teaching in Alabama; that there were three sides to a question: your side, my side, and the right side; and kidded them about the Mormons giving up polygamy in 1890 when it cost them money. I had a barrage of questions, and, to my surprise, half a dozen young men came up and thanked me for opening up new ideas to them. The next day, Bishop Neal Maxwell, of the Mormon Church, who had been in the room and heard me, asked me to tape a record, for his television program, of all of my radical ideas. I said that surely he did not want all this radicalism, and he replied that Mormons were supposed to search for the truth, and if I had more or less of it, it would be good for the students. The tape was played later, twice, when I was in New York City. I bought a typewriter and work clothes, stored them with a pacifist friend, and hurried back to New York City, to perhaps be arrested for refusing, for the seventh time, to take part in the air raid drill; but, as related elsewhere, I was not arrested.

Chapter 16

In the Marketplace

New York City

1953–1961

Tom Sullivan, associate editor of the CW, gave the above title to my activities on the streets of New York City. As a salesman I understand the value of being at the same place at the same time with the same article for sale, and not to jump around, or have a perpetual “gone to lunch sign” in your window. There is another thing that I have learned which is that the wider the sidewalk where you are standing the less likely it is that anyone will break through the line of moving people and buy from you. Also if people are burdened with shopping packages they are not likely to put them down and buy a paper. Also if people are rushing to make a subway to get home they would not take five dollar bills if someone was handing them out. If there are four people selling one block apart they will sell more than if scattered.

During the Fall and Spring season there are free lectures on Monday night at Cooper Union, and from 9:45 to 10:45 as many as 2,000 people may emerge. It is true that many just go in there to get warm. In 1920 Mrs. J. Sargent Cram of Peace House, a wealthy pacifist, and a descendent of Peter Cooper, had planned a meeting where Senator Borah would speak. He was three quarters of an hour late and she asked me to get up and talk until he came. I can’t remember what I said but I held the crowd. Students and “Bowery philosophers” often interrogate me as I am selling CWs there and we go to the all night restaurant across the Bowery and discuss radicalism. One person cannot take care of such a crowd, so Patricia Rusk helped me for a time and others around the CW came along. Once we met a seminarian who had formerly been in the army and who said that he could love the enemy and kill him at the same time. Theological discussion had gone on for a long time when Pat looked up at the seminarian and innocently said, “You say this to me now, and you tell this to God when you die.” That was the end of the conversation.

Tuesday from noon until 2 p.m. I hold forth at Pine and Nassau, a block north of Wall and Broad where I formerly soapboxed. This is a narrow corner and Catholics coming to and from Our Lady of Victory Church two blocks to the east on Pine have an opportunity to know about the CW. A well-dressed man said hello to me, mentioning my name, and I said that I couldn’t remember him.

“Oh you wouldn’t know me. I slept on the floor at your place all one winter and saw you come and go. Booze had dragged me down in the gutter of the Bowery. I had lost my job and family. But with you folks I sobered up, then went to the AA, and now everything is fine.”

I meet people who have heard me speak on the street years ago. Several guards from the banks have bought from me. At times I have had young folks, seminarians, and visitors come down and each one take a corner so that the name “Catholic Worker” resounded. On snowy days I did not sell so many papers. I always have a place handy where I can get warm. The Watchman in one bank chased us, but the others were more cordial. I took friends to see the stock exchange. I suppose it is some old Fenian blood, but I felt an urge when looking over the balcony at the thieves quarreling over their loot, to have a bag of feathers and throw them all over the place, as one pacifist from Kansas did twice among the Congressmen in Washington, D.C. “First time I ever bought a paper from the editor of a paper,” said a customer to me.

9:45 to 10:30 p.m. Tuesdays at New School, 12th St. near 6th Ave. Very few Catholics attend this liberal school of adult education but I have many friends there who tell others about the CW. They accepted my book in their library. One night a cab driver waiting for his “fare” who was at the school said, “There’s a guy in there talking against you folks, name of Blanshard.” I didn’t believe him, but in a few minutes a man whom I knew by his moustache was Paul Blanshard, the professional anti-Catholic, came out.

“Have a Catholic Worker, Mr. Blanshard,” I said handing him one.

“How much?” he asked.

“Nothing, you need it bad,” was my reply. He gave me a nickel.

A man who had known Vachel Lindsay in the old days talked with me for a few minutes, and when he heard that I had attended Hiram College he was glad to know that I quoted my favorite poem of his to the students often: The Leaden-Eyed. The Village Voice had a picure of me selling CWs there, and later when I was in Sandstone prison they said I was not able to sell CWs for a time and folks had better subscribe for the CW as they were missing something good.

Wednesday from noon to 4:30 at Fordham University Uptown 190th St. This is about the noisiest place in New York City, what with the elevated, the Boston Post Road whizzing by with trucks, and students running like mad to make a train. In many other campuses there are a dozen places where students come and go, but here you can get them all at once as they come out. One student liked Eichenberg’s drawing of the six workers and bought 300 CWs in order to send them as Christmas Greetings to his friends. I have met hundreds of nuns and priests from over the country who are visiting or going to school at Fordham. And every day many students ask me questions about CW ideas. And in traveling over the country speaking, priests who have met me when they were seminarians at Fordham will tell of the cold days when we both shivered in the wind, they as they came down the quarter of mile walk to the street, and I as I buffeted the wind on the street. One priest was talking to me and later that day he told me that his superior had noticed us together and had said, “Don’t encourage that Hennacy, for after a student hears him it takes five years to get him back in the groove.”

14th Street and Broadway, Thursday, 6 to 8 p.m. (and for years noon to 2 p.m. but in 1960 picketing Woolworth’s at that time.) This is a cosmopolitan place where you meet every kind of person. It is also a very noisy place, and very windy. Competition here is great, for two or three street merchants will be shouting their wares and looking for a cop, for they are not allowed to do business without a license, and the city will not give them a license. I have witnessed one fellow selling toys get pinched four times in two hours, but he kept right on selling. I have made many valuable contacts here.

“Give me a dime. The fellow down the street says for you to give me a dime,” said a short fellow with a string tie. I gave him one.

“Make it a quarter,” he said cheerfully, and like a rabbit before a snake I was charmed and handed it over. A few weeks later he came into our office and said to Dorothy, “Here is $2. Ammon loaned me 35¢ recently.”

Drunks who hate Catholics, and sober people who despise us, call me “Communist” and say they are going to call the FBI. Spanish Priests who are Fascists hurry by not looking my way. One pious woman had just come from Mass and wanted to know if the CW had an imprimatur. I told her that only diocesion or Order papers had an imprimatur, and that there were many papers printed by lay people. “Ask a priest about us; here comes one,” and I turned to see our own Father McCoy whom I had never met down this way before. He of course told her we were the best.

43rd and Broadway, Friday noon until 2 p.m. enormous crowds pass by here. I am really part of the pillar by the Peerless store, so am not pushed around by the crowd. A young man told me that I had a kind face and that I must be a very good man. I told him that I was not a “goody-goody” but I aim to do the best I could, and not the second best.

“I’m in such a fix that any way I turn I am in a fix. I know if you would say a prayer for me it would help.”

“What’s your name?” I asked.

“Jimmy,” he answered.

“Alright, I’ll pray for you at Mass each morning,” was my reply.

Going home I stopped at a market to get some yogurt for a friend and the manager came running out shouting, “What did you steal. Let me search you. You look like a crook. My man saw you stealing something.”

I told him to search me and he did so but found nothing. How am I going to please the public? One man wants me to pray for him, and another thinks I am a crook. A year later Jimmy greeted me, “Better keep on praying Hennacy, I’m just making it by the ragged edge.”

I am always telling success stories but there is once that I had to admit defeat. A tall Irish drunk came up and asked me if the CW had an imprimatur. I told him it didn’t need to have one. Somehow in his befuddled mind he though I must not be a good Catholic if I sold a paper not formally approved by the Church. So he said give me some, and took a dozen and commenced to shout: “Catholic Worker, free copy. No imprimatur.” And pointing to me he added, “Don’t buy from this jerk.” I couldn’t argue with a drunk man and I do not believe in calling a cop. I thought he would tame down, but he kept on for about ten minutes and no one took a free copy from him, those who knew me took papers and paid me for them. I got tired of this and thought if I walked quickly around the block I might lose him. Half way down the block as I neared St. Agnes he caught up with me and whispered in my ear: “I am your persecutor! I am your persecutor!”

I walked faster around the block and looking back did not see him. I stopped in a restaurant for a cup of coffee, but before it was served he was beside me saying again, “I am you persecutor!” and he handed a copy of the CW to the waitress saying, “Free copy; no imprimatur.” I walked out and back to 43rd and he followed me. I had 15 minutes yet before quitting time, but I was defeated, and I went home. I never saw him again.

A lady coming from Church wanted to know if the Church supported the CW and I told her it was not for us or against us, and to ask some priest about it. Just then I saw a priest walking our way and I said, “Ask him.” And again it was our friend Father McCoy who was on hand to reassure the good woman that the CW was good for her soul.

At times I wear sandals that friends give me. A kind old man saw me thus attired and said that he would come back and bring me a pair of shoes that he thought would fit me. I thanked him and said that I had shoes at home. Several times innocent Catholics who hear the name Catholic as I shout will stop and buy a paper and say “God bless you. I am glad to see someone besides a Jehovah’s Witness on the streets selling papers.” Yet at other times Catholics will say it gives the Church a bad name to be out on the street. At times Protestant ministers, seminarians, and even high school students such as 16-year-old Judy Shafer, who played hookey from school for the aid raid demonstration, will stop and help me sell CWs.

A Jewish man who often buys a paper from me here told me of his eight-year-old boy who was showing a neighboring Irish boy how to hold a bat. This boy did not want to be shown and said, “You can’t show me anything, you dirty Jew!” In a sober and innocent manner the Jewish boy replied, “You have committed a mortal sin.”

“Why don’t you get a job?” asked a kindly elderly man.

“I don’t need any,“ I replied, “for I work for my keep at the CW.”

“I’m a retired policeman with a pension, and I make $65 a week on an easy job.”

“We believe in living poor near the Bowery,” I told him.

“I am happy and I want you to be happy and have a job too,” was his rejoinder.

I told him to read the CW and see how we could be happy without bosses. He wanted to know how much the paper cost. I advised it was a penny and he replied that he didn’t have any money on him, so I said to read it and pay me next time. I never saw him again. An Irish woman bought four of my books and offered me an Irish sweepstakes ticket for free. I told her that I did not believe in gambling, bingo, chances on Pontiacs, etc. for this was the something-for-nothing idea that was the basis of exploitation and slavery. An atheist stopped and said that the Catholic Church was the source of more evil in the world than any other institution. He did not call the Church the Whore of Babylon as fundamentalist Protestants call Catholics. I believe in putting my worst foot forward, and after that my best foot, so I replied: “Sure, compared to the good it is supposed to do, the Catholic Church is the cause of much evil, by watering down the Sermon on the Mount, by justifying wars and exploitation, by ransoming slaves but seldom opposing slavery; by insisting on married people living together midst fighting, malice and hatred, and the Jansenist idea on sex: expecting men and women to live together in ‘self-control’ when this advice often comes from the mouths of clergy who never could be accused of any self-control in eating and drinking. I suppose if all this accumulated misery was on one scale it might seem to out balance the good that the lives of saintly nuns and priests do in consoling the wife of a drunkard, the mother of wayward children, the man yoked for life with a termigant, the nursing of the sick, and all the works of mercy. The Church as a whole, as Monsignor Guardini has said, is the Cross on which Christ is crucified, for in His name they deny Him, but yet through the Church comes a St. Joan and a St. Francis of Assisi and all the saints down through the ages. So while only God knows how the scales balance, I would venture that there is more good than evil.”

St. Patrick’s Cathedral, 8 to 10 a.m. Sundays. I am across the street, for the people seem to come out in a flutter or in a daze. Many pass me by but I do meet folks from all over the world who know of the CW, and others who are surprised to learn about us. The priests never bothered me here but I have had to educate a few cops as to this being a free country. On very cold days I have a few friends who invite me for a cup of tea after 10 a.m. The parades, swinging of flags, playing of Star Spangled Banner and Onward Christian Soldiers, and the visiting dignitaries, and the whole spirit of obeisance to Mammon makes this an odd place for a radical. I did go to Mass there at 8 a.m. for years, generally being one of the first to take Communion in order to get out and sell CWs. Once the priest handed me the paten and I officiated as his server for twenty minutes before Cardinal Spellman and the Cardinal from Australia who was visiting. (This ought to get me inside the pearly gates.)

St. Francis of Assisi, near Penn Station, 11 a.m. to 1:30 Sunday. From 1954 through 1958 I sold CWs here. One priest who acted more like a cop than a priest shouted at me and Pat or whoever was helping me sell CWs to get away. I was to the side of the entrance and would have moved down aways if asked to do so in a civil manner. The priest said he would call a cop and I told him to do so. I showed the cop the Supreme Court decision as to my right and he said I had the right to sell the CW any place, but suggested that as we were all Catholics and for the sake of peace would I move down a bit. I told him that out of courtesy to the Church I would move down, and I did. Again a visiting missionary priest said I was not allowed to sell the CW in N.Y. City, and that he would call a cop if I didn’t go. I told him this had been tried before, and if he didn’t believe it to ask inside. He didn’t bother me again. For the past two years I have been attending the 10:30 Uniate Byzantine Rite at St. Michaels Mass back of old St. Patricks, near us on Mulberry Street. I like the singing, which is done more by Irish than Russians. The Czar could be blessed for all I understand it but the sermons are honestly religious and no political propaganda against the Communists and for capitalism.

Julie Lien, a girl from Ohio, was with us for a time and helped me give out CWs once a month at the National Maritime Union. Finally their goon squad came and chased us. One of them grabbed her papers and she took them back and sweetly said, “One at a time, Mister,” as she gave him a CW. We had fed these men in 1936 at the time of the waterfront strike and had been thanked by their leader, but now the line is to make a bargain with capitalism. I have enough to do fighting ordinary cops and the State, so I left this labor front.

Chapter 17

Communities

1921–1963

All Over the U.S. and Canada

The Amish

The Amish are an offshoot of the Mennonites, from the 18th century in the Palatinate in Europe, led by Jacob Ammon. For over 150 years, they have developed the farm land in Pennsylvania, until it is the most valuable in the country. My friend Vincent Tortora, a Catholic who has written about the Amish, drove me through the Amish country here around Lancaster, Pa. where, over the rolling fields, I saw the Amish farmers plowing and harrowing with horses and mules. You knew the “House” Amish because they had windmills and no wires, or telephones, or electricity, and no tractors in the yard. They are so called because they have prayer meetings and services in their homes instead of in churches. The “Church” Amish have churches, and use tractors and automobiles, and perhaps have a telephone and electricity. Another name for the “House” Amish is “hook and eye” Amish, because they use no buttons and are very strict. Tradition says that in Germany, in the old days, the most conspicuous point of attire of a soldier was his brass buttons, so they used no buttons in protest. All these Amish vote and pay taxes, and mostly are allowed by the government to stay and work on their farms instead of going to war. To them, the outside world is called “gay,” as the Gypsies call the outside world, much as the Mormons call all others “Gentiles.” Their children are taught in parochial schools or in public one room schools where the teacher is sympathetic and all the children are Amish. Vincent took me to one such school where he knew the teacher and children. When I was introduced, the children looked at me attentively. I did not realize then, until I saw signs on billboards advertising companies with the name “Ammon,” that my first name stood me in good stead. I played some Hopi records and told them Indian stories. The girls in their blue dresses on one side of the room and the boys in their broad hats and long-cut hair on the other side listened with bright faces to my talk. Lunch time came, and the older girls crowded around Vincent, asking him to bat on their side in the ball game outside. He knocked a homer.

There are 10,000 Amish in and around Lancaster. None of them need sign a note, for they are absolutely honest in business. Some put money in banks, but most of them do not. The Amish have very little heart trouble or tuberculosis. They do not carry insurance, and if a building burns, all the Amish get together and have a “bee,” and the new building is up in a few days. We passed “black-bumpers,” which are cars with the chrome painted over by the Amish, for otherwise they would be thought “gay.” The Amish do not live in town or carry on any business. Dairying and chicken-raising occupy them for long hours each day. Their land grows in value, for they use only natural manure from cattle and horses, and no commercial fertilizers, hence their land is never worn out, but grows deeper topsoil, as generation after generation of these old country Christians continue their culture in our atomic age. The Amish do not go to court in any circumstance. If any one steals from them, they do not report it to the police. Vincent told me of cases where outsiders had reported someone stealing from the Amish, and the judge had given them the limit “for stealing from these good people.”

The Hutterites

Professor Joseph Eaton was coauthor in the December 1953 Scientific American of an article about the Hutterites in South Dakota, Montana, and Canada. These descendants of the Anabaptists in Transylvania had been tortured, robbed, and exiled by Catholic civil authorities and the clergy. (Their founder, Jacob Hutter, was burned at the stake in 1536.) Driven from town to forest, and given sanctuary now and then by some noble, they were driven out again and again. Many recanted, but in 1874, 102 families came to the Dakotas. They were persecuted because of their pacifism in World War I, and the Hofer brothers died in solitary in Alcatraz. I have corresponded with their family in Canada. These brothers were buried in the army uniforms which in life they had refused to wear.

I had corresponded with Professor Eaton, and visited with him for an hour at Western Reserve University in Cleveland. He suggested that I visit the King Colony Ranch near Lewistown, Montana. I wrote to Rev. Joseph Stahl there, and his bearded son Joseph met me at the bus, in the midst of an unusual snow storm on April 30, 1954. He is the manager of this 7,000 acre ranch where 61 Hutterites live, all of them being related, so that, the young folks told me later, when they wanted to marry, they visited other Hutterite colonies where they had no relatives, and in a couple of weeks in August, there was some quick courting going on. There are three other ranches within thirty miles. Rev. Stahl greeted me kindly. He is an old man who, after illness two years ago, relinquished his position as minister of this community to a younger man who was just recently ordained by the religious head of the Hutterites, who lives in Canada. He knew of my pacifist history but, in a forthright manner, was disconcerted about three things: (1) Why I had waited until 59 years of age to be baptized a Catholic. (2) How I could be a Catholic as well as a pacifist, for the Church upheld war. (3) Why I did not live with my wife. I had given him a copy of my book, and showed him one about the Hopi, and also Dorothy’s book, and he remarked, “Did Jesus have any books?” And looking at the medal of St. Francis which I wore, he said, “And would Jesus wear a medal?” Nevertheless, he gave me a doctrinal book on Hutterite history and theology. His daughter, Mary, asked questions about the CW, and other teenagers and men and women of the community came back and forth. The women dressed plainly, with polka-dot kerchiefs over their heads. The family, of this house of children and grandchildren, ate in the dining room, but I ate with Rev. Stahl in my alcove near his room, his wife having passed on five years ago. He folded his hands in a German blessing and thanked God after the meal. Services are held each day about 5 p.m., but there were none that day, as the Chapel was being painted. The meeting lasts for two hours on Sunday morning.

During the evening, I was asked questions about Catholic faith and customs, and later, when the older folks had gone to bed, the teenagers showed me their hope chests, where all that they were allowed to own was placed. Once in a while, one would place a picture of a movie star on the inside of the lid, but this was very daring indeed. They freely discussed the outer world and their happy life within this community. They had met some sweet nuns at a hospital, but had read Maria Monk stories, and had much to learn. Statistics show that there is less mental disturbance and a higher birth rate among these folks than any other of record. They do not send mentally ill people to hospitals, but take care of them at home, which is the CW and anarchist ideal. I asked them about discipline in the community. They said that a certain boy had stolen a bicycle from a neighbor in the “outer-world” (my daughters of the I AM religion speak of the outside in this exact term also). He broke it trying to ride it, and he was paddled, and had to stand ashamed before all in Church. The community repaid the value of the stolen article in wheat. Later this boy enlisted in the army, and now writes back that he has learned to obey, and when he comes back, he will consider himself lucky, and will behave. If a person of adult age did evil, he confessed his sin before all in church, and if it was possible to undo the injury, he did so. A more serious crime—where there was no repentance—resulted in the person leaving the community. No cases were ever taken to an outside court. Seven boys from this community were in Civilian Public Service in World War II, and none have been sent to date to alternative service in the draft which continues today. Some rabble-rousers, led by a military man from the city, tried to use KKK tactics at the time of Pearl Harbor, but as the Hutterites have the respect of the community, this soon died down. There are 98 communities of the Hutterites, divided as follows in the 1954 Almanac shown to me: 7,264 in Alberta and Manitoba, having 88 ministers; 372 in South Dakota with 24 ministers, this number being included in the Montana groups who have 12 ministers. There are 472 in Paraguay with 7 ministers and 124 in England with 2 ministers. Each colony is on its own, although they may trade produce if they desire. This colony has 200 cows, 700 sheep, 2,000 chickens, and 20 hives of bees. No tobacco is used, but beer and wine is made, and is consumed by these German folks without drunkenness. No ornaments, musical instruments, radio, television, dancing, or going to movies are permitted. No photographs are ever taken.

These folks do not like being called Mennonites, for they are Hutterites. Rev. Stahl read to me from Acts, telling about obedience to authorities and the payment of taxes to Caesar. Here they pay $5,000 local taxes for roads and schools, and some federal income tax. They liked my idea of simple life on the land and did not mind my vegetarianism, admitting that they ate too much meat. They are not out to disturb and convert the world, as are the Doukhobors, and told me that I would make a good Hutterite; but I felt that while it was wonderful to visit these good folks, their atmosphere was too puritanical for me.

When a young man is married, he then grows a beard, and he gets a bed, 25 pounds of feathers to make quilts, a bureau, a spinning wheel, and a sewing machine. With more children, they get more rooms. There is no honeymoon. Each farmer is allowed a dollar a month to spend if he has to go to town for anything. As they buy wholesale, many of the local merchants do not get Hutterite trade, and so restrictive laws as to their expansion have been passed in South Dakota and Manitoba.

The Doukhobors

I have visited these anarchistic pacifists four times in the past 19 years. They broke off from the Greek Orthodox Church in Russia about 300 years ago.

“Each priest argued that the Holy Spirit was in favor of his own way of making the sign of the Cross,” Peter, their leader, continued. “I rose from behind the trees where I had been sitting. ‘You are both wrong,’ I told them. ‘The Holy Spirit is not concerned whether you make the sign of the Cross with two fingers, three fingers, or with all fingers of both hands. And if you priests had enough of the Holy Spirit within, you would not be squabbling over such foolish things.’

“ ‘Oh,’ said the Governor, baring his teeth at me like an angry dog, ‘You are wrestling with the Holy Spirit, eh?’ You are a spirit wrestler; a Doukhobor; tie him to the post and whip him across his back.”

This quotation is from F.C. Wright’s Slava Bohu (Praise God), a story of the Doukhobors published in 1941 by Farrar, Rinehart. I have corresponded with him in Vancouver, where he is a newspaper man.

As a Tolstoian, I had read of these 7,000 Christian Anarchists coming from concentration camps and the wilderness of Russia to Saskatchewan in 1889. Tolstoy’s royalties from Resurrection, with money from the English Quakers, provided their transportation. After seven years of homesteading, they were asked to swear allegiance to the king, but as they did not believe in king or czar they refused and gave up their land, and moved to British Columbia, 150 miles north of Spokane, where they bought land. Alexis Carrel in his Man, the Unknown, says of them: “The Doukhobors of Canada have demonstrated that those whose will is strong can secure complete independence, even in the midst of modern civilization. I know with them that: ‘Christ said turn the other cheek. Some among humanity must begin, must set an example. Our ancestors did not give way to the Cossacks. We will lead the way, will suffer for our principles come what may.’ ”

Tradition says that the Doukhobors come from the Three Hebrew Children of the fiery furnace. In 1893, at the village of Kars, in Russia, they had received word from their leader, who was in prison in Siberia, that they should reform their lives and burn all guns, knives, ikons, tobacco pouches, vodka containers, and that there should be no more division of rich and poor among them. When they built this fire, Cossacks beat them with knouts and trod them with their horses.

In 1954, in upper California, I met aged Fred Sorokoff, who at the age of 12 had witnessed this terrible scene. His son had been in prison as a conscientious objector in World War II.

They burned schoolhouses rather than send their children there to be taught militarism. They took off their clothes in court, as much as to say, “You have taken our land, our children, because we would not send them to your schools, now take our clothes, take everything.” St. Francis divested himself of his clothing in the public square at Assisi rather than be a part of the commercialism of his wealthy father. George Fox went naked in the streets of London; so it is an old tradition. In 1941, I met Peter and Lucy Maloff, and later Helen Demoskoff, who was my interpreter as I spoke at Krestova, where a score of men and women stood naked after a vegetarian meal, singing their religious songs. Helen had been in jail for 11 years, off and on, for going naked in court, refusing to send her children to school, and for burning down community property which the government had confiscated and turned over to other Doukhobors whom they could train, more or less, in Canadian ways. Helen also burned her own house for good measure. Dorothy has also visited Helen, and looks upon her as a sister. After thirteen years, I visited the Doukhobors again, and was pleased to see the calmness of her grey eyes, the lucidity and spirituality of her conversation, and the warmth of her love, which the hounds of the government could not lessen. The government had taken hundreds of Doukhobor children and kept them for five years in the New Denver Sanitorium to brainwash them into patriotic ideas. The Quakers had sent a certain Emmet Gulley from Portland to help the Doukhobors, and he gradually turned into a persecutor of them, and worked hand in hand with the government. I reported this to the Quakers in Philadelphia and Pasadena several times, until they finally removed him. In fact, the Vancouver Sun had a cartoon of a Quaker kidnapping a Doukhobor child and turning it over to the Mounties. Bloodhounds were used in some cases. Now, after my fourth visit in 1960, I find that a compromise has been reached, and all children are returned to their homes, no patriotic history is taught in the schools, there is no homework, and girls are allowed to wear the traditional Russian blouses and skirts. But recently, a teacher asked children who had been brainwashed for five years what they wanted to be when they grew up, and two boys answered that they wanted to be policemen. So it was about time that they came home, where the parents could counteract some of the devilishness taught in the schools.

The Doukhobors are divided in five factions. The great majority live in Saskatchewan and are on big farms, and have for the most part succumbed to Canadian ways—voting, eating meat, no communal life, smoking, drinking—but they are legally recognized as pacifists, and do not have to go to war. They support the Red Cross instead.

The Orthodox, led by Johnny Verigin, nephew of Peter the Lordly Verigin, who sent the message from Siberia in 1895, lives in Brilliant, and there are a great number of others around Grand Forks, to the west, who are still pacifists and live fairly simply, but who are tired out, and have finished with community living and with any opposition to the government. They meet in prayer and singing and keep up many traditions, and for the most part accept old age pensions.

The prophet Sorokin came here, but some years ago migrated to South America, and did not come back. He has some followers, of varying adherence to Doukhobor ideals, who await his leadership.

The Reformed Spiritual Community of Christ, some of whose members may also follow Sorokin, and who in the past burned down schoolhouses, went naked in court, and refused to send their children to school. Some of them live in a sort of communal group in Krestova. They have not promised to cease their violent tactics, and as I drove toward Nelson recently, at night, police were stopping all cars to see if any Doukhobor was up to mischief; and a guard is at certain bridges and schoolhouses all night.

The Lebedof Faction is a smaller group, to which Helen belongs. They have formerly burnt houses and gone naked in court, and they feel that they have already established this witness, and the time is now ripe to emphasize more positive aspects of Doukhobor tradition, such as in the old time, and a refusal to accept pensions from the government.

There was also a very small group under the leadership of Michael Verigin, now deceased, where communal living and communal marriage was practiced, at Hillyers, B.C., near Vancouver. One child was born there, and was given the name of the mother, as it was impossible to tell who was the father. Helen’s brother, Joe Podvinikoff, was one of the leaders. This group has now disbanded.

There is much animosity between all of these groups, much high-sounding intellectual hairsplitting, each accusing the other of not being a good Doukhobor, when in fact there are some in each group who do smoke, drink, eat meat, or vote, and there are some in each group who fall away from one or more of these Doukhobor ideals.

In my 1960 visit, I got acquainted with Helen’s husband Pete, and her brother Pete, who had both done time in prison. Her brother Philip, nearby, has a small flour mill where wheat is stoneground. Unlike the Hutterites and some other communities, the Doukhobors have not succumbed to white bread. Helen made some wonderful pancakes, and her husband warmed up a steam-bath, where you sit on a table with feet on a bench, midst steam made from dashing hot water on hot stones, and wash yourself with hot and cold water, and finish off with a switch of tree branches.

The Canadian government negotiated with the Russian government to move the Doukhobors back to Russia, and Helen’s brother Joe was on a committee that went to Russia to see about it. They signed away their Canadian citizenship, to take effect when they were on a boat going to Russia. Helen and about 50 others do not consider themselves the citizens of any government, so they are now free, it would seem. But negotiations have bogged down, and nothing has come of this removal.

I went with Helen to Nelson, B.C., and we visited the newspaper office; and in a few days a picture of us appeared saying “Anarchist Visitor … with Helen Demoskoff, member of the Sons of Freedom … an admirer of the Doukhobors ‘because they have been in jail so often in defense of their beliefs.’ ” My last evening, this time with the Doukhobors, was spent in hearing about thirty of their youth practice songs, at Pete Maloff Jr.’s house. I was asked to speak to them, and I only wished that they lived in the United States, for then I could teach in their home schools, and rest up between jails with these wonderful comrades; but I could only stay in Canada a short time without being deported as a subversive. I plan to visit the Doukhobors soon, in Saskatoon.

The Molokons

Molokon means “Milk Drinker.” This name was given to them in Russia by the Orthodox because they were dissidents from the regular church, led communal lives, and were pacifists.

Thousands of them came to Arizona and central California at the turn of the century. Each family had a quarter of an acre strip of land for their home and cow, chickens, etc. and all farmed in common. Any extra money earned outside was turned over to the local Molokon preacher. In 1917 in Phoenix about fifteen Molokons went to federal court for refusal to register for the draft. One of them was David, who worked for the Old Pioneer with whom I lived in the late forties. In court the Molokons wanted to sing and pray, but the Old Pioneer told them this was not allowed, but spoke to the Judge about it, and of course the Judge had to uphold the dignity of the court. The Old Pioneer told the Judge, “you had better let them sing for they will do it anyway.” So they sang and prayed. They all got time for opposing the war.

Later David’s wife Stella said that it was not fair for her and her husband, who worked hard, and had no children, to turn their money over to the Molokon preacher. “The serpent has entered the garden,” the Old Pioneer said. And sure enough, in a few years all this communal life was abandoned, and now Molokons have big cars, get drunk, and in 1952 I was asked by two young Molokons down the lateral to go to court with them, as their brother was up for being against the war. He had registered but the authorities did not want to defer him. Now there was no singing and praying. About the same time, David and Stella revisited the Old Pioneer. Now, he is a wealthy Molokon preacher, and there is no radical talk. One Sunday, I went down the road, several miles, to the Molokon Church. Not many young folks were there. The men sat around a table on benches, and the women sat in the back of the room on benches. They have no musical instruments, but do a lot of singing in Russian. As each one enters the church, all present get up and bow. There is a short sermon, and all kneel on the floor and pray. When this is finished, each man kisses all the other men, and each woman bows before each man, and he, in a stately manner, puts his arm around her and kisses her. Then each woman kisses all of the other women. The preacher here is a farmer, who gets no salary. He hears confession, but it is not obligatory. There is no collection, but anyone can place money on the table for the poor if he likes, but I never saw any poor Doukhobors around Phoenix. They keep the Jewish holy days too, and do not eat pork or lard, and at certain times the the preacher blesses the crops in the fields. Dorothy and I have visited some of the old-timers who were in jail in 1917, and whenever I go to Phoenix, I always visit them. In August, many Molokons visit in California who are equally prosperous. Many of them are friends of some of the Doukhobors in Canada.

Single Tax

Arden, Delaware and Fairhope, Alabama were started in the 1890s as Single Tax colonies. At the former, Upton Sinclair lived. An obnoxious anarchist shoemaker had him arrested under the old blue laws for playing tennis on Sunday, and he left. My wife and I spent a week there in 1920, visiting its founder Frank Stephens, and Don Stephens, who was a conscientious objector in World War I. Those who lived there were artists, or retired people, or bourgeois radicals who made a living in town. The intellectual atmosphere was better than most places. It was not intended to be the center of any revolution, only that in the matter of land there was not any exploitation. Profit and banking were not disturbed. As related in the first part of this book, my wife and I lived for six months in 1924 in Fairhope, where I taught in the progressive school there. I have made two visits, since that, time to Fairhope. It is growing in population and is surrounded by real estate speculative land, but the Single Tax idea is practiced as of old. I stayed at the home of the secretary of the Single Tax Corporation, Cornie Gaston, and he explained the idea to me. Tolstoy and other anarchists were friendly to the arguments of Single Tax, but as in practice a government is sanctioned, I am not interested in it. Fels of Fels-Napha and Lincoln of Lincoln Electric Co. have left millions for Single Tax propaganda but it seems that no one is enthusiastic enough to work overtime or to sweat, let alone die, for the cause, so it progresses not even as much as we poor anarchists. I quote from the Single Tax leaflet: “Under the Single Tax the government, not the land holder, is entitled to that portion that is now paid to the so-called ‘owners’ of land, as rent. Ownership is a term that can be properly applied only to those things that come into existence as a result of man’s labor applied to land. Land, by its nature, and by reason of man’s necessity to use it must be treated as common property so far as rent is concerned, if justice is to prevail … Since much of that which results from man’s labor on the land cannot be separated from the land upon which it is produced, it follows, that to have for himself the full ownership of that which he has produced, he must have exclusive title to the land involved in the production. To prevent such exclusive title from constituting a denial of the equal rights of all others, the single tax requires the holder of such title to pay into a common fund, for the equal benefit of all, an annual rent (single tax) equal to the value of the special privilege of exclusive title to the land. This value … is measured by the market value set by those who want land to use at its fullest productive capacity. This makes it unprofitable to hold land out of use or for inferior uses.”

Llano Colony

This was started near Leesville, La., around 1912, by Job Harriman, Socialist leader, who was defeated for mayor of Los Angeles because of the McNamara brothers’ confession of dynamiting the Times building. My wife and I spent a couple of weeks in the colony in 1922. They wanted us to stop and teach in their school, but we still wanted to hike over the U.S., and we did not like the dictatorship of Pickett, who was the manager. We met Kate Richards O’Hare and her family, there, and Bill Zeuch. The plan was for radicals to gather in this utopia where they would cooperate and not be exploited. The price of admission was $2,000. Old cut-over land had been bought cheaply and somehow, instead of cultivating and building homes on the land they had, they bought more and more land, and also some on the Isle of Pines, to grow tropical fruit. They had a good bakery and dairy, with milk and bread routes toward Leesville. The Llano Colonist was a well written paper with a growing circulation. When we were there, they were filling the silo. Last year there were dozens of trucks with silage, and only a couple of people to tramp it in the silo. This year, there were half a dozen to do the tramping, but only a truck coming in now and then. The manager did not want to thin carrots, for that would be wasteful, so we had thin, spindly and crooked carrots. Now anyone could come, if they only had two mules and 10 children. The old timers were leaving and the newcomers were loafing. In religion, no one agreed on anything. The only thing all agreed on was that they did not like capitalism. My brother Paul roasted the peanuts, ground them into peanut butter, and packed it in cans or glass for sale. He was there for ten months, and got tired of the continual quarreling among the leaders. New folks came and the older ones left until, around 1936, it was dissolved. Pickett hung on until around 1957 on an acre or two. There is some committee in Los Angeles that claims some of the assets. Llano was bound to fail for the same reason that others failed, such as the New Harmony colony of Robert Owen, the Phalanges in Wisconsin of the Fourierites, etc., etc.: because these colonies were made up of people who came to escape life, with very little ability to work, and very little desire. What they wanted was a hand out. They could have been held together by some religion, perhaps, but they had different religions, or none.

The Bruderhof

They began in Germany after World War I, had to go to England when Hitler came into power, and then migrated to the wilds of Paraguay. With their German efficiency, they cleared the wilderness, built a hospital, and provided for themselves, however, they hired natives to do unskilled work. They were pacifist, but decidedly not anarchist or vegetarian. Later they established a group at Rifton, N.Y., where they manufactured wooden toys. Anyone can join, but they are looked over by The Servants of the Word, a self-perpetuating group who pray and are led by God to do the right thing. Everyone has to think alike and there is no deviation from the norm. You cannot wear whiskers if that is the line, you cannot travel unless you get permission, you cannot write anything for publication unless it is o.k. A young fellow could not court a girl unless the Servants of the Word felt it was best. When Vivian Cherry took pictures of our Newburgh farm for Jubilee in 1955, we stopped at the Bruderhof at noon. I knew some folks there who were vegetarians, and suggested that I eat at the vegetarian table with them. “Oh, we are not vegetarians any more: we have achieved unity.” This is another name for brainwashing. There are folks who have been pushed around in life, and they turn over their worldly goods to the Bruderhof, and have security. If they like it, then it is the place for them. If they can change their ideas and habits to suit the Servants of the Word and think they are doing God’s will, then they are happy. I do not know what the rate of turnover is here. A few years later, I was visiting the Macedonia Colony for the second time. The Bruderhof was just in the process of liquidating it and selling out, moving the members either to another colony in Pennsylvania or the one in Connecticut. I asked the son of the founder, Mr. Arnold, if a Catholic could be a Bruderhof. He said: “You could come here and live, and we would search for the truth. There is just one truth, not two.” And of course that would be the Bruderhof. It is therefore no place for an anarchist, but for those who do not mind being regulated and ordered around, it is fine. It is also a haven for tired radicals, or those who do not wish to oppose the system. To say that they are demonstrating anything about a future society is foolish: what they are doing is to provide a haven for those who are tired of fighting and who want to feel secure. (Dorothy Day does not agree with my ideas. She likes both the society of Brothers and Hutterites, and points out that their rule is voluntarily accepted.) I have friends in the Bruderhof in Paraguay and in England, as well as in this country, but they, as a whole, are too organized and medical-minded to suit me. But they don’t have to please me: there are plenty of people who will appreciate them.

The Koinonia Community

This group is not far from the site of the old Andersonville Prison of Civil War time. It is near Americus, Ga. and is comprised of 1,100 acres of fairly good farm land where cotton, peanuts, pecans, etc. are grown. Two Baptist ministers started it around twenty years ago with the understanding that colored and white folks could live together. The ministers were put out of the Baptist Church, and they continued to be a source of cheer to the poor Negroes around there. After the Supreme Court decision, the White Citizen’s Councils got excited and bombed the road stand where the colony sold hams and other produce. They also shot at random with rifles at night through the windows of the houses, cut down thousands of young trees, and raised a lot of terror, until finally, no Negro would live on the premises. Any neighbor who would deal with the colony, or any store, or even a bank, who would deal with them was also bombed. They had to go 50 miles to buy feed or gasoline, and of course, they could not sell any produce. Even the insurance company canceled their insurance. So they bought pecan-shelling machinery, and made a living shipping the non-perishable nuts. Friends took up the slack of the insurance so that, in effect, they are insured. Members were beaten up in Americus, and brought to court on false charges and fined. An effort was made in the legislature to make them illegal. But Clarence Jordon, their leader, remained adamant; he would not run away. Three of us from the CW have been down there on night watch, and Dorothy had bullets sprayed around her, but no one was hurt. The few days I was there, there was no shooting. I worked in the shed packing pecans. While these folks are Baptists, they do not shove their religion at you the way some colonies do. Of course, people come and go for various reasons. They are pacifists, but not anarchists or vegetarians. I have no criticism of Koinonia, and would enjoy another visit.

St. Francis Acres, Glen Gardner, N.J.

This 17-acre wooded community was founded around 15 years ago by the man whom I consider the best fellow I know, David Dellinger. He had been in prison as a conscientious objector, and bought this land and established a printing press, bringing young pacifists and their wives to establish the new life. But the women wanted the pretty things in town, and both men and women wanted other spouses, and soon they all left, but others came and left, and now others came and stayed. As it happens, all but one, besides Dave and his sons, are now Catholics. They have a common purse, and democratic meetings as to how to run the colony, but the trouble is that very few people there are responsible workers, except Dave. I lived there for five months while the first edition of my book was being printed. If people are all of one religion, it is possible for them to live together in harmony, but this is not the case at Glen Gardner. If, after living in a community for many years, the common pocketbook idea is found among people who know each other, that is fine; but to begin with that impediment among people who come there because they can’t make it on the outside, does not make for a growing, successful community.

The Amana Society

These pacifist Germans lived in community in Iowa much like the Hutterites, having a blacksmith shop, some small industries, a brewery, and farms. Around 1942, they ceased their community living and divided the industries into shares, like capitalistic organizations, and all now own their farms. I stopped there when hiking in 1946, but could not get any interest in pacifist ideas from anyone I spoke to. The older ones did not understand English, and the younger ones, I suppose, were now sold on The American Way of Life. Now, the “Amana refrigerator” is widely advertised.

Celo Community

I visited this beautiful valley among the North Carolina mountains in 1950, when the Hopi, Joe Craigmyle, and I were on our way to Washington, D.C. Each one has five or ten acres and owns it outright, but there is a provision that he cannot sell it to anyone who is not approved by the community as a whole. There is a Quaker hospital nearby, where some of the colonists work. I had corresponded with one of the first conscientious objectors, Arle Brooks, and wanted to see him here, but he was miles away chopping wood, so I visited his wife Tillie, as related previously. Some old folks have come here to retire, and while the tone of the community is pacifist, it seems to be a resting place, rather than one which is alive. As I understand it, no Negroes live here; whether this is planned that way I do not know, but they do not have any racial trouble. It would be too quiet and too medical for me, but for some it would be, and is, the good life.

Macedonia Community

As mentioned before, this group was liquidated by the Bruderhof. I had visited it in 1950 and knew most of its members. They had a notation of the amount (not their name) on the score board, so that it would be known when the barrel was empty. They had a fine dairy and a milk route in town. They also made wooden toys, and raised vegetables and had a small school. There was a great variety of religious beliefs here, and continual turnover, as some were very pious, and others atheistic. They were all pacifists. The community was bound to fail because of this controversy on religion. The Bruderhof was the answer, for now they could all believe the same, with exception of a few who did not go with the Bruderhof.

Meadowlark, Newton, Kansas

When I spoke to the college of the Brethren in Newton, I went out to Selma Platt’s place, called “Meadowlark.” Here she took care of mentally ill people, for free and also for pay. She had enough land surrounding the main house for cottages for others, and some came from the defunct Macedonia Community. The spirit was cordial, well organized, and more of a venture than a real community. There was no religious basis upon which it could be founded. It could function as a helping hand. The people there tended to be liberal rather than radical.

Gould Farm

This large farm began half a century ago as a rest home in the Berkshires, near Great Barrington, Massachusetts, where mentally disturbed people came for rest and received treatment from specialists in the nearby town. Some of them could pay, and others couldn’t. There is a Protestant religious atmosphere, with chapel and evening meetings, but it is not forced upon the members of the community. There are a dozen small cottages where those who need privacy can have it. I attended a convention of social workers there and gave the CW radical philosophy. Later, I was invited again, and spoke to a smaller audience. Pacifists and anarchists have at times been part of the staff, although the foundation that runs the community pays salaries, and is liberal rather than radical. With these limitations, I feel that they are performing a good service.

Harold Gray, Saline, Michigan

Harold had been in jail in World War I, and had inherited a large farm near Saline, Michigan. Here he gathered pacifist friends, and had a large dairy, and raised pigs, chickens, and fruits and berries. They had milk and other routes, whereby they sold their products. Harold was Episcopalian, and the others were of varying beliefs, or none. All were pacifists. However, when big wages in the city beckoned, they all left for the fleshpots. I visited there twice when Harold was in the process of selling his herd of cows, as he could not hire men to tend them. He often went to the CW farm at South Lyons to get their whole-wheat bread, and in fact drove me there once. Now he is building houses for city folks on his place and is a landlord, with no idea of the community with which he started. He just couldn’t buck the whole Ford way of life.

Spirit Fruit, Lisbon, Ohio

In 1907, in my home town, Jacob Beilhart bought an old farmhouse on the edge of town and started a religion by this name. A relative of the man who brought up my father joined it, and was known as “Ma Young.” The local newspaper wrote terrible stories about them worshiping the devil, and when, finally, a girl there from Chicago had a baby, they were driven out of town and went to Kansas, where, after a few years, Jacob died of appendicitis. As I remember it, he dealt with spiritualistic mediums, was against all exploitation of capitalism, and there seemed to be some kind of communal marriage. Everything, of course, was held in common, and those who came gave all they had. There seemed also to be an idea that money would come in abundance if prayers were directed toward the cash. Jacob’s brother in nearby Columbiana was a Socialist. He kept a harness shop, and distributed some of my anti-draft literature in 1917.

The Shakers

This was an old time group of craftsmen and farmers of the early 1800s. They did communal farming like the Hutterites, but the men lived in one huge stone house, and the women lived in another huge stone house. When my wife and I visited what had been such a community in Kentucky, in 1923, the very old lady told us that there were times when the supposed celibacy was overcome. They were prosperous, but after the Civil War they seemed to get no more recruits, what with the expansion of agriculture to the west, and the conscription which had disturbed the even keel of Shaker farming.

Paul Williams, Nyack, N.Y.

This pacifist inherited money from his father and bought the side of a mountain, and began to exercise his unorthodox architectural ideas in housing. He called this a certain cooperative name, built homes for artist friends, charged them a nominal rent, and presently, they live in a congenial community. Each one makes his living as it happens. I visited there one afternoon, and found each home “a castle” as it is supposed to be, with privacy, and yet with the understanding that each neighbor was sympathetic.

The Lemurians

This group started in Wauwatosa, Wisconsin in 1940. They were young folks who were pacifists and vegetarians, but particularly not anarchists, for they envision a perfect society with a constitution somewhat like that of the United States, but without war. This was all to happen in 1953, when a new continent called Lemuria was to rise from the Pacific, and meanwhile, we here would sink. They moved to California near Los Angeles and bought a farm, and prepared to perfect themselves for the great event of 1953. They printed all of their literature in green ink. But time went by, and nothing happened in the Pacific. I do not know if they advanced the date or not, but they are still on the farm in California. I was not able to visit them last time, but will do so on my next trip west, as I knew them as personable young folks, who printed my statement of refusal to register, for free, in 1942, two of them going as conscientious objectors to the CW camp in New Hampshire. In their community in California, they lived in common, each giving all they had when they joined. I have no idea of what the turnover has been with them.

Individuals on Farms who Like the CW Idea

A CW farm was started in the depression, bought for $1,000; and now Carl Paulson, Ridgeroad, Upton, Massachusetts, with his wife Mary and nine children, lives there. He makes a living in stained glass window work. I have visited there half a dozen times. Bill Roach and his wife and nine children also live there. He works in a church furniture factory nearby. The O’Donnells formerly lived in another house, but they have scattered. Carl’s father and mother have built a home nearby also. Each family has a garden, and there are some fruit trees. I have visited thousands of families over the United States, and I would not hope to find a finer one than that of the Paulsons. Carl went to Danbury prison as a conscientious objector. He had married a young artist friend of Ade Bethune, who was a trustee of the farm when it was a communal farm. If I were a young man with a pregnant wife, I would build a house there, and make a living selling milk and honey to the others, and to neighbors.

R. 1, Springboro, Pennsylvania

Jack and Mary Thornton, a farm and a lot of children. Jack worked until recently in a foundry in Erie, and does a lot of farm work. I have visited there several times, and have made calls for friends to come and help Jack. There is room for a dozen families to live on the farm, but they would have to get work in town to supplement their income.

Bill and Dorothy Gauchaut, Avon, Ohio (near Cleveland), formerly had a small acreage, and ran a home of hospitality on Franklin Street, in Cleveland, for years. They sold their acreage and bought, at a bargain, a large, well-built house. Here, Dorothy take cares of spastic and other crippled babies, and gives hospitality. Bill works for a utility company. I have visited them several times.

At South Lyons, Michigan, between Ann Arbor and Detroit, Father Hessler, the pacifist anarchist Maryknoll priest in Yucatan, gave a small farm to the CW in Detroit. Part of it was deeded to Lou Murphy, who runs the Detroit CW, and the rest of it to several families. They built their homes, and have their gardens, and some animals. They make their main living working in hospitals or at other work. There has been a spirit of friction here for years, and although each family may be very good, they do not seem meant to live so close together. Glen Johnson is the one whom I know on the farm now.

Jack Woltjen, Bluffton, Missouri, read the CW after he got out of the army, and used the GI Bill to borrow money to buy a large farm. I have helped him build fences and feed hogs the times I have visited there. He works in a hospital part-time, and hopes to be out of the red soon. Here is room for many families to live, and the place is big enough so that they do not need to be too near each other. They are a fine young couple, well worth knowing. Nearby, Ruth Ann Heany, widow of Larry Heany, my good friend in the CW in Milwaukee, lives. She has five children, and a small place. Marty Paul tried to farm with the Heanys, but gave it up and moved to the city. Her black-Irish children are beautiful.

Bob and Ann Stowell, of Cabot, Vermont, head workcamps in the U.S. They are pacifists, anarchists, and vegetarians, but not Catholics. I have visited them several times. He has been a teacher at the University of Vermont, and does small-job printing too. They work at a southern community in winter. Erie Freedman and wife, a young Jewish couple decided to go to Alaska, and came over to the CW to give help and get ideas. They landed in northern British Columbia, and live off the land.

Communities that I have not Visited

The Huntington Library, Stanford, California, have a book on twenty efforts at communities in the history of California. I visited Kawea, up in the Sequoia region, where there was once a Socialist community. They have only a very small post office, by a rushing mountain stream, now. The big tree that you drive through there, called “General Sherman,” was first named “Karl Marx,” but that was in the old days of the community. There was the Home Community of anarchists on Puget Sound, but it did not last very long. There was the Theosophical community of Madame Tingley, and many others. I have been not far away from The House of David, at Benton Harbor, Michigan, but I never visited it. Their lawyer was a federal judge in Los Angeles in World War I, and resigned and joined this pacifist group, which is really better known as bewhiskered ball players. The son of this lawyer was a conscientious objector, with my friend Rik Anderson, in a camp in California, in World War II.

Ottawa Housing

In 1957, when I was speaking in Ottawa, Paul Harris invited me to his home, which was one of 80 built cooperatively. Father Morosco, now Bishop in Toronto, had about 80 families meet weekly and study cooperative housing for a year and a half, until they were ready to pool about $300 each to form a cooperative for a house for each one. They had met weekly in small groups, and all together once a month; mostly Catholics, with a few Protestant friends. Reasonable loans were made, and each did as much work on his own house as possible, with the help of friends. The houses are with four bedrooms, so that Catholics can have large families. They have a common skating rink, and a park.

In Notre Dame

About ten years ago, Julian Pleasants and friends, who were teachers at Notre Dame, bought a farm on the outskirts, and measured it out in five acre lots, with unpaved roads running through. No one made any profit out of it, and each had a place, with congenial neighbors, where living was cheap. I visited them twice in the winter, so do not know just what they could raise in the summer. The houses were not zoned to be expensive. I don’t think they have much of a community life, but at least they have the basis of cheap housing.

Jehovah’s Witnesses, Brooklyn, N.Y.

I visited their printing plant, and the huge hotel in which they house their four hundred workers, who print millions of copies of books, and work for their keep. They have fine meals and luxurious quarters, and it is considered an honor to come from all over the world and work there for free. Like the CW, workers do not earn a wage, so do not pay an income tax for war. All of the pacifist societies take a war tax from the pay of their employees. It was formerly the rule that those living here could not be married, but this was recently changed—some say, so that some of the big shots could be married. All the JWs live under a discipline that would make any anarchist shiver, and, having little sense of humor, I suppose they take it, and never know what happens. They formerly had a farm near our farm on Staten Island, and I visited that twice. They knew who we were and had brought us some vegetables when we first came there. They now have a much larger farm and a school in upstate New York.

Short Creek, Arizona Mormons

On the Sunday morning in 1953 when the Korean War was ended, over 100 state police and deputies came to this peaceful community to arrest 26 men, 38 women, and 154 children because polygamy was practiced. Short Creek is in “The Strip,” which is an area as large as New Hampshire, Delaware, and Rhode Island combined, and with a population of 700. It is north of the Grand Canyon, and logically would belong to Utah, but it is in Arizona. To get there from the county seat, Holbrook, south of the Canyon, is 430 miles around through Nevada and Utah. The suppression of this great rebellion against the “decency” of metropolitan Phoenix was engineered by Republican Governor Howard Pyle in a theatrical attempt to gain votes, but it was one of the reasons for his defeat in the next election. The real issue, of course, in Arizona is that the copper companies never have paid their share of taxes, and the big land companies have prevented any law regulating the ground water that they pump out and thus impoverish ordinary ranchers. All this dust storm about the immorality of the Short Creek Mormons was used to keep the minds of the people from the real issues. When the state police, camera men, reporters, etc. arrived to conquer this great rebellion against the sovereign state of Arizona, the children were neatly dressed, and stood in the early dawn singing God Bless America. The men were taken to Holbrook, and then to Prescott, to prison, and the women and children to Phoenix, where the Welfare Department portioned them out in rest homes. After some months in prison, the men were released with the half-promise that if they were quiet they could see their children. However, the women were not allowed to see their husbands, and the children are not permitted to see their fathers. An article in Colliers, for Nov. 11, 1953, describes the situation. Ray Williams is one of three school teachers in Short Creek. He is a Mormon who has one wife and three children. He has never practiced polygamy, but unless he promises that he will never practice it in the future, he will not be allowed to teach. Furthermore, he is not allowed to see his children or his wife unless he gives up his religious belief of polygamy. Another man of Short Creek is married but has no children, yet he is not allowed to see his wife unless he promises to give up his ideas of polygamy. Meanwhile, the parasite Tommy Manville is free to have a dozen wives, and the courts over the country grind out fake divorces for him and for others. There are many cases of Navajo men having several wives, for the women here own the sheep, and the more sheep he has, the more wealth he has. The government winks at this, and calls the extra wives “boarders.” Maybe it is because the Navajos are so scattered, and it is difficult to tell them apart. Before I came east, the last money I made as a migrant worker was given to the Catholic lawyer who was defending the Short Creek folks. Perhaps by this time promises have been made by the Mormons which they never intend to keep, and the families are together again in Mexico, or some place else. I plan to visit Short Creek sometime, and see how these folks live in community.

The Order of Aaron

Maryellen Fullem drove me the 230 miles southwest of Salt Lake City, through the town of Delta to within six miles to Eskdale, on the Nevada line, where this group has 3,000 acres in the desert, a school of 50 children, and 17 adults who raise food for the colony and alfalfa for their stock. At Partoun, 50 miles north, they have 5,000 acres where Mr. Card, an early convert to the group, lives and helps take care of their land. They also have a sawmill at the top of a mountain, near Price. I had met Mr. Conrad, a cheery, outgoing man, who, along with his wife, are teachers here, two years ago, when Mary and I were picketing the tax office. We visited some classes, and later heard the string orchestra play classical music. I spoke of the Indians, and made friends with ten-year-old Mary, who was especially interested. Mr. and Mrs. Conrad receive a salary from the state for teaching these children, and this money is a help to the colony. They have eight of their own, and a divorcée is there with five children. The others are boarded at $30 a month from families of the Order who cannot live here at present. Members also tithe to Bishop Glendenning, and he has a Council of Twelve, and a Patriarch, as in the Mormon Church, and a successor determined in case of his death. He is 72 years of age.

The custom here at meals is to eat silently. The girls wear blue corduroy dresses, but the boys wear whatever they happen to have. Fields of alfalfa dot the desert. The Snake Mountains are about ten miles to the west, and the colony is six miles off the highway leading from Delta to Ely, Nevada. The nearest town is Garrison, Utah. They have their own power, for lights and for pumping water, from a diesel outfit. Their small houses are of wood, and unpainted. Water is pumped into a wooden tank so they have water pressure. Small trees stick up hopefully around the place.

We spoke for a time with Mrs. LaRue Snow Young (a good Mormon name), whose husband, until his death two years ago, had been one of their leaders. These folks are ex-Mormons who believe in living cooperatively with all in common, like the Hutterites, whose King Colony in Montana, where Dorothy and I have visited, they have also contacted. This cooperative effort they call The United Order, this being the Mormon term used by Joseph Smith and Brigham Young. They also live The Word of Wisdom, which means that they do not smoke or drink, as good Mormons are supposed to do. Those who use tea or coffee do so as long as they feel they have to, but this is frowned upon. They are pacifists, and teach that the Lord will soon come, so they have unsheathed their sword and taken up the Bible, and all their young men go to alternative service rather than go in the armed services. They are not polygamists, although many people around here think there would be no other reason for so many women and children to be hidden away in the desert.

While we were picketing the tax man here in 1961, Mary and I were invited to a singing fest of this Order at a private home, and I was asked to say a few words. A chiropractor, by the name of Dr. M.L. Glendenning, had started this group 30 years ago, but it was not legally chartered until 20 years ago. I subscribed to the CW for him and Mr. Conrad in 1961. I looked up their address, but Dr. Glendenning and his wife were in Arizona. I spoke to a middle-aged woman in charge, and she explained the principles of the Order; and I bought a book, Now My Servant, by Blanche W. Beeston, Caxton Press, Caldwell, Idaho, 1957, which tells of the life of Dr. Glendenning. According to this book, he is said to have heard a voice, supposed to be Elias, speak to him since the age of 14. These messages are collected in The Book of Elias. He has been directed, he states, to documents left by his ancestors, in this country and Scotland, proving that he is a lineal descendant of The Order of Aaron, and that he was directed to continue this Order. Converts have been made in Provo and Salt Lake City. At the semiannual Mormon Conference April 6, 1931, because of the activity of Dr. Glendenning, Joseph Fielding Smith declared that no messages or revelations were bona fide unless they came to the President of the Mormon Church. An attempt is made to prove from The Book of Mormon and their Doctrine and Covenants that this Order of Aaron is not spurious. I have spoken to men outside this group who know Dr. Glendenning, and they say he is sincere, and acts fairly with those who join the Order, and that it is not a fraudulent group. I have met leaders of other religions who have claimed to have received Divine instructions, and I have found that their main emphasis was upon collecting money from the gullible, and that their private lives were materialistic and gluttonous, and far removed from the ideal which they preached.

At Eskdale, they keep Saturday as the Sabbath; but in Salt Lake City, they keep Sunday. I have attended their Sunday meetings and find them a cheerful and sincere group. If I meet Dr. Glendenning, later, and more of this group, I will be able to form an opinion about them. Right now, I am favorably impressed. Those who join the Order are on probation for a year, and, after the first noviceship, anything that they turn over cannot be refunded if they leave the Order. The writer of this book says that Dr. Glendenning will allow a person whom he has chosen to do any certain work the freedom to make mistakes, for by this method he will learn the hard way, and the lesson will stick. This is the only pacifist group that I have met that has come out of the Mormon lineage. It is easier for those raised for generations in an “out-of-this-world” religion to remain “unspotted from the world.” But for the Bruderhof, Koinonia in Georgia, and this group to take people out of the commercial life of the cities, and expect their children to grow up and not to go back to the fleshpots, is surely a problem. The personality of a leader may hold them together as long as he lives, but generally there is a fight over who is to succeed in authority. This has happened among the Doukhobors, Molokons, and Bruderhof. If the organization squelches all discord, affairs may run smoothly, but it is likely that the spirit may be lost, as has happened to all orthodox religions. If these new groups cannot prove by their lives, as the Hutterites have done, that they do lead the true Christian life, then they have no excuse for existing.

Always, there have been remnants of the early Mormons who felt that their freedom of religion allowed them to have more than one wife, despite what they called the “sellout” of the Salt Lake Mormons. They felt also that the centralized authority of the banking and other industrial interests of the rich Mormons in the big cities of Utah was not the real spirit of those early Mormons who trekked the desert, and worked and suffered in common. Somehow, also, these Mormons got away from the bloodthirstiness of their Book of Mormon and took the pacifist attitude of The Sermon on the Mount. Without using the words, these folks were primitive pacifists and anarchists, for they had seceded from the state and were breaking the laws of the state. They lived with everything common except wives, just as the early Christians had lived.

There was the New Home colony on Long Island founded by Josiah Warren of Bunker Hill lineage. It lasted until that generation had died away and the young folks became city and capitalist minded. There was the Socialist Colony in Ruskin, Tennessee founded by J.A. Wayland of the Appeal to Reason. Debs went there once. It lasted only a short time. And of course there was the classic Oneida Community founded by John H. Noyes, which lasted only part of a generation and ended up as a financial success in the famous Oneida Community Silver. Books have been written about the community of wives here, and of the discipline whereby the sexual act was prolonged. There was a lot of opposition to this community, but Noyes, who was a brave and forceful man, fought for his rights. Whether or not his leadership kept anyone else from developing sufficient strength to carry on when he gave up, at least the community did not last for long.

The Catholic Worker

“People shipwrecked on an island—that’s not a community: that’s a disaster—that’s the Catholic Worker!” All of the things that made for the failure of other communities that have failed, or that are now on the skids: we have all that and yet survive somehow. We take in those that no one else will have, and for many there is no other place to go, and some of them stay with us until they die. Our New York group had its first farm at Easton, which was taken over by some families.

We did some good for many, and how much we will never know. There were many retreats there, and vacations for children; but as a farming commune, we were a failure.

Our next, Maryfarm at Newburgh was again the occasion of many retreats where spiritual seed was sown, and we raised plenty of food, but civilization in the form of jet planes that worried cows and chickens, and liquor too close by, coupled with the fact that it was really too far from New York City, caused us to sell the farm. Our Peter Maurin Farm on Staten Island grows plenty of vegetables, and we have retreats and meetings there, but it is in no manner self-sustaining. It is really just another House of Hospitality, such as we have in New York City. It serves a purpose and it is a community, somewhat as a jail is a community—not that you can’t leave the farm, but it is a place that never can be considered a community in the sense of any of the others which we have discussed; it is like our place in town—a station where people come and wait until they can make up their minds where to buy a ticket to, and if they can’t make up their minds, they stay.

Conclusion

It would seem that the only communities that carry on successfully are those of a small religious sect who feel that they have the truth, and they also have a discipline that keeps them away from the outside world. The test comes when it is seen whether or not the second generation carries on the idea. The most successful would seem to be the Hutterites. I have read of communities in England such as the Taena, which is Catholic and nearly a part of monastic life, and of Lanzo De Vasta’s L’Arche in France, and numerous ones in India. I do not have enough firsthand information about them to form an opinion. For myself, I would rather live out in the world, and propagandize “the heathen,” and fight the devil, there. Within the next few years, readers of the CW will see from my writings what I think is valuable about the polygamous Mormons in Utah, Idaho, and Arizona. I intend to visit the Argenta Community, near Nelson, B.C., Canada.

Chapter 18

Book Reviews

1950–1960

Inasmuch as I have gained insight from others, a short summary of the most important book reviews I have written for the CW and in the I.W.W. paper Industrial Worker is given.

The Hopi Way by Laura Thompson, and Culture in Crisis, a study of the Hopi Indians, former U. of Chicago Press, and latter by Harpers.

The thesis of Culture in Crisis is that the influence of missionaries, especially Mennonite, has broken down traditional religious beliefs of the Hopi in the villages of New Oraibi, Upper Moencopi, and Bacobi. And also that the coercive measures of the government have produced “rigidity and ultra-conservatism” in the outstanding rebel village of Hotevilla and in a lesser extent in Shongopovi. As the white man’s world crumbles, the Hopi are shown to have a world outlook, a faith, a Way of Life more satisfying and wholesome than that of the ancient Greek city-states or of any modern Utopia. Will the Indian Bureau succeed in demoralizing the Hopi? Will the missionaries, the army, and the cattle and oil men succeed in getting the souls and bodies of the Hopi? The author says that “The Navajo-Hopi land dispute was not legally settled until 1943, when the Navajo were confirmed in the use of three-quarters of the original Hopi reservation which they had upsurged and were occupying, leaving the Hopi the use of only 986 square miles of desert land.”

The Bending Cross, a biography of Eugene Victor Debs, by Ray Ginger, Rutgers Univ. Press, New Brunswick, N.J., 1949.

Born in a Catholic family, he was not baptized and seldom entered a church, but he was a better follower of Christ as far as I knew than any so-called Christian leader of his time. Even in the 90s he refused to speak before a segregated audience. He was not a pacifist, nor an anarchist, but when Emma Goldman, the anarchist said, “Mr. Debs, you’re an anarchist.” Debs clasped her hand and said, “Not Mister, but Comrade, won’t you call me that?” He said that “The capitalist politician tells you how intelligent you are, to keep you ignorant. I tell you how ignorant you are to make you desire to be intelligent.” His speech to the court in 1918 in Cleveland is a classic. He boldly gave the revolutionary position and got his ten years in Atlanta. Here he was beloved by all prisoners, and refusing to go to compulsory chapel, the warden abolished compulsion for all. In his early days when he was ordered by a group of thugs out of Colorado, he said, “This will either be the beginning of organized labor in Colorado or the end of me.”

The Autobiography of Mother Jones, Mary Field Parton, Charles H. Kerr Co., Chicago, 1925. Reviewed in Dec. 21, 1951 Industrial Worker.

“There’s only one thing to be afraid of … not being a man.” This was the characteristic brave answer of Mother Jones in 1919, at the age of 89, during the steel strike when a union official felt it might compromise their fight to allow a Communist to put out leaflets in the union hall lauding Russian revolt. She was born in County Cork of a family of fighters against British terrorism, she taught in a parochial school in Monroe, Mich., had a dressmaking shop for the rich until burned out by the Chicago Fire of 1871. She then became an organizer for the United Mine Workers until her death at the age of 100. She led hundreds of the wives of miners, armed with mops and brooms and banging on dishpans, to the mine pits, straight up to the machine guns of the Colorado thugs. On elections she said, “You don’t need to vote to raise hell … you need convictions and a voice.”

The Life of Mahatma Gandhi by Louis Fischer. Harpers, N.Y., 1950. $5.00

In dealing with the enemy it was Good will to the enemy that Gandhi always had. Fischer said that “Victory came [in South Africa] to Gandhi not when Smuts had no more strength to fight him but when he had no more heart to fight him.” Gandhi’s idea of fasting is little-understood in the West. Fischer quotes him as saying: “One may fast against those who love you, not against a tyrant.” Gandhi said, “We must widen the prison gates … Freedom is to be wooed only inside prison walls and sometimes on gallows, never in the council chambers, courts, or the schoolroom.” Fischer contrasts Churchill and Gandhi: “Churchill is the Byronic Napoleon. Political power is poetry to him. Gandhi was the sober saint to whom such power was anathema. The British aristocrat and the brown plebian were both conservative, but Gandhi was a nonconformist conservative. As he grew older Churchill became more Tory, Gandhi more revolutionary. Churchill loved social traditions. Gandhi smashed social barriers. Churchill mixed with every class, but lived in own. Gandhi lived with everybody. To Gandhi, the lowliest Indian was a child of God. To Churchill, all Indians were the pedestal for a throne. He would have died to keep England free, but tried to destroy those who wanted India free.”

The Pictorial History of the American Indian, by Oliver LaFarge, Crown Publication, N.Y., 1957.

This book accomplishes the difficult feat of interspersing 350 illustrations of American Indians with their historical perspectve and debunkng much of the fiction in our history books, so that it ought to be required reading in every high school in the country. The map giving the ancient location of over 200 tribes ought to help put the white man in his place geographically, while the details of the government’s deceit ought to put us in our place ethically. Indians lived in New Mexico 20,000 years ago and for 3,000 years grew corn. The way the white man got the land of the Indian was, “get him drunk, talk him into signing a mortgage he cannot pay off, does not understand that he must pay off, and in due course foreclosure… that is the system.” “Many missionaries think that a man cannot become a good Christian unless he dresses as the missionary does, lives in the same kind of a house, eats the same food—despite the fact that, as Indians sometimes point out, Our Lord wore His hair long and wrapped Himself in something very like a blanket. The same line of thinking led well meaning schoolteachers on the Navajo reservation to propagandize their pupils urgently against eating the ‘disgusting’ parts of a sheep, until a study by the Association on American Indian Affairs showed that only by eating the whole animal could the Indians achieve a balanced diet, and that those who followed the teachers advice were more susceptible to tuberculosis than those who did not.”

Cherokee, by Don Tracy, Dial, N.Y., 1957.

True to the history of Tsali, who by his bravery in refusing with his band of mountain Cherokees to accept the white man’s false promise of freedom in Indian Territory, and by his voluntary death at the hand of the U.S. Army, was able to purchase the freedom of the remnant of his people, this thrilling story gives the customs and traits of this noblest of eastern Indians. The love story of Suti, the boy who killed two panthers with his blowgun and darts, and of Meg, the daughter of freedom-loving pioneers, is more gripping than most of the romances of modern whites.

The Royal City, by Les Savage, Jr., Hanover House, N.Y., 1956.

This book tells vividly of the rebellion of 1680 led by Po-pe, esthetic cacique whom power led into a gluttonous life and deserved death when he visited Acoma. In a natural consequence of character and historical events the author gives a thrilling story of Luis, the young American-born Spaniard, who tried to get justice for the Indians whom the greedy zealots of the Inquisition robbed for their own profit and that of wealthy Spanish nobles. He tells of the relation of Luis and his relation with three women: Condesa, the courtesan, Kashana, the Acoma maiden, and Barbara, the Spanish aristocrat whose love for the wholesome desert country around Santa Fe ennobled her life more and more as she saw through the wickedness of her aristocratic surroundings. The contrast of the corruption and intrigue of Mexico City with the simplicity and integrity of the Acoma cacique who fasted in nakedness for the sins of the whole tribe; the sunrise and sunset of the Sangre de Christo (Blood of Christ) Mountains near Santa Fe; the smell of the mesquite burning from countless fireplaces in the morning air—all this to those of us who have lived with and known the Pueblo Indians and have loved their “way of life,” makes this book one to be enjoyed and remembered.

The Hopi Indian, by Harry C. james, Caxton Press, Caldwell, Idaho, 1956.

Mr. James knows much about the Hopi from scores of years spent near them. He tells of the beating to death of the Hopi Juan Cuno of Oraibi in 1655 by Friar de Guerra. He says that “the best of the Hopi have no desire to lead the easy, parasitical life of the rationed, clothed, housed, and protected ‘ward’.”

America’s Concentration Camps, by Carlos B. Embry, David McKay Co., N.Y., 1956.

The author is a liberal southern editor who sympathizes with the Indians but would solve their problems by assimilating them into white society. Until 1834 an American citizen had to have a passport to enter Indian territory. And the Red-Cloud Treaty was the only one ever made by the U.S. where the enemy received all its demands.

Conquest of Violence: The Gandhian Philosophy of Conflict, by Prof. Joan V. Boudurant, Princeton University Press, 1958.

“Oppression Ceases,” Gandhi taught his followers, “when people cease to fear the bayonet.” Unlike regular anarchists Gandhi sought by negotiation with politicians to achieve the stateless anarchist ideal, and also unlike most anarchists he was able to develop both personal and mass resistance to the state and to exploitation and to overcome the government. The author quotes Bob Ludlow in an article in the CW as saying, “It is the political element that will destroy Gandhi’s teachings in India for he did not realize that Satyagraha must be united with an anti-state philosophy.” The author replies, “nevertheless with Satyagraha as the functioning socio-political technique of action, anarchism could conceivably result.” Gandhi said, quoting from the Gita that “when there is no desire for fruit, there is no temptation for untruth.” Gandhi says, “Do not resist arrest; if taken prisoner, behave in an exemplary manner… do not expect guarantees for maintenance of dependents.” Courtesy to the opponent was shown in India when “Satyagrahis ceased their civil disobedience at midday because of the hardship this would work on European opponents who were less accustomed to extreme heat… and postponing an action to spare the Englishman for his Easter Sunday services and celebration.” The author quotes Gandhi as saying, “I do believe that when there is only a choice between cowardice and violence, I would advise violence… Non-violent conduct is never demoralizing whereas cowardice always is.” Fasting is primarily a penance and according to Gandhi “there can be no penance where the accused person is not conscious of having committed a wrong… Fasting… no one who has not earned the right to do so should use this weapon.” The author shows an understanding of anarchism when she says, “Anarchists urge freedom from politics rather than political freedom.”

The True Believer, by Eric Hoffer, Harper, N.Y., 1951.

“Who is the true-believer?… He’s a guilt-ridden hitchhiker who thumbs a ride on every cause from Christianity to Communism… When we renounce self and become part of a compact whole, we not only renounce personal advantage but are also rid of our personal responsibility.” I read and reread this thought-provoking and cynical book. Most of what he says is true for nearly every “true believer” you meet, but it is not necessarily true of all, and these few like Debs, Tolstoy, Gandhi, etc. who acted and whose truth somehow diffused itself in the hearts of people rather than to be organized into corruption. To cast his incomplete self on the bandwagon after the after pioneers have blazed the trail; to take benefits of the union scale of wages after having scabbed in thought or deed for years; by the impact of his numbers to water down the purity of any cause. “The mass leader: this strength lies in his blind spots and in plugging all outlets but one.”

The Autobiography of Big Bill Haywood (reprint from 1929) International Publishers, 381 Fourth Avenue, New York City, 1958.

In the face of a 20-year prison sentence, Haywood was asked in court if he was conspiring to interfere with the profits of the munition makers. He answered, “We are conspiring to prevent the making of profits on labor in any industry. We are conspiring against the dividend makers. We are conspiring against rent and interest. We want to establish a new society where people can live without profit, without dividends, without rent and without interest if it is possible—and it is possble—if people will live normally, live like human beings should live. I would say that if that is a conspiracy we are conspiring.” Wonderful words! An old “Molly Maguire” taught him unionism when he was working in the mines in Nevada as a boy. He helped found the I.W.W. whose slogan was, “overtime is scab time, any time there are some working no time.” He was born in Salt Lake City. He married Nevada Jane Minor and delivered the baby himself on a lonesome ranch. He attended two terms in a parochial school in Salt Lake City and knew Father Hagerty, who it is said wrote the I.W.W. preamble. Through the famous Moyer, Haywood, and Pettibone trial when the stool pigeon Harry Orchard perjured himself and Darrow finally won the case, and through the days of 1917 when hundreds of I.W.W.’s were in jail against the war Haywood stood firm. The I.W.W. was the only union that had the rule that “any one who joined the army, the militia, or the police was forever denied membership.” Haywood was a lover of centralized power in administering the I.W.W. Many of this union became Communists and went to Russia. I disagree emphatically with his skipping bail and going to Russia, but I tend to remember his good fiight up to that time rather than to castigate him. His wife died in 1917 and his two daughters also passed away before Haywood died of diabetes in Moscow, May 18, 1928.

Attorney For The Damned, by Clarence Darrow, Edited by Arthur Weinberg. Simon and Shuster, N.Y., 1957.

This is a lengthy book which gives excerpts from some of the greatest summations which Darrow gave over the years, but one would have to feel the tone, see the light in his eyes, and observe the swing from nonchalant humor to heart-rending emotion to know how he swayed juries and never lost a case. His summations lasted at times for three days with never the use of a note. In 1894, when he was general attorney for the Chicago and Northwestern Railroad, and Debs with his American Railway Union had a strike on the line, Darrow resigned his good job and represented Debs. He is known for his speech to the prisoners of Cook County jail:

Preachers will tell you that you should be good then you will get rich and be happy. Of course we know that people do not get rich by being good, and that is the reason why so many of you people try to get rich some other way, only you do not understand how to do it quite as well as the fellow outside.

And again Darrow said, “If a doctor were called upon to treat typhoid fever he would probably try to find out what kind of milk or water the patient drank, and perhaps clean out the well so that no one else could get typhoid from the same source. But if a lawyer was called upon, he would give him thirty days in jail, and then he would think that nobody else would ever dare to take it (that is the typhoid fever). If the patient got well in 15 days, he would be kept until his time was up; if the disease was worse at the end of 30 days, the patient would be released because his time was out.”

Anarchism by Paul Eltzbacher, Libertarian Book Club, GPO Box 842, N.Y. 1.

This book is mentioned by Kropotkin in the Encyclopedia Brittanica as the best book on anarchism, and Alexander Berkman told me in Atlanta prison that this was the one book I should read. The author analyzes Godwin, Proudhon, Stirner, Bakunin, Kropotkin, Tucker, and Tolstoy as to law, the state and property and as to means of achieving the revolution. I agree with Tolstoy in critical idealistic anarchism, no law in the future, no legal relation, and pacifism. I agree with Godwin in no law in the future and no legal relation. I agree with Tucker in pacifism. I agree with Bakunin in having both individual and collective property. I agree with Proudhon in critical idealistic anarchism. There is also an article by Rudolph Rocker on anarchist communes in Spain and other of his ideas. This book as a guide to the anarchist writings is invaluable, for anarchism remains, if taken with the pacifist approach, as the only hope, for all other roads lead to tyranny and death.

Anarchism, by George Woodcock, World Co., 2231 W. 110 St., Cleveland, Ohio, 1962. $1.95 paperback.

“Anarchism has thriven best in the lands of the sun, where it is easy to dream of golden ages of ease and simplicity, yet where the clear light also brightens the shadows of existing misery.”

“Two recent historians of anarchism, Alain Heslier and Claude Harmel, have discovered the first anarchist in Jean Meslier, the 18th century cure of Etrepigny, whose resentment against the ecclesiastical and civil authorities of his time festered into a great Testament which he left to his rural parishioners (it was intercepted after his death by the Church authorities and never reached the farmers for whom it was meant) and in which he denounced authority of every kind and advocated a bucolic society based on friendship among peasant communities.”

And Jacques Roux, a country priest, in 1790 led a group called the Enrages, said that land belonged to all equally, and burned chateaux. He was sentenced to death by a revolutionary tribunal, but he cheated the guillotine by killing himself, saying, “to die placing liberty above law is the death of an anarchist.”

“In Italy on Aug. 1, 1877, Father Fortini, the priest of Letino, welcomed the anarchists as ‘true apostles sent by the Lord to preach His divine law’… Guided by Father Fortini, the anarchist band set off for the next village of Gallo, where Father Tamburini came out to welcome them, and went from house to house, shouting to the people, ‘fear nothing. They are honest folk.’”

Tolstoy said that “the man who wishes to abolish the state must cease to co-operate with it, refuse military service, police service, jury service, the payment of taxes.” “Perhaps the most impressive example of Tolstoyan influence in the contemporary Western world is—ironically in view of Tolstoy’s distrust of organized churches—the Roman Catholic group associated in the United States with the Catholic Worker and particularly with that saintly representative of Christian Anarchism, Dorothy Day.”

In Spain Pi Y Margall, a Catalonian bank clerk, was the first active anarchist. Pio Baroja, the author of Red Dawn, was a great anarchist writer. “The Inquisition effectively stifled any tendency toward religious dissent during the 16th century, anarchism has in fact taken on the character ofa delayed Reformation movement.… All anarchism, has of course, a moral-religious element which distinguishes it from ordinary political movements, but this element is far more developed in Spain than elsewhere… for in the eyes of the Spanish libertarians the Catholic Church occupies the position of anti-Christ in the Christian world… the anger of an intensely religious people who feel they have been deserted and deceived.”

The conclusion of the author is well stated: “The great anarchists call on us to stand on our own moral feet like a generation of princes, to become aware of justice as an inner fire, and to learn that the still, small voices of our own hearts speak more truly than the choruses of propaganda that daily assault our outer ears. ‘Look into the depths of your own beings.’ In this insistence that freedom and moral self-realization are interdependent, and one cannot live without the other, lies the ultimate lesson of true anarchism.”

Chapter 19

Questions and Answers

1950–1964

Over the U.S.

Questions and Answers

Why do you deny the authority of the state and accept the authority of the Catholic Church?
Why do you refuse to pay taxes when Christ said to render unto Caesar?
What about Christ chasing the money changers out of the temple? Does this not justify war?
What would you do if Russia attacked us?
You are not Catholics, you are Communists?
You are not practical.
You Catholic Workers knock the bourgeois society yet you depend upon donations from the bourgeois to feed you.
How are you going to run things without cops and soldiers if we abolished them all tomorrow?
Why are you so critical of other people? Is it kind?
Why do you fast in public when Christ said to do this in secret in your closet?
Why don’t you work like other men do?
Christ ate meat. Do you think you are better than Christ by not eating meat?
Why don’t you vote for the good man for office? You just help the bad man by your negative attitude.
Would you defend some one dear to you who is being attacked?

“Why do you deny the authority of the state and accept the authority of the Catholic Church?”

Because I consider the function of the state as essentially exploitative and immoral with its denial of the Sermon on the Mount in the return of evil for evil in courts, prisons, and war. While the Church in practice approves of exploitation and war this is not an essential doctrine of the Church but a perversion of what Christ taught and the early Christians lived.

Around 1845 Thoreau was asked to pay taxes to the Church and he refused, saying that he was not a member, and asked for a piece of paper on which he wrote, “I am signing off something I never joined.” He then asked for another piece of paper on which he “signed off” from the state into which was born but never joined. Likewise I have seceded from the state and give it very little. To churches where no bingo or gambling prevails I will give generously, but to commercialized churches I give a nickel.

When I became a Christian I did so because I felt Christ was a rebel against the same old eye-for-an-eye policy which has made the world a shambles. When I became a Catholic later I did so because I was first drawn to the pacifist-anarchist policy of the Catholic Worker, and came to see like Karl Stern, that I brought with me into the Church all that was good from Tolstoy and Gandhi. So the Church that I joined was the real one founded by that St. Peter who said to obey God rather than man. I accept the authority of the Pope on the essential matters of faith when he speaks ex Cathedra, but on matters like anarchism and pacifism where he differs I am free to follow my understanding of the Sermon on the Mount. In Boston Father Feeney said that no one but a Catholic could go to Heaven. That is the line in Spain but not in Boston, so he was excommunicated. On television here I was asked if I believed in the infallibility of the Pope and I answered that I did when he was infallible. When he talked through his hat his opinion could be no better than that of anyone else. So his views on Franco, Communism, war, etc. are worth as much as they are worth in fact, and no sanctity need be given to them.

If I go to the wall and push a button which says light, another which says heat, and another which says refrigeration and I get the results expected I do not tear down the wall to see how the wires are put together, for, not being an electrician, I could not put them back together again. I accepi the word of the electrician and leave the wiring as it is. But I do not take the word of the electrician about Franco, war, capitalism, etc. Likewise I accept what the Holy Father says about the Faith but not on matters of Franco, war, capitalism, etc.

The Church allows me more freedom than the state. The state has arrested me thirty times, and the Church through police only twice. Out of courtesy I will address the authorities of the state in good humor and announce my proposed acts of disobedience, but I have no hope nor intention of reforming the state. I try to live as a good Catholic and I have some hope that this leaven may help to bring to light the teachings of Christ and the early Christians and be a leaven in the commercialized mass of the Church.

There is no contradiction in my denial of the authority of the state and accepting that of the Church unless the Church makes me be a servant of the state in issues which I consider immoral, which please God, I hope I will never do.

“Why do you refuse to pay taxes when Christ said to render unto Caesar”?

Dorothy Day gave the best short answer, quoting St. Hilary, “The less you have of Caesar’s the less you have to give to Caesar.” Those who believe in rendering unto Caesar will still do so no matter what I may say. To those who may have a doubt I will give several thoughts to build up their “render unto God” instead of to Caesar. When Jesus was asked what was the greatest commandment He told them that the first one was to love the Lord with all your heart and the second one was like unto it, to love your neighbor as yourself. “Who is my neighbor?” asked those who wished to argue. Then Jesus told the story of the Good Samaritan.

Again Jesus was taken up into a high mountain by the devil who told Him if He fell down and worshipped him He could have the whole world and in fact would not have to pay any taxes at all. Jesus told the devil to go back where he came from.

Then again He was asked if He believed in paying taxes to Caesar. In those days different districts had different money and the Jews had to change their money into that of Rome, so Jesus asked, not for a Jewish coin, but for a coin with which tribute was paid, saying “Why tempt me?” Looking at the coin, He asked whose image and superscription was there inscribed and was told that it was Caesar’s. Those who tried to trick Him knew that if He said that taxes were to be paid to Caesar He would be attacked by the mobs who hated Caesar, and if He refused to pay taxes there would always be some traitor to turn Him in. His mission was not to fight Caesar as Barabbas had done, but it was to chase the moneychangers out of the Temple and to establish His own Church. Whether He winked as much as to say that any good Jew knew that Caesar did not deserve a thing as He said, “Render unto Caesar what is Caesar’s and unto God what is God’s,” or not, no one knows.

The U.S. government considers that I owe over a thousand dollars in income taxes and if I offered them a penny they would consider it an insult. Christ insulted Caesar when He offered Caesar a penny.

Once in Phoenix I had announced that on Monday I would picket the tax man for a week. On a Saturday night a policeman told me that I could not sell papers on a certain corner. I could have stood on my rights and insisted and spent the night and Sunday and Monday in jail and not been able to be on hand for my main battle. Jesus had to choose His battleground. Now it was also said to Pilate by Christ that he would have no power over Him unless it came from God. Despite what anyone says each of us has to decide for himself whether to put the emphasis upon pleasing Caesar or pleasing God. We may vary in our reasons for drawing the line here or there as to how much we render unto Caesar. I make my decision when I remember that Christ said to the woman caught in sin, “Let him without sin first cast a stone at her.” I remember His “Forgive seventy times seven,” which means no Caesar at all with his courts, prisons, and war.

“What about Christ chasing the money changers out of the Temple? Does this not justify war?”

Christ was “true God and true man.” He was hungry and thirsty and He hungered and suffered and bled on the Cross. In this He was the man. He saw the Jewish Temple made a den of thieves, and evil being done by hypocrites who kept the letter of the law—taking legal advantage of the rate of exchange and of technicalities that the poor and untaught knew little about. As He suffered when scourged so did he suffer at this blasphemy and He chased the cattle that would not move without the lash. Whether He actually lashed the money changers or whether their guilt made them flee we do not know. But we do know that He did not try to exterminate their families or to imprison and kill them. He used no man-made law against them. “Let him who is without sin first cast a stone.” So Jesus was without sin and was the only one who had the right to chase the evil men out of the Temple. And for this among other things they killed Him.

Likewise during the agony in the garden when He knew that Peter, despite his protestation of great faith, would soon betray Him those three times, His flesh was tired and He told Peter to sell his clothes and buy a sword. Peter said there were two swords. Jesus replied. “That is enough.” Then when Malchus was arresting Jesus, Peter took one of the swords and cut off the ear of Malchus. Jesus was God and He did not tell Peter to cut off the other ear, but performed His last miracle by healing the ear. He then disarmed Peter and all of us by saying, “Put up again thy sword into its place; for all that take the sword shall perish by the sword.”

The whole essence of the Sermon on the Mount is to love the enemy, to turn the other cheek, and to return good for evil. The enemies of the Jews were the Romans. Jesus did not join with the Macabees and Barabbas in violent insurrection against the government. He did not show any hatred toward them and even said that if a Jew was asked according to Roman law to carry the pack of a soldier one mile, he should cheerfully carry it two miles instead of grouching about the one mile. What aroused His anger was hypocrisy in the Synagogue. Jesus knew that to exchange a Roman despot for a Jewish despot was not worth dying for. He had a better way which was to overcome the enemy permanently by love. Today we find those who trust in violence, both in the courts and in war, who justify this violence by quoting this passage about the chasing of the money changers out of the Temple. If they would take it in its context they would look at the Churches today with their bingo and selling of chances and charge of admission at the door, all to keep up a big show, and know that He would overturn these tables also.

“What would do if Russia attacked us?”

Kneel and pray for our sins that have brought the attack upon us; and pray for the Russians.

We have scattered obliteration bombing in Bremen, Hamburg, Tokyo, and atomic death in Hiroshima and Nagasaki, and we continue our atomic testing which spreads Strontium 90 over the world. We have spread death over Europe in two wars; now we will learn what it all means here at home. We have taken the sword and now we are dying by the sword. In Dugway, Utah at the U.S. Proving Ground in 1960 “a healthy rabbit died in seventy seconds after a military scientist had placed a droplet of an unnamed nerve agent in the animal’s eye. Sparky, a black mongrel in a glass-enclosed cage, was instantly paralyzed—and rendered painless—when an aerosol was ‘vented’ into the air he breathed,” this being all a part of our chemical, bacteriological and radiological warfare.

“He wins who gets there fustest with the mostest,” said a Southern leader in the Civil War. If we believe in the military way of life we ought to be armed with the most terrible weapons and have the facility of using them quicker than the enemy. To be inefficiently armed is not to be a pacifist. To disarm without ceasing our exploitation would be foolish for we are told in scripture that he who hath great possessions keepeth them by being well-armed until he who is stronger taketh them from him, but to trust in the Lord and Spiritual values rather than in much possessions. A clean about-face toward the principles of love and brotherhood of the early Christians is needed. And we are the nation least probable to acknowledge our sins and repent. The whole history of our country has been militaristic from the time we tried to exterminate the Indians to our Mexican and Spanish American wars. And our dollar diplomacy in the banana republics and our stranglehold through loans to most of the South American countries is a scandal, let alone our support of Franco, Salazar, Chiang, and until their overthrow seemed at hand, of Batista and Trujillo. We have spoken for years of the natural result of capitalist imperialism and of the need to expand. As Randolph Bourne said, “war is the health of the state.” Even if now war has become suicidal our exploiters must needs live up to the tradition of all exploiters.

So if Russia attacked us with missiles or atom bombs, all that we would do, if by some miracle we would be alive, is to help those nearest to us in whatever way we could. We would obey any necessary routing or traffic regulations but it is likely that we would find it necessary to circumvent the red tape of the bureaucrats and help people on our own as we did during the depression and as we do now. By our contact with the enemy we would not show fear or hatred and by our actions we would try to make them ashamed of their oppressive tactics, but we wouldn’t “preach” to them. With Wall Street destroyed maybe some of us could get together in small communes and live like we ought to without exploitation or government, but by mutual consent.

“You are not Catholics, you are Communists”

Call up the Chancery office in New York City and they will tell you that we are Catholics and that they are not for or against us. We are members of the Catholic Press Association for twenty-seven years and this would not continue if we were Communists.

Now as to being Communists it is true that we accept the Marxian analysis of what is the matter with capitalist society, but as to what is to be done about it we differ. Communists want the state to do everything, and after the dictatorship of the proletariat the state will wither away and we will have the stateless society, which is anarchism. The anarchists don’t believe in any state at all and they agree with Lord Acton that “power corrupts and absolute power tends to corrupt absolutely.”

With the Communists we believe in

The Economic Interpretation of History
Which means that for the most part the way people make their living determines how they think. As the western Catholic sheepherder who clips wool and the Wall Street Catholic broker who clips coupons: they pray the same but they think differently about life.
Surplus Value
If I earn $40 a day for my boss and get $10 in wages I can only buy back $10 worth and the balance piles up and we have depressions and wars.
The Class Struggle.
Between those who work for a living and those who own for a living there is a struggle and we are on the side of the have-nots; and we choose to live poor among them and help them fight in a nonviolent way and a nonpolitical way against exploiters. And where those who run the Church side with the exploiters we oppose them and side with the exploited even if they are Communists, being critical of them as anarchists and pacifists should be, but with sympathy.

“You are not practical”

I am the most practical fellow you can find. The dictionary says being practical is “pertaining or relating to practice or action.” You might say that we anarchists are the original “do-it—yourself” folks, for we do not depend upon politicians and bureaucrats to do things for us.

Being an anarchist means being responsible for the needs of yourself and others without being told or ordered by authorities. While walking to the Post Office one morning for the mail I saw a block ahead of me a two-by-four full of spikes fall from a truck into the middle of the street right at a crosswalk. Dozens of cars whizzed by and scores of pedestrians edged around it but no one picked it up, for they didn’t put it there, and neither did I. But I picked it up and put it in the container for waste by the curb. Another time when I had been fasting for ten days and picketing the tax man here in New York City I noticed a huge bale of paper junk fall from the rear of a truck into the very middle of the intersection at Varick and West Houston Streets. No one did anything about it until I laid aside my sign and pushing with my shoulder with all my might I finally edged it over to the curb. Likewise when walking the roads in the country I always removed nails, glass, dead cats, limbs of trees, etc., which would impede traffic, so that I think the government owes me money for my scavenger work. I do not feel a bit guilty in using the roads for which I pay no income tax to build.

If being practical means piling up money and worrying yourself sick saving for a sick day, or to retire with your ulcer, then I am not practical. If organizing thousands of people into a group promising to do good, or pledging themselves to revolutionary action is practical, then I am not practical. When I have been picketing the tax office I did not need a committee to coordinate or regulate me, for I can organize myself. This is what the one-man revolution is supposed to do.

“You Catholic Workers knock the bourgeois society yet you depend upon donations from the bourgeois to feed you.”

Who else lives among the poor twenty-four hours a day? Sure, “we comfort the afilicted and afflict the comfortable” until the latter shell out voluntarily to help us do the things that need to be done, that the state neglects to do. We do get money in small bits from many people who are poor; very little of our money comes in large amounts. We refused to apply to a large foundation that offered us money, and we returned $3,500 interest to the City of New York because we did not believe in interest. One millionaire gave us a thousand dollars for Christmas for helping someone he had known on the Bowery. The next year he wanted to give us more and wondered if it was deductible from his income tax. We told him that we were not an “accredited” charity organization, and that he would have to give from his heart and not from his deductible surplus. We didn’t get it.

We couldn’t live in this society and get our money from anyone else; and whatever money we as writers or speakers get we turn in to feed the poor.

“How are you going to run things without cops and soldiers if we abolished them tomorrow?”

We are not going to do anything tomorrow or the next day except perhaps die from the atom bomb. The welfare state is here to feed us with bread and circuses into complete senility. Even then no one is ever going to get all people to think alike—the Catholic Church has been trying it for two thousand years and they have millions saying the same words but their quality is nothing to boast about. For as the Indians said, “If everyone thought the same everyone would want my wife.”

This wholesale mass idea of doing things is what is the matter with this world. There will be cops and soldiers for a long time yet. I have already resigned from the need of cops or soldiers to protect me for I rely on a greater power. Obviously if I do not believe in voting or shooting, I, or a million like myself, could not begin to think of overturning society. What I have done is to remove the need of my dependence upon these instruments of violence.

Democrats and Republicans do not make good anarchists. When we have enough pacifist anarchists in any geographical area who resign from the state and its coercive measures then we will begin to have a small anarchist society. The radical Hopi Indians have had it for centuries without being anarchists in the true sense of the word for their action comes more from a communal tradition.

There is no reason why people interested in the transportation industry could not meet in local, regional, national, and international conventions, much as chess players, scientists, and others do, and discuss how best to solve the problems of transportation in any given area or weather condition. A railroader, a truck driver, an airplane pilot, and a steamboat man all are prejudiced as to the efficiency of their own way of travel. But when profits are not the measure, but service, then the true solution can be arrived at. Not by baby kissers or banjo players or lame ducks appointed to commissions to regulate commerce, but by the very men who do the work. A decoration of, say, The Order of Frank Lloyd Wright, would be a greater incentive than political glory. Anything that the government does, except make war, all of us could do if we got the idea of doing it, and we could do it better.

“Why are you so Critical of other people? Is this kind?”

There is a great difference between kindness and weakness. To give a derelict a “dime for coffee” because you are too weak to say no, knowing that it is for liquor, or to give money for carfare when a walk of a mile for an able-bodied young man would help to waken him up a little, is also weakness. Sometimes we act through stupidity. In Salt Lake City at our Joe Hill mission a red-faced town bum and an anemic white-faced old man asked me for 80 cents for carfare to go to the bloodbank to sell their blood. They promised faithfully to pay me back that afternoon. I have no regular donors who g1ve me money to pay the rent and utilities and could really not spare even that amount, but I gave it to them. They would not take blood from the old man for he had hardly a pint in him to work on, let alone any to sell, and, of course, the town bum never showed up again. How stupid can a fellow get? With all of my experience I should have known better. To make a decision is a sign of growth, but many of us postpone decisions for we cannot accept the idea that we might be wrong. No matter how humble we may appear, our basic motivation here is pride, and not the humility and kindness that we front to the public.

“I was just going to ask you for a dime,” said a well-heeled, non-Catholic acquaintance of mine to a young man on the Bowery who had just asked him for a dime for a cup of coffee. The young man looked dazed, stammered a bit, and reaching in his pocket took out a dime and a nickel and handed my friend a dime. This was too much for my friend whose conscience hurt him. He ran after the derelict saying, “Here I’ll trade you the dime for this quarter,” which he did.

The moral, as I told my friend, is not to be sentimental and weakminded. My friend robbed the derelict on the Bowery of whatever faith in human nature he might have had. To do one good deed that day would have perhaps built him up, but now he would think, “I have met another phony.”

There are people who have been babied by their relatives and as they whine their way through life most people are too “kind” to jerk them to their feet. One such person stumbled up to me, tramping on my toes and excusing himself by saying that he hoped he was not in the way. Itold him he sure as hell was. And what could he do to help. I told him he could keep out of my way and sit in a corner. I said this in an alert manner and not with venom, and finally after some years there is no animosity between us. It was not unkind of me to educate this young man to be less rather than more of a nuisance. To encourage nitwits is not to help them. Useless conversation just to be saying something is the worst waste of time. The congenital blabbermouth, even of pious words, needs conversation like I need a third eyebrow. In our office and in every city where I have lived, there is one or more of such meddlesome pious souls sputtering superlatives to cover up their ignorance. They cannot be squelched, but it is weakness and not kindness to encourage them.

There are too many “Uncle Toms” who by their sycophantic attitude mess up values. I have met such ones who praise me and agree with me when I know that they have just the faintest idea of what it is all about. These phonies do not need encouragement.

There are able men who are basically sentimentalists. They enthuse about “the revolution” or they are trigger-happy about “dying for Christ” in some protest, but when it rains they run for cover, “to live again to run away another day.” These folks are not insincere, but they clutter up any movement with their bubbling froth which soon settles down.

Then there is the clever manipulator who is sincere, but who is determined never to sweat overmuch or to neglect being paid for overtime if by chance he is found on the job after the whistle blows. To contrast these pie-cards of today with Debs, Mother Bloor, Mother Jones, and Bill Haywood, is to know the difference between the real McCoy and the counterfeit.

I have worked with radicals in and out of jails for half a century. There is not one of them whom I have met that I would not gladly meet and work with again, but there are several who are hard for me to take, and a little bit of them goes a long way.

Walking through our office just now I notice a score of derelicts, each one of whom if you take them by themselves with even the doctored history which they have seen fit to tell us, cannot be blamed overly much. They are weak and they have been buffeted by “the system.” To these folks I am not critical, but neither do I fall for their alibis, but good naturedly refuse them.

In a mushy atmosphere of pollyanna optimism anyone who clears the air by calling things by their right names and facing facts runs the chance of being called arrogant and egotistic. This could be, but I submit that if taken as a part of my whole life and philosophy I have, by placing myself in a limited pacifist-anarchist-Catholic sphere, put myself in a glass house. If so I must needs take whatever stones come my way. I have the right by my life of integrity to criticize, but I must also take whatever criticism comes my way in all good humor. If I hand it out I have to take it.

When speaking at a Catholic girl’s high school in Tucson I had occasion to deflate an arrogant young priest who was misquoting Christ. A girl brought up on respect for the Cloth was amazed and innocently asked me, “Mr. Hennacy, do you think that you are better than other people?” “Sure, but I have too good manners to say so,” I replied.

Another time a spoiled and arrogant priest wanted to know if I was “holier than thou.” I told him that I hoped by Christ I was, for if I wasn’t I would be in a hell of a fix. I used this blunt method to deflate his spurious piety.

Those who criticize me me for criticizing others, are themselves criticizing, and by what right are they above criticism themselves? I do not claim to be above criticism; I am not going to allow such accusations to keep me from exposing fraud.

“Why do you fast in public when Christ said to do this in secret in your closet?”

If I was doing this for any vainglory it would be terrible, but it is, like the small top of the iceberg appearing above water, only an indication of the huge mass beneath. It is only the result of a dedicated life which appears because of an emergency in the war-mad world, meant to say “Danger” to those about to be wrecked. You can’t obey all scripture at once. You have to choose. Christ also said to “shout from the housetops,” and “not to hide your light under a bushel.” If I did not speak and fast the very stones would cry out.

I also fasted before I was a Catholic. I do this as a penance for all of our sins. I do not do it to coerce or embarass my enemy the government, and the tax and war officials. I do it to waken up the timid pacifists who know better and don’t do better. Someone has to raise the ante of what should be expected of a Christian and a Catholic. Talk is cheap and in this gluttonous world fasting can be a means of waking up some people.

If anyone thinks the mainspring of my action is egotism I would ask by what measure they value their own actions. I am willing to be judged as a man, not a mouse, by my fruits, both now and hereafter. My message is not meant for those unable to receive it.

“Why don’t you work like other men do?”

I could answer this in these days of automation with the old wobblie refrain, “How in the hell can I work when there is no work to do?” for they work for companies where a withholding tax is taken from their pay for war. I have to bootleg my work, and work by the day where there is no tax taken out, such as migrant work or in self made jobs such as speaking in colleges and schools.

I work for my keep just now here at the CW, getting up early for the mail, recording the income, answering letters, selling CWs each day on the streets which is much harder than walking around, speaking upon call at the office to visitors, and when called upon to do so travelling over the country. Now, since November of 1961, I am in Salt Lake City directing the Joe Hill House of Hospitality and St. Joseph’s Refuge, collecting food daily to feed thousands who come here from the freights. I will describe this elsewhere in more detail in this book. If anyone thinks that sleeping on the floor by the door with from thirty to fifty people snoring, coughing, mumbling in the after affects of liquor—answering the door a dozen times a night as drunks pound for entrance—is fun, let them try it.

I am sixty-nine and I do not ask the state for any social security or old age pension. I have worked up to the age of nineteen on a farm, and eleven years not long ago at stoop labor on the ranches of the southwest. I have worked eleven years in Milwaukee as a social worker, and six years on a farm near there.

I fast and picket the tax office each year and several times have fasted for over forty days and picketed. If you think this is easy work, try it.

“Christ ate meat. Do you think you are better than Christ by not eating meat?”

If He hadn’t eaten fish He would have had a hard time; that’s what His disciples were for the most part: fishermen. I am a vegetarian for sentimental reasons: I don’t like to kill animals and I don’t want someone else to do it for me. And for pacifistic reasons I won’t kill capitalists.

John the Baptist, Buddha, Gandhi, and the Trappists, Camaldolese, and other Orders are vegetarians. It is a matter of where a person draws the line. The Essenes of Christ’s time were vegetarians and He did not reprimand them. He was asked why He and His disciples did not fast as John’s disciples did. He reached a different class of people: wine-bibbers and gluttons for whom the Gospel was also meant.

In old English law a butcher is not allowed on a murder jury for fear that his occupation as a killer would make him too hardhearted towards the prisoner before the court. Primitive man had to kill and eat or starve to death. He had no supermarkets where he could buy vegetables. Outside of the Eskimos who have little vegetation there is no excuse for modern man consuming so much meat. And doctored up before they are killed to produce more fat, and preserved by questionable chemicals. The eating of these fowl and animals is not conducive to spiritual or bodily health.

Those who wish to kill their own animals for food are welcome to do so, and for those who wish to be kind to animals the best advice is the vegetarian slogan: “Be kind to animals by not eating them.”

There is the cartoon of the Father Bear with a gun pointed at the hunter who is asking for mercy because “of my wife and children at home.” The bear replied that the hunter had killed his wife and children, not for food, but only to show off to his friends. “I won’t do it again,” promised the man. “You won’t have a chance to do it again,” said the bear as he aimed his gun.

“Why don’t you vote for the good man for ofiice? You just help the bad man by your negative attitude.”

A good man is worse than a bad man for he finds a good reason for doing a bad thing that a bad man couldn’t figure out, so he lends his goodness to evil. The devil doesn’t have horns, he has a halo as big as a hoop. We elected Wilson to keep us out of war, and Roosevelt when he said, “I tell you again, and again, and again, that no boys will be sent across to foreign soil.”

A good man cannot get any legislation passed or enforced unless he plays ball with the bad men who have a head start on him and surround him. He has to vote for their post office, harbor graft, or other larceny-minded bills to even get his bill out of committee.

I only voted once in my life and that was in 1916 when I voted for Allan Benson, the Socialist candidate for President, who was against the war. And before I was out of Atlanta Prison, Benson was for the war. I might as well have stayed at home. My capitalistic brother is not a pacifist nor an anarchist, but he had sense enough never to vote in his life, as he does not trust politicians.

In 1960, I was asked to run for Vice President on the Vegetarian ticket, but of course I refused to do so. Both major party candidates believe in the return of evil for evil in courts, prisons, and war. The Socialist parties believe in violence and Socalism, so as a pacifist and an anarchist I could not vote for them.

I have already seceded from the idea of government. If I voted for a pacifist and he was not elected, I would be honor-bound to obey the winner, who of course, this time (1960) would either be Kennedy or Nixon, both of whom believe in greater armaments and in war as a means of defeating Communism, although, of course, they say they believe in peace. I vote every day by my anarchistic actions.

“Would you defend someone dear to you who is being attacked?”

Christ was defended by Peter who cut off the ear of the attacker. Christ gave the answer when He said, “Put up thy sword; he that taketh the sword shall perish by the sword.”

Pacifism does not mean to stand by and do nothing. It means to do something: to use the strongest weapon, spiritual force, rather than the weaker weapon, violence. But you can’t use it if you don’t have it. First, you must not be afraid, for even animals can smell fear. Second, you must feel that there is good in your attacker. Third, you must have the agility of mind to speak sincerely without preaching in “very few words” that will deflect the violence. This can’t be learned in a book. It has to flow from a life of integrity, with the minimum of show-off. If you invade an army camp you must not expect them to act like pacifists toward you; you are asking for trouble.

I hope I would defend those dear to me as I have defended myself many times, by spiritual understanding rather than by violence. But none of us can be sure until the last chapter how we will actually act in a given circumstance. My friend Bayard Rustin was asked this question, and he said that once he acted in one way and once he acted in another way. He was in a barricaded cabin in the deep South with other Negroes where the surrounding KKK were masked ready to lynch them. Bayard opened the door and stood with folded arms, saying, “You came here to lynch us; start with me.” They went home in shame. If he had spoken in anger and called them bastards he would not have won. Another time he was in a taxi on the Bowery and he saw a Negro being beaten by two white men. He jumped out and kicked and hit the white men in the appropriate places and drew the Negro in the taxi away to safety. My friend Ned Richards was in the Near East at the time of World War I. He was a young man doing missionary work and was the oldest male among women and children at the time when a crazy Armenian was standing on a hill nearby and shooting at each one as they came out of the house. After a time Ned walked with hand outstretched, a perfect target, up the hill to the Armenian whose gun was pointed at him. The Armenian handed him the gun and commenced to weep.

An AP dispatch tells in Bloomington, Illinois in 1936 of two bandits who held up a small restaurant where a girl and her father were the owners. The girl asked them why they held the place up. They said they were hungry. “Sit down and eat,” she said. “You will call the cops,” the replied. “You are between me and the phone and the cop went by half an hour ago,” was her answer. They ate and whispered and returned the money. If she had screamed when they came in she would likely have been shot as well as robbed. Another time two robbers held up a filling station run by Father Divine’s followers in Philadelphia. “Peace, Brother,” said the attendants when told by the robbers, “Your money or your life.” However the guns were brandished or whatever the admonition was to hand over the money, all that the men said was “Peace, Brother.” It was impossible to rob such people, so the robbers went away.

Chapter 20

Joe Hill House

Salt Lake City, Utah

1961–present

Time: May 1961 to Present
Place: Salt Lake City, and West to the Coast

After speaking here in April of 1961 at the University I hurried home to New York City to take part in the air raid refusal. 2,000 protested and some were arrested, but few leaders, so I came toward Salt Lake City. Arriving in Cleveland, Ohio to visit my mother and brother and sisters I had a phone call from Mary Lathrop in New York City, saying that she had quit her job and wanted to come with me to Salt Lake City to help start the Joe Hill House. Mary’s father had been a Communist organizer so she knew the radical part of the CW message. She had been a Catholic only a short time. She had met my mother while traveling with Dorothy before. We left for Notre Dame where I had several meetings, staying at the home of Terry McKiernan, who has the House of Bread; then to Nauvoo where we saw the grave of Joseph Smith, and I spoke to the Catholic nuns at their school. Mary had been here with Dorothy previously. Then to visit my daughter Carmen in Santa Fe, a week with Phil Burnham in Tucson where I had a meeting at the Allen’s; and a week in Phoenix visiting my many friends. Joe Craigmyle drove us up to the Hopi and back to Flagstaff where we stayed with Platt and Barbara Cline, going to the bottom of the Grand Canyon, before coming to Salt Lake City.

Here we found work picking cherries, hoeing beets, etc. I irrigated one night for a Mormon and got odd jobs washing dishes in a restaurant or unloading trucks. Mary got jobs at housework. We visited the town of Layton about 20 miles north trying to get work in the fields, and also talked to the local priest but he was not a bit interested in any work among the migrants. A friend told us that a Catholic student at the University had raised $240 for us to start a House, so we looked around and found this location near the employment office and skid row. A friend in the east gave us $100 to pay the rent ahead. We got two months free rent and paid the two months ahead which brought us up to November First. Meanwhile I slept on the floor here and we looked around for furnishings, carrying bits of lumber from the alleys on our way from Mass early in the morning. Ren Mabey, a seminarian and ex-Mormon whom I had met several years before in Mt. Angel, Oregon, mopped our floor and gave us a few furnishings. We bought a secondhand small roller-top desk and a rocking chair. When we went to get the money collected for us by the student it turned out that he could not be found, but Mary worked and we were able to make it.

We had picketed that August 6th until August 21st and fasted because of the atom bomb dropped at Hiroshima 16 years before. In our leaflet, headed in old English Thou Shalt Not Kill, we quoted Joseph Smith as saying, “even the Congress of the United States has no power to make a law that would abridge the rights of my religion.” Two young men were sentenced to die at Utah State Prison and their friends asked me to speak at Liberty Park at a protest meeting. The attorney general said that it was against the law to picket the prison, so I wrote to the sheriff and the warden saying that Mary and I had picketed at Sing Sing and we would picket here. The young men got a reprieve the night before the execution and we did not have to picket. The radio and television gave us good coverage and the afternoon daily, The Deseret News (Mormon) had a headline: “‘Anarchists’ Picket In City Against Taxes, Killing.” I had met the brother of Ernie Linford, one of the editors of the Morning paper, the Tribune, owned mostly by the Catholic Kearns family, in Santa Fe, and had looked up Mr. Linford when I came here. In his column he good naturedly headed it saying “Hennacy’s Coming,” and continued: “You may have lived such a sheltered life that you don’t know this one-man-revolution, but you likely will soon know him by reputation, if not personally.” Then he tells of my radical history and intention to open the Joe Hill House. The police did not interfere with our picketing and we were seldom called “Communist.” One young Catholic who had formerly read the CW in Laramie gave us $15 to get the electricity turned on. We met a sort of Rosicrucian who bought us six cots and mattresses, but when he saw the statues that priests from across the track had given us he didn’t come around any more. One of these priests who was head of the Catholic Youth asked me to write an article for their paper against war and capital punishment and to speak to the youth at Lourdes High School, but a few hours before the meeting he told us that the Bishop did not want anything “controversial” discussed. We had written to the Bishop when we came telling him of our plans and sending him our leaflets and asking for an appointment. After six weeks we received a letter from him saying that he did not approve of our activities. We did not expect him to but we thought we might as well be friends with him. The Catholics have eight churches here and the Mormons have 200 so they want to be overly respectable and conservative, so of course anyone half as radical as we were would be out of bounds.

Joe Hill

Joe Hill, born Hillstrom in Sweden, but as he wrote songs for the I.W.W. (The Industrial Workers of the World), the radical union of the first quarter of the century, his name came to be Joe Hill. Big Bill Haywood of Salt Lake City had been one of the organizers of this union which sought to help the transient and the poorly-paid laborer. I had belonged to it from 1912 to 1922. The story goes that they were called “Wobs” because a Chinese restaurant owner who fed them for free during a strike in Seattle couldn’t pronounce “I.W.W.” so as they came in for free eats he would ask them “You Wobble, Wobble?” They would hold meetings on streetcorners and the Salvation Army would sing, so in order to be heard they made up parodies on the Christian hymns. The best known was Joe’s The Preacher and the Slave:

Long-haired preachers come out every night, Try to tell you what’s wrong and what’s right; But when asked ’bout something to eat They will answer with voices so sweet:

Chorus

You will eat, bye and bye, In that glorious land above the sky; Work and pray, live on hay, You’ll get pie in the sky when you die.

And the starvation army they play, And they sing and they clap and they pray. Till they get all your coin on the drum, Then they tell you when you are on the bum:

If you fight hard for children and wife— Try to get something good in this life— You’re a sinner and bad man they tell, When you die you will sure go to hell.

Workingmen of all countries unite, Side for side we for freedom will fight: When the world and its wealth we have gained To the grafters we will sing this refrain:

Last Chorus

You will eat, bye and bye. When you’ve learned how to cook and to fry; Chop some wood, ’twill do you good, And you’ll eat in the sweet bye and bye.

The chorus of The Tramp is especially good:

Tramp, tramp, tramp, keep on a-tramping Nothing doing here for you; If I catch you ’round again, You will wear the ball and chain, Keep on tramping, that’s the best thing you can do.

The I.W.W. called for all those who worked in one industry to belong to one union, as in the Brewers Union. In the 1890s when Eugene V. Debs organized the American Railway Union and everyone who worked for Jim Hill on the Great Northern struck at once they won the strike in a short time. Debs was one of the organizers of the I.W.W. It is said that Father James Hagerty wrote the famous preamble of the I.W.W. which begins with these words:

The working class and the employing class have nothing in common… Between these two classes a struggle must go on until the workers of the world organize as a class, take possession of the earth and the machinery of production, abolish the wage system. Instead of the conservative motto, “A fair day’s wage for a fair day’s work,” we must inscribe on our banner the revolutionary watchword, “Abolish the wage system”… By organizing industrially we are forming the structure of the new society within the shell of the old.

No wonder when in the winter of 1913 there was a strike of 5,000 miners at nearby Park City where Joe worked, and his revolutionary songs were sung “to fan the flames of discontent,” the wealthy Catholic and Mormon mine owners felt disturbed. Joe had been in jail in the free speech fights in San Diego and San Pedro in California. There the authorities did not allow street meetings. Thousands of the Wobs went to jail, sang Joe’s songs, were beaten and killed, but they won freedom to talk. On the famous May Day in 1912 the “bindle stiffs” burned their lousy bunk houses in the lumber camps and there was a revolutionary urge in the air.

On the night of January 10, 1914 a former cop by the name of Morrison, who had been attacked twice by robbers in recent months, was killed in his small grocery store at 8th Street and Southwest Temple by two armed men. The older Morrison son was also killed, the only witness being the 13-year-old younger son. One of the robbers was shot. That same night Joe Hill was shot with the same kind of a bullet as that which the Morrison’s shot at the robber. Joe had Dr. McHugh, former Socialist candidate for Governor, attend to his wound. Later the Dr. turned in a report of the treatment of Joe, and he was arrested and charged with the killing of the Morrisons. He claimed that he had been shot in an affair over a woman, but gentleman as he was, he refused to name any names. It is thought that the girl was Hilda Erickson in Murray, and that a former suitor of hers, a hanger on of the Wobs, by the name of Otto Applequist, was the one who shot Joe. It least Otto was not to be found the next day. It could be that Hilda tried to take the gun away from Otto, and that Joe was shot in the scuffle. There was no reason for Joe to have robbed the Morrisons. In the preliminary hearing the 13-year-old Morrison boy said it was a shorter man than Joe who did the shooting, but at the trial the boy was frightened into saying “It might have been Joe.” The same tactics were used in the trial of Sacco and Vanzetti. Joe fired his inefficient court appointed lawyers but was finally found guilty. While his appeal was going on under the able Judge Hilton of Denver as counsel, an ex-army man openly killed an I.W.W. leader and was quickly acquitted. Tom Mooney at the AFL convention in San Francisco introduced a motion which was passed unanimously for justice for Joe, and President Wilson asked twice for a reprieve. The school principals of Salt Lake County publicly approved of the Mormon Governor Spry who stood fast against the radicals. The only person of importance here who said that the whole thing was a frame-up was Virginia Snow, the daughter of the President of the Mormon Church, who taught art at the University of Utah and was fired for her courage. Joe was executed at the old Sugar House state prison on Sept. 19, 1915. He had written the song Rebel Girl while in prison and dedicated it to Elizabeth Gurley Flynn. No friends were allowed to witness the execution. He gave the order to “fire” prematurely, but the guards were not ready. He refused any dope or liquor and stood up like a man. His ashes were distributed in every state but Utah and in many foreign countries. Dr. McHugh later wrote to the Governor and asked for $500 reward for turning Joe in, but he didn’t get it. In the archives a friend of mine found a letter written from me in 1915 from Columbus, Ohio asking for clemency for Joe Hill.

Later the song was written I Dreamed Last Night I Saw Joe Hill and it is sung all over the world today. Mary painted a mural of the execution of Joe Hill which in size is 12 by 15 feet and is the prominent feature of our House. As you see Christ is in it as another One who was framed. The I.W.W. wouldn’t print this picture because it had Christ in it and the Catholic papers won’t print it because Joe Hill is in it. Mary also painted a mural of the Holy Family, a picture of a Russian Pilgrim, something resembling a Russian ikon, St. Joan and the Wicked Bishop, etc. We believe we are being true to the memory of Joe Hill by feeding the tramps and transients for whom he cared, and in having no Bible-banging. We do have radical meetings each Friday night.

At one window we have this quotation from Debs: “While there is a lower class I am in it; while there is a criminal class I am of it; while there is a soul in prison I am not free.” And in the other window this wisdom from John Dewey: “A good man is one, who, no matter how bad he has been is getting better; a bad man is one, who, no matter how good he has been is getting worse.”

How We Got Started

A friend gave us an electric hotplate and we cooked on that. Finally some Ute Indians who were up on trial for chasing an Indian Bureau man off the reservation, stopped in their truck and brought two stoves from a priest across the track. It took us several weeks to get the down payment and the authorization for gas, but finally we could cook on a gas stove. My friend Francis Gorgen stopped in for a visit of a day or two. It seems that again by reverse action we were to be helped, for a priest sent a young Catholic alcoholic to us and he slept here nights. He ate where he worked it seemed, and told us that he had bought us a hot water heater, which was soon delivered. Upon seeing the heater Francis said he would stay over a few days and connect it up. While looking for the connections he bought us a gas refrigerator second hand and connected it and the stoves up also. By this time the folks who had brought the heater came and got it back, for our friend had not paid a cent on it, and was already in jail for some other larceny. I looked around and went to buy a heater from a company second hand. The man, who was a Baptist, said if we were doing good work he wouldn’t take any money for it, so Francis soon had it in working order. I got two laundry tubs second hand but some welding needed to be done before they could be connected. A man came with a portable welder after hours and when he had finished he said, “Hell, I wouldn’t charge you anything, for I used to hop freights myself.” Francis finally stayed three weeks and the kitchen was in running order. Later I bought a shower bath for $35 and Francis installed it. Meanwhile our friend was out of jail and was collecting money and cashing checks for more liquor, all in the name of our House. I got the Mormon daily to print a notice that no one was collecting money for us. I went to one paint company and got 2½ gallons of light grey paint; then I told the next company about it and they gave me the same, and another company upped it to four gallons, and our walls were clean. I went to a paper company and had to ask them for new toilet paper, so they gave me a carton of it. Then to three other companies who each give a carton a year. A cracker company brings us crackers, and a few coffee companies have given us coffee. I had written to General Foods telling them that here was the opportunity to have Postum given free instead of coffee, but they had no imagination and answered no. The Hershey man brings us plenty of cocoa. Mary and I carried 120 lbs. of wheat on our backs for nearly a mile, and it is ground on the old coffee grinder I had in Milwaukee when my girls used to grind their own cereal for breakfast. Nearly all the bread companies said if they gave to one they would have to give to all. I told them to break down once and see how it felt. Finally one baker allowed me to get two baskets of bread three times a week, and another hearing about it allowed us two baskets once a week. The Spudnut folks gave us doughnuts twice a week and likewise a pie company. But milk and egg folks wouldn’t budge.

Mary and I went around to the merchants saying, “We are pacifists, anarchists, subversives, and Catholics too radical for our Bishop, but we need sugar, etc.” We got it. Readers of the CW over the country who know me send bits of money at times, so I make it alright. $100 a month is enough. I know that if I do the best the best will be done by me. Few Catholics in town help us but in time they will get over their fear. Mary had been in California working among the migrants in the fields around Tracy and Stockton, and painting murals for the Mexicans and the Quakers. Now in San Francisco she wrote in the January 1963 CW: “I was down in the kitchen of St. Anthony’s Dining Room when the Archbishop was dishing out meals to the men, and I wrote to Ammon that someday perhaps Bishop Federal will go down to Postoffice Place and do the same thing for him. Stranger things have happened.” And although one of the leading priests advised us that, “It is more meritorious to obey a stupid and mistaken priest than it is to obey your conscience, for that may be self will,” and although he stands for capital punishment and war, it also it not impossible that such men may change. Cardinal Suhard, an old man in Paris, saw that the workers were not going to Church and he started the Worker Priests.

Public Relations

The Mormon radio, KSL, interviewed me here at the House, asking me what our rules were. I said “no liquor and no cops.” Coy Ringo was doing life for murder and had escaped from the state prison, stabbing a guard. I was asked if I would hide an escaped murderer. I replied that “I sure as hell would. In the Middle Ages anyone whom the law was after could find sanctuary in a Church. Now the Mormons and the Catholics see which one can shoot them first.” This was released twice on the radio and I had several elderly Mormons come in and ask if I was the man that would protect criminals. In asking the merchants for food, one of them wanted me to get a clearing from the Chamber of Commerce. I went there and explained our ideas and was asked what my racket was. I told them that Mary and I would not sit out on the cold curb early in the morning waiting for some padrone to pick us up if we had any racket. Nor would we spend 14 hours going to and fro to a job and working picking cherries and then get a rubber check for our trouble if we had a racket. I said that the Salvation Army only allowed transients to stay there one night a month, and if they didn’t have a social security card they would turn them in to the police. That the cops had police dogs after the men in the alleys at night, so where the state left off it was the place for anarchists like us to begin.

The health department came around and said that it was unsanitary to sleep men on the floor. I said where were they going to sleep the men. They said I should have double bunks with mattresses. My reply was that the men would fall out of the bunks and crack their skulls, and besides I could only have room for a very few such bunks while I could sleep 70 on the floor. But it was still unsanitary they said. I told them that there must have been some regulation from folks like them that Christ shouldn’t have been born in a stable.

The police came in and wanted to know the name of some man. I told them that I didn’t ask any questions. They said that by law I ought to take the names of all who came. My reply was that inasmuch as I did not charge anything I did not have to take names. It was not long until the police brought men in late at night, or even in the daytime, for us to sober up in our “cooler” under the stairway. They are friendly now as we take a lot of grief off of them.

Four times the FBI came in looking for someone. I shut my eyes and told them that I couldn’t see, and if anyone whom they wanted was in here I wouldn’t tell them anyway; that besides I didn’t like that stinker J. Edgar Hoover. Later they took our literature and do not bother us. A man from the Fire Department came in and said that this place was a fire hazard. I told them that I slept on the floor by the door at night and was up most of the night so that if there was any fire I would know it, and that we took matches away from any drunks we kept in the cooler. He looked around and said, “Well, I guess 60 men in 60 doorways are more of a fire hazard than 60 men all in one room here.”

Several people from the Federal Building where we had picketed came over and gave us $5, refusing to give their names, but saying they liked the work we were doing. The Mormon afternoon paper generally prints a small item each week telling of the subject of our Friday night meeting. I spoke several times at the university, and at a luncheon at the Presbyterian Westminster College. Hundreds of students, mostly Mormons, have come down from the university to interview me about our House and to report back to class, and as a result students often come to our Friday night meetings.

Elizabeth Gurley Flynn gave us a framed picture by Art Young from the old Masses of a reward wanted for Christ, the vagabond, “wanted for sedition, Criminal Anarchy, Vagrancy, and Conspiring to Overthrow the Established Government. Dresses poorly, said to be a carpenter by trade, ill-nourished, has visionary ideas, associates with common working people, the unemployed, and bums. Alien—believed to be a Jew. Alias ‘Prince of Peace. Son of Man-Light of the World,’ and Professional Agitator, Red Beard, marks on hands and feet the result of injuries inflicted by an angry mob led by respectable citizens and legal authorities.”

Picketing for Garcia and Rivenburgh

These young men had been raised in reform school, and Garcia had at the age of 16 been put in the state prison among old tough prisoners. He was held and forcibly raped by a score of men. Later in trouble among homosexuals one man was killed. Three were charged with the murder. One got life, and Jesse Garcia and Mack Rivenburgh were sentenced to death. In March of 1962 they were again sentenced to die on the 13th. I wrote a leaflet entitled Thou Shalt Not Kill and picketed the Governor and Board of Pardons daily for 12 days. The night before the execution they got a reprieve. Mr. McNamara, a Catholic Sociologist from New York City, lectured at the University against capital punishment for a week in January, mentioning these cases and Garcia’s married sister and myself, and Mrs. Ethel Hale distributed these leaflets after the evening lectures at the University. One young woman, after taking a leaflet, came back up the steps and asked if I were Mr. Hennacy. I admitted it. She said she was the warden’s secretary, and that they read the literature I had sent them.

It is reported that an Eastern Catholic Governor appointed 25 people on a commission to report back to him on the subject of capital punishment and that 20 of these were of other religions than Catholic, and five were Catholic priests. When the problem was decided by this committee, 20 were against capital punishment and of course the five who were for it were the five priests. I wrote to every minister in the City telling them that unless they took a stand against these executions that their hands would be bloody. The Catholic Chaplain at the prison spoke to me on the phone and was sorry about the pending executions but would not say anything about it openly, and of course the Catholic Bishop ran true to his conservative form in only being interested in the quiet of the bank and of the grave: nothing to disturb the collecting of money. The only one of the clergy who replied was the Unitarian minister who wrote openly in the newspaper, as I did also, against capital punishment, and who spoke against the executions in the pulpit. He said that the time had not yet come to picket, but at the time of the executions he would stand with me at the prison gate at dawn in silent protest.

A young, self-centered egoist who was writing a book about Joe Hill came and lived here from the middle of November 1961 for ten months, picketed with me for about ten days, and an employee of the Utah Historical Society picketed also until the heat got too much concerning his job. I do not blame him, but was glad to have his help. The television and radio reported my opinions fairly, and the Mormon daily took our pictures. It was quite a walk uphill to the Capitol on an empty stomach as I picketed the hour at noon, so finally I rode on the bus, and walked home downhill. Beautiful blonde Molly Fisher, whose folks had been missionaries in South America, had heard of our House and picketed with me for two weeks while waiting in the City for a friend. As always in my picketing after a time I got my second wind and for as much as 11 days I did not lose a pound. I continued with my regular work getting the food and sleeping on the floor by the door nights. Mrs. Mildred McAlister, a Quaker woman, head of the local chapter against capital punishment, and Professor Paul Vernier of the University, who had been visiting Garcia for years, spoke at hearings before the Pardon Board. I could not get out to the prison those nights because I was needed here to keep peace among the drunks who happened to be especially troublesome just then. Finally, the night before the execution, on September 13th, Garcia got life, but Rivenburgh, discouraged at this 6th time he was facing the firing squad, took poison in his cell. These young men were both Catholics, but no priest was present at Rivenburgh’s funeral in the cemetery where the young Unitarian minister officiated. I was present and was ashamed of this callousness which placed Catholic dogma and cowardice ahead of humanity.

Several times when coming back from picketing, Molly and I gave our leaflets to the young LDS missionaries assembled for an outing as we passed by. Before the scheduled execution in March, Mrs. Hale and about 20 others held a protest meeting on the Capitol steps on a snowy night. The radio gave us publicity, but some Jack Mormon rowdies tried to break the meeting up, without success. The letters in the papers during these days were mostly by Mormons who, because of their dogma of blood atonement, believed in capital punishment. I found this also in my picketing. The Saturday before the scheduled execution in September, Mrs. Hale and an elderly Italian from Magna, Utah, participated in a poster walk with me on Main Street at noon. Others promised to walk with us but in this conservative environment it is difficult to get people to come out and be different. Poulson’s case was carried up in the courts, and he lost his appeal. He never should have been let out of a mental institution, but he was paroled to his mother. He might as well have been paroled to a chair for he had a continual record of sex offenses. He went to the police in Provo and said that he was going to get in trouble again and they had better lock him up, but the police said he hadn’t done anything yet. The next day he killed a babysitter. As in the case of Garcia and Rivenburgh this young man was a product of reform schools and state institutions. Whatever guilt there is lies with the state as much as with the individual. The Supreme Court denied his appeal, so I may be picketing and fasting for him.

Who Comes to Us?

About a third are Jack Mormons, a third Irish Catholics, and a third Oakies or Arkies from the South, with a sprinkling of Negroes, Mexicans, and Indians. About 25 town bums come and go. Many of them get kick-backs from their landlords from rent that the relief pays for them; and also they sell their meal tickets for half price back to the restaurant and have money for booze. In their prosperity, they pay double price to bootleggers on Sunday and holidays when the state liquor stores are closed. Only beer is sold in taverns, and no taverns are on the main street in down town Salt Lake City. You have to have a dollar permit to buy from the state liquor store. Several men know about my ideas on drinking and have given me their liquor permit cards to tear up. Drinking is not the cause of crime or of discord; it is an effect of a discordant and frustrated life. Overprotection by the mother in the home, the fears taught by religion, too much of the rod, and a general sense of the futility of living are causes which drive people to drink or dope to get away from their troubles. When a person desires to sober up, the AA is a great help, but the people I see here do not want to sober up: what they want is one more jug. Preaching to them does not do any good. As I have said before the only way to cure drunkards who do not want to be cured is to put them on some island or far away mountain where a saloon is too far away for them to get at. Then have work for them to do and no one making a profit from their labor. Let them have chicken for dinner every day if they want it; strawberries and cream, or whatever they can raise. Let the place be supervised by one who does not drink himself, and who will pour out any moonshine made from sugar, raisins, etc. locally. In most institutions the bosses get cream, butter, steaks, while the men get skim milk, oleo, and hot dogs. Let all eat the same food. There is Antelope Island in Great Salt Lake. Men cannot be rehabilitated when there is a tavern on every corner.

“Eli Begay, sober,” said a young Navajo at midnight. I let him in. Another time he came with an Indian friend, saying, “Eli Begay, drunk. Let my friend in for he is sober. I go away.” Indians do not have much sense of time and while I will turn away a town bum after ten o’clock, I have more patience with Indians. If I am not sure if the man is a transient or a town bum I will give him the benefit of the doubt. By the time I am awakened, up a dozen times a night, every night, I seek to minimize this grief. Many town bums have learned to come by nine p.m. and they can be in the cooler and sober up. I repeat that there is a difference between kindness and weakness. If I find a bottle on them at night I pour it out and put them out. I announce this policy each night before bedtime.

Cooks who come here and help me say that all cooks are drunks, and in fact I have not found a sober one. On our first Thanksgiving Day in my innocence I thought that the cook was preparing the meal: a turkey given us by a woman who worked at the Post Office, with trimmings. But he was in the back room, passed out. Alba Ryan, an old friend who had been a nurse with the Loyalists in Spain, had stopped for a day or two and took over and we had enough for all. Alba is a fine woman but sentimentally she said, “No one is boss around here; we are all one big family.” I spoke up and said, “I am boss, though not a very eflicient one or I wouldn’t let the cook get by with his boozing. There has to be someone here to see that this place doesn’t deteriorate into a dirty box car.” This cook had told Mary that he wanted to be a Catholic and went to Mass once with her, and then tried to burn her for money to get drunk on. Other cooks sold whatever they could get for liquor. One fat fraud collected about $25 for my birthday, baked a cake, gave me a new typewriter ribbon, and next day went on a drunk with the remainder. I have had scores of men help out with washing the dishes, peeling potatoes, scrubbing the floor, etc. They get a job for a day and get drunk and move on. If they come back sober and they are needed I take them on again. In the beginning I used to buy them packaged cigarettes, but I quit that for I found that they always had enough money for booze, so they could buy their own cigarettes too. For the last eight months I have an aged cook whose friends buy him liquor. He is responsible, keeping the ice box and his room where sugar, canned goods, etc. are stored, locked. Often men get a day’s work and buy some meat, eggs, cofiee, and treat the men who work here and eat with them. Several sentimental people have thought that everyone on the line should get this extra food. There is not enough to go around. These men who do the work get a cot to sleep on. If they can get a little work on the side that is fine.

Often a Jack Mormon will give me a dollar as sort of a tithe, for he would not dare go back to his Church for they would want him to quit smoking and drinking. Men who get a steady job can sleep here and we give them sandwiches until they can get a payday. Scores have said that when they get paid they will help us, and they mean it, but between their payday and us there is the tavern and they are soon broke again. Many men have been around here for months, helping us at times, and have told tall tales about their former prosperity, and of leads they have for wonderful jobs now, but it is nearly all romancing. Men have worked for days for padrones who cheat them, mainly at cleaning bricks, at $7 a thousand. They may give them a dollar now and then for lunch and then they go bankrupt or disappear. Or they leave the employment office nearby with the promise of a job which terminates five miles from town with 50 cents an hour, or the promise of a payday tomorrow. These cheating employers think that the “bums” will work for very little because they are poor, or they will not bother to stay in town and will leave, and therefore will not have to be paid.

At Night

The sign on the door says that 9 p.m. is bedtime. This is meant to keep the town drunks away after that hour, but any transient is welcome any time. As Indians do not have much sense of time I let them in unless they are too drunk to stand up. We have a “cooler,” a place under a stairway where we keep garbage and can accommodate five white drunks or six Indians, for the latter curl up like kittens and take little space. The cops often bring men in to sober up whom they are tired of pinching. Often two men will bring a comrade in who has passed out and have him sleep it off here. Two men kept me up all night with the shakes, but I guess it was worse on them than it was on the rest of us. Around midnight I wouldn’t allow a drunken Navajo inside and in a minute he had thrown a vodka bottle through the window, and I was combing glass out of my hair for a week. All Indians stayed away for two weeks, thinking I might turn some of them in for the damage. At times I get up half asleep when there is a knock on the door and I am not sure if the man there is a stranger or a town drunk. I give them the benefit of the doubt. Sixty men sleeping on the floor without anyone snoring! It has happened a couple of times, but generally I have to get up and turn a man over several times on this account. And sometimes a drunk will escape our eyes and commence to babble in his sleep, and then he will have to go to the cooler. At times one of these drunks will urinate wherever he happens to stand, and one morning I got up to turn on the light and stepped in a mess that “Five by five,” an enormous Mexican, had deposited on the floor. Of course he said that he was innocent but the evidence was all over him. While on the subject, one afternoon I was resting in the cook’s room when the phone rang and I got up to answer it. I noticed a stream of water flowing from a corner by the bedroom door. It couldn’t have come from the bathroom. Two drunks had slipped in and were sleeping on two nearby beds. I woke them up and asked which one had urinated in that especial corner. Each said that he was innocent, and one of them noticed the St. Francis and the Wolf medal that I was wearing and asked what that was. I told him not to change the subject, that the subject was piss, and not holy medals. Coming back from Mass one morning I found that the yardmaster at the freight yard had brought five men up in his car for breakfast, saying that it was better to have them here than to pinch them.

Social Work?

Both Catholic and other religions have wondered if I have been able to rehabilitate the derelicts who come here. These men have had enough preaching. They know better than anyone else what is the matter. They only feel sorry when they get out of jail or when they have a headache. Several men have given me their liquor permits to tear up, but this was only temporary, for in a few weeks they were drunk again. They have a quiet place to read, or if they are sleepy they can go in the cooler and sleep. I would not have a radio or television with all the noise. Several men have come here broke and have sobered up, got a job, and settled down to a good job and a married life. They have come back and told me about it. There may be others. I set them the example of being sober and willing to do any of the tedious or disagreeable work around here. They know I go to Mass daily and that I say prayers for all of them. Prying into their lives does not do any good. When they want any help from me or the AA they will ask for it. I have faith enough in what I am doing to take the long view and do not have to build up my morale by having them sign on the dotted line that they have been “saved.” That is up to God.

The Daily Routine

I get up at 5 a.m., turn the lights on, roll up my blankets, put jelly between two slices of bread, while the cook makes cocoa, and two others get the chalrs and tables ready. Often someone offers to sweep the sidewalk but if not, I do it. Then I read the morning paper or write letters until time to go to 6:30 Mass. Back at 7:30 and have breakfast if I am not fasting. The first mail comes at 8:00, and by 8:45 I am on my way with the rubber-tired cart from the supermarket for fruit and vegetables which they have saved for us, at two stores about a mile away. Often one of the men goes with me and we are back by 10:00 with potatoes, carrots, apples, onions, lettuce, and even avacados and strawberries and melons at times. One place gives us dented cans or cans with the labels off. On Mondays and Thursdays, I go to another store, coming through the Temple grounds where the guards greet me kindly. Monday morning I go for candy to a wholesale house; and for salt, sugar, spices to other places when needed. At 3:30 three times a week I walk 18 blocks (long Mormon blocks like between the Avenues in New York City) for bread, and twice a week I walk 35 blocks for spudnuts and pies. I ride home on the bus. Folks ask me why I don’t get a car or have some of my help get these things. They do not understand that the tax man would get the car, and that most of my help would peddle the bread or pies and doughnuts for booze before they got home. If I have time in the afternoon, I try and sleep or rest for a few hours but often drunks are making too much noise. During the day and before 9:00 p.m. visitors or students often come in to ask questions. On Friday night I always speak on some radical subject, with a notice being generally printed in the Mormon Deseret News. Students come to the meetings often. Afterwards we serve cocoa and cookies. This is a 24-hour-a-day job. Once I went away to Colorado speaking and the drunks had nearly taken over by the time I got back. Folks have suggested that I get a bigger place, but this is enough.

A Parable

One Sunday while listening to the Buddhist sermon in Japanese, I had the following thought and wrote it out afterwards as a Parable:

A man built a house on the upper side of a road, “to be a friend to man,” as he had spent many years traveling over the country and desired to rest a bit. The storms came and the winds blew and the fire poured down from above, and he saw the floods and debris going by where the road had been. He held out a lifeline secured at one end to a huge rock at the side of his house, and upon part of which the house was built. The name of the house and of the rock was called “Independence.”

Most of the people went by on bits of raft or old tress, saying that they were going to the “promised land,” for if they grabbed the lifeline they would get wet, and would have to struggle and might get drowned, while this way they could go half-merrily along. The man shouted that there were rapids below where they would surely get wrecked, but most of them laughed in a crazy manner, meanwhile drinking from a bottle labeled “social security,” and they smoked from a pipe labeled “peace.” One or two were not drinking from the bottle or smoking from the pipe and they looked up and grabbed the line and manfully struggled to this oasis.

Panhandling

Currently there is a campaign on by the police against panhandlers. They have ceased bothering me for they know I feed them here. My friend Ren Mabey had a letter in the morning paper saying that Buddha and St. Francis were beggars; that if the fact that they spend their donations for liquor was the excuse for not giving them anything, then the police should go after the liquor traffic, but this is a source of profit to the state and at times a source of graft for the cops. I don’t believe in putting men in jail for panhandling. My solution is not to give them anything except to take them to a restaurant for the coffee or food they ask for, and nine cases out of ten they don’t go, for what they want is a jug. Men getting over a drunk have really not eaten for five days and then I will give them half a dozen bowls of soup if they want it. Then there is an elderly packrat who would carry a ton of junk from garbage cans into our place and hide it here and there if we would allow it. Stuff that is already spoiled, and old clothes with holes in them. Fellows tell me that he has shown them his bank book and that he gets a pension. He does not eat here but cooks food in the tourist park.

If I paid a man $200 a week to run this place, it is not likely that he would stay the second week, for he would not put up with the grief that is a part of a flop-house on skid-row. (My old wob friend Guy Askew says the proper term is skid-road.) Some Gypsies live two doors away and their youngsters called a colored man who ate here “nigger,” so he pushed a Gypsy man through our window in a fight, only it wasn’t the right Gypsy. The landlord has insurance so it was fixed. One drunk slammed the door in anger because I wouldn’t allow him to lie around drunk in the front room, but told him to go to the cooler and sober up. It was on Valentines Day I remember. Then we didn’t have a pay phone, and the minute it happened Mary phoned from California asking how things were. I told her the nice sign she had painted on the door was lost midst the thousand pieces of glass on the floor. Another big bellowing bull of a drunk put his foot in the door and dared any or all of us to make him get away. He said that I was making a fortune out of feeding bums lousy soup, that he could beat the hell out of me, etc. After half an hour he cooled off and went away and at 10 o’clock that night asked if he could sleep on the floor. There is no use in arguing with a drunk: you only hear wine talking, not the man. I bought eight bath towels and it wasn’t long until the only one left is the one I have for myself. I bought paper towels for the men to use but instead of putting them in a box for used towels they clogged up the toilet. I couldn’t talk the towel company into giving us a roller towel service free so I pay $3.09 a week: one of the few flop houses with such service I expect. Even then the men cut part of the towel off of the roller. They finally got the idea that the company would not bring me any more towels if they continued.

Men get off the freights four miles away and it is often late by the time they get here. Salt Lake City is surrounded by desert for 500 miles every way you go, so men who ride the freights are tired and hungry and need a place to rest. They are welcome here any hour of the day or night. Several times young couples came along on scooters, broke, and I allowed them to stay in the cooler a night or two, and in flush moments I have paid for a woman to stay in the cheap hotel upstairs. The Jewish Social Service, Lutherans, Unitarians, and Catholics send men here at all hours. At midnight, a woman three miles away phoned saying that a drunk man was sleeping in her house. He had done painting for her that day and had not sobered up yet. She was a widow and her priest said to call the cops to get him out, but she didn’t like to do that, so the priest said to call me. She sent him here in a taxi. He was hardly able to walk but with my help made it to the cooler. An enormous man sat on the floor and dared us to put him out. It would have taken half a dozen men and most of the windows would have been broken, so we had to do as Peter Maurin says: to put up with each other the way God puts up with us. I wouldn’t mind an adult pacifist to help me at times, or free.

Pious frauds come around and want to make our place into some racket of collecting clothing and selling it; or collecting money house to house. One such fellow had been to many monasteries he said. He wore scapulars all over his coat and offered to go right out and collect money for our place. I told him to get out and stay out. Another bewhiskered “Messiah” was flashing money in the tavern and was robbed and raised a fuss about it. He made the excuse that Christ associated with winebibbers, but I told him that Christ didn’t flash any money but went “without script or purse.” Then a whisky-faced lout came in from Chicago wanting to know if “Big Brother” had been here yet to start a mission and make “big money selling jewelry.” Maybe I could get in on it if he recommended me. I chased him too.

Catholics have told me that I am “earning merit” if I do this for Christ’s sake, but that otherwise it is all wasted time. Some radicals tell me that I ought to be “making the revolution” instead of patching up the system and coddling bums. The religious want me to bookkeep my good deeds like a Boy Scout. I tell them that of course I see somewhat of Christ in every man but I joined the Catholic Church for the Sacraments and for my appreciation of Christ and many fine saints, but I didn’t have time to bookkeep “indulgences” and that my prayers at Mass were direct to Christ and not to any mediaries. I tell the radicals that the Joe Hill House is a base where I can with honor picket military bases nearby, picket against the execution of prisoners, hold forth to students who are curious about radicalism, and have a meeting very Friday night where no Board of Directors can tell me “not to be so radical or you’ll slow up money coming in.” I am a free man in a slave-minded society.

Mary Lathrop

I have mentioned Mary and her help with my picketing in New York City and our coming to Salt Lake City. There was some criticism from the Catholic clergy about our radical message. I did not seem able to write anything about it that suited Mary or myself so we agreed not to mention the subject in my book. However this fall Dorothy Day’s book, Loaves and Fishes, was published by Harper and Row. And in it is a chapter entitled “Picture of a Prophet.” The last six pages discuss Mary and me. It is done with such a good spirit and is so fair, and is so much better than either Mary or I could do that I am repeating it here, with special permission from the publishers.

He liked women, too—especially young and pretty women—and greeted them all with a swift embrace when he met them. “I never remember the time I was not in love with some woman,” he declared happily on the evening of his sixty-eighth birthday. Another time he said seriously, “There is only one woman I ever really loved and this is my wife.” I suppose it was some aspect of his wife that he saw in all women…

This marriage had been a common-law one, and I think he always felt free to marry again, although he spoke of his anarchism as an obstacle. He did not believe in getting permission to marry from the state by applying for a license. Anyway, until last year the matter never came up. Up to that that time Ammon always had three or four good women friends who were truly devoted to him, even though he often spoke of women scornfully, insisting that they held men back in their radical careers.

Then, a year and a half ago, Mary Lathrop erupted into his—and our—life. She is a lively young woman who looks eighteen rather than twenty-eight, slim, beautifully built, with the strong legs of a dancer. She had worked for almost a year in a burlesque show. “…I guess I did it to shock my New England family, to get even with them, and also to get enough money to pay my psychiatrist…”

Soon after Mary’s arrival, Ammon got out of Sandstone prison… (after arrests on the air raid demonstration). Ammon announced that he was going to picket all night along Greenwich Avenue, which fronts the jail. Mary said she would picket with him—and she did. She was always ready for an adventure.

She was getting rid of some of her driving energy, too. Ammon recognized that energy in her at once, and he loved it. Soon he began to talk of her as a wild young colt who needed to be hitched to a plow. He’d tame her, he seemed to imply. Certainly he began to work her hard. He was up every morning for seven o’clock Mass at old St. Patrick’s Chiirch on Mott Street. If Mary did not show up, he took to going to her apartment door (she shared two rooms with Judith and me) and waiting until she came out. They went for the mail together, and he kept her at the typewriter until every letter was answered. Around eleven each day they sold the paper on the streets and then went on to picket he Civil Defense headquarters or the Atomic Energy Commission. They would be back in the office for supper, perhaps, and out to more meetings in the evening. It was the kind of life that appealed to Mary.

“I like to be with Ammon,” she said, “because I love to show off and so does he. I was brought up to show off,” she added a little bitterly. She came from a broken home and spoke sadly of having two mothers and two fathers. She felt injured and aggrieved, but one could tell how much she loved her mother and father and how much she missed them. She turned to Ammon as to another father; she liked to cling to him. She was demonstrative, as was he; and he satisfied her need to show tenderness.

Sometimes she rebelled against his routine and morning after morning would take off to the flower market, where she begged armloads of flowers, with which she decorated statues, tables, and desks. We were in the loft on Spring Street when she first came to us. If she felt like running from end to end of the place, letting out Indian war whoops, she did it. (The loft was 180 feet long, so she had scope for her talents!) At other times she threw herself into skits or parodies with such verve and humor that we laughed until the tears came. Her imitation of Captain Ahab in Moby Dick and of a Southern senator were equally funny. But she could be as gentle and appealing as she was outrageous and boisterous. She has a lovely voice and often sings folk songs. Once, when we were driving somewhere together, I started reciting the ‘Veni Creator Spiritus.’ She began to weep. She wanted to join a convent immediately.

She used to paint pictures on the walls, on pieces of board she picked up on the street, on the head and footboard of an old bed she had rescued from a gutter. Her side of the room in our apartment was one grand clutter of murals, pictures, paints, paper, paint brushes, books, and clothes. Mary loved clothes. As fast as they came in to be donated to the poor, she dipped into them for a change of her own costume.

Ammon, like most men, preferred her in frilly things, her hair waved, face made up, and so on. He liked frivolity in women—but Mary rebelled at that, too, although half the time she fell in with his wishes. When she dressed as she pleased, she came either in rags or in some dramatic costume that set off her rather austere beauty. On the latter occasions she would put on a cultivated New England accent and the manner of the exclusive girls’ school. I am sure that this charmed the Midwestern and Will Rogers type of person Ammon was. He liked to show her off to his friends. “She’s going out with me to Salt Lake City,” he boasted. The boast became “And she wants to marry me.” Not that he wanted to marry her; Mary wanted to marry him, he insisted. When Mary heard him say this, she would announce that what she really wanted was to go into a convent.

“But what convent will harbor that wild creature?” everyone around the office asked. “She frightens young men; convents are too conventional,” an old friend of the family observed. So all agreed “she might as well marry Ammon.” It was as casual as that…

“I’ll stay two more years, then I’ll go to Utah. There are fewer Catholics there than in any other state. However, I like the Mormons because they accept no aid from the government but have their own mutual aid.”

He liked, too, the polygamous Mormons who defied the government and the concessions made by their own Church. Perhaps he was thinking of all the women friends he himself had.

Mary came into his life six months before his projected departure. The first plan was that she would go west and work with him. When it was pointed out to Ammon that this was somewhat unconventional, he decided he could forget his anarchist principles to the extent of getting the marriage license from the city. He knew being married by a priest was necessary, of course.

Difficulties began to arise with the chancery office. The Church moves slowly in such affairs. Neither Ammon or Mary was willing to give up their companionship, although they were perfectly willing to remain celebate. So Mary followed Ammon to Salt Lake City. She worked with him, opening up a house of hospitality on Post Office Place, which they call the Joe Hill House and St. Joseph’s Refuge. He named the house for St. Joseph, too, as a concession to Mary’s piety. Ammon lived in the house, while Mary had a furnished room nearby and did housework to pay for it. Ammon took jobs unloading freight to keep things going. Like the Mormons, they gave up tea, coffee, and cigarettes.

Their “Gandhi—and-Mira” situation was not generally understood. In turn, they resented the bourgeois questioning of their relationship and stubbornly continued with it in spite of criticism from both Catholic and Mormon clergy.

All through the summer they worked in the orchards. From their letters it appears Ammon did most of the picking, while Mary sat by the irrigation ditches and taught the children of the Mexican workers to paint and make toys for themselves.

And then winter came, and with the cold, indoor work. Mary’s job as chambermaid in a rooming house was a hard one. She got up early each morning to go to Mass. The parish priest called her attention to the fact that she was out of place with the crowd of men who began to come around the little house of hospitality. He offered to give her carfare to San Francisco any time she wished to go. One day she got from him a bus ticket and an extra twenty-five dollars and—skipping the painful farewells—left early the next morning. She, who was a most devout convert, had fought with Ammon daily over his anticlericalism. So it should not have come as a surprise.

But for Ammon it was a shock and he was deeply hurt. He blamed me (because Mary regarded me as her mother), and he blamed the priest as well.

For a while Ammon used to write bitter letters to his Bishop, calling on him to speak out against capital punishment and injustice in general. I taxed him with being a most militant pacifist, and a most domineering anarchist. Now there are no more letters. His anger, which was never out of control before, has exhausted itself. He goes evenly on about his work.

At various times he has said that he would move on, after a few years, to the West Coast, where his daughters are now living. But when I asked him in a recent letter if these were still his plans, he replied that he expected to end his life in Salt Lake City. He loves its beauty, he loves all that is good about the Mormons, and in time, I am sure, he will come to love the Bishop.

Mary has continued to paint pictures for the Joe Hill House which she calls “ours,” She is working and going to night school, and growing up in San Francisco. I write her often and we talk on the phone when rates are cheaper. I have visited her several times. We love each other, but how it will work out in the future, time and circumstances will tell.

Health without Medicine

Pacifists, anarchists, Catholics, and most of my friends are friendly to me, but when it comes to the subject of medicine they generally disagree more violently than they do to my other radical ideas. It seems they like their aspirins. When a person says that they do not believe in medicine they are generally called Christian Scientists. I have read all of Mrs. Eddy’s books and for ten years I attended their Church and read their lessons daily, and of course took no medicine. Neither did my daughters take any medicine, nor my wife. However my opposition to medicine is not based on the denial of disease, which is the Christian Science basis. To deny a thing does not remove its cause. Only in the case where disease is based on fear, and if Christian Science or any other idea can get rid of this fear, then can it heal the disease.

I do not know of any one who has my ideas entirely on this subject. The person from whom I have received the most understanding is Dr. Herbert M. Shelton, whom I mention previously in this book. He is editor of The Hygienic Review, Box 1277, San Antonio, Texas. He has written many books on the subject. His idea is that disease is remedial, and is only an effort of the body to get rid of a toxic condition caused by wrong living, wrong eating, wrong thoughts. Another man from whom I received enlightenment is a former Christian Science practioner, William Walter, of Aurora, Illinois. He was so successful that the Christian Science leaders wanted to know his method. When he told them, and didn’t parrot the cliches of the Christian Science Church sufficiently or mention Mrs. Eddy’s name often enough, he fell in disgrace from that church and started one of his own called “Eschatology,” with practitioners in many cities. I read their literature which said that every disease is caused by a certain sin, so if you cease that sin you will get well. This group, like the Christian Scientists supported war and had no sense of social responsibility. Whether they performed healings after the death of Mr. Walter I do not know.

Dr. Shelton teaches that because of our wrong way of living and eating our systems become clogged with impurities, and according to our inherited bodies we become susceptible to discomforts which medical folks call diseases. For instance in one person this toxemia results in diarrhea, in another boils, in another vomiting, in another fever, and finally when they have lived stupidly for long enough they get cancer. One of his sayings is that the stupid perish. The way to health, he says, is to cease eating any food, that is to go on a complete fast, drinking only preferably distilled water, to rest in bed, get plenty of fresh air and sunshine, and get rid of any mental worries, and the body will heal itself. When you are well you will become ill again if you continue your evil habits, so you should become a vegetarian, cease any smoking, drinking of alcohol, tea, coffee, cocoa, soft drinks. And of course never take any medicine of any kind. He says that medicine given to a dead body has no effect. That any foreign substance in the body is ejected by nature, such as pus collecting around a splinter in your finger and thus it is driven out. So medicine taken into the body is vomited or ejected somehow. This is the body acting on the foreign substance, not the medicine acting on the body. He says that the improvement in health is due to better sanitary conditions and not to vaccinations or inoculations. The wonder drugs kill more people than they are supposed to cure. He has had many thousands of people come to his rest home who are nearly dead, having tried every other way, and less than a score have died there. Many regaining their health and living for many years. The AMA in states like New York and Ohio have caused the imprisonment of doctors who use his methods.

I admit that it is well to have doctors who know the parts of the body so that in the case of an accident when a person is unconscious, bleeding, etc., it can be attended to. Many reputable physicians will not indiscriminately give blood transfusions for they know that derelicts who sell their blood either do not know that they have had malaria or jaundice, or are in such a rush to get money to go on another spree that they lie about it, so that many deaths are caused by the injection of this impure blood into patients who are already ill. The death of many people is caused by the use of the so-called wonder drugs which have side effects upon the body not known until they have been tried upon patients. And people vary in their reaction to these poisons injected into their bodies under the guise of “helpful drugs.” I am not mentioning in detail the sleeping pills which cause the birth of deformed babies.

There are four causes of diseases: First, the body which you have inherited which may be prone to certain weaknesses, such as heart trouble, diabetes, rheumatism, tuberculosis, etc. Or the habits of living which people in any certain occupation or in any certain geographical environment are accustomed to, such as Navajos smothering themselves in their stuffy hogans, coal miners whose work makes them liable to rheumatism, etc. So every one has a web of circumstance which may help or hinder them throughout life.

Second, the presence of fear. No matter if a person believes in God there are many who are forever fearful of everything that might happen. They are afraid of snakes, darkness, heights, cats, dogs, etc. These fears may come from frightening childhood experiences which they have never overcome. They may be afraid of certain diseases, and as the Bible says that which they fear has come upon them.

Third, there is the matter of stupidity. Some folks are told what to do but they are too stupid to understand or too inept to do anything for themselves. They can’t sleep; they don’t seem to digest their food. They are always ailing. If they were a bit alive they would look around them and see the people who are healthy and they would ask questions and perhaps learn something. They suffer from too much mucus in the form of catarrah, yet they must drink milk and eat starchy foods and imbibe more mucus. They have arthritis yet they keep on eating bloody meat, sweets, and starches and get worse. They go from one fake patent medicine to another and never learn.

Fourth, there is this matter of sin. If any certain disease is not caused by the first three mentioned then it is caused by a certain weakness or sin. I will enumerate a few. Asthma is caused by smother love, the overprotection by the mother or other female relatives of children, especially boys, so that in order to breathe they have to get away from under the wings of the mother hen and breathe on their own. You find the grown boy whose mother must spread his bread for him, who hovers over him forever. She does not trust in God no matter how much she may go to Mass. Fears of ragweed, etc. on her part will prepare the boy for hayfever. Allergy specialists have told me that boys suffering from asthma and hayfever have been sent away to boarding schools and recovered in a few months, but as soon as their mothers visited them they commenced to breathe hard and choke. They have to get weaned sometime. In the case of anemia or tuberculosis a person may have lost their loved one, their job, or their faith, so there is no use of living. Neither is there any use of dying. They have nothing to live for so they just fade away. A study was made in Switzerland for years by doctors of tuberculiar patients and its was found that with one lung the patient could live if he had some reason for living. In some cases a love affair was patched up, in others an interest was found in life. Vain and greedy folks want to be first in everything. They rush around and overtax their heart. When they die someone else will perform the work. Diabetes is a gluttons disease. They eat and eat until they can’t eat any more. The person who is forever fighting and arguing may very well be always bothered with the common cold. In more aggravated cases when food is not digested because of the anger which happens many times at meals colitis ensues. Years ago experiments were made at Harvard University where cats were fed liver and then a dog was presented to them and their stomachs were in a turmoil for hours. Continual disturbance may cause gall stones. But in the case of the stolid temperment where there is not anger in the form of action but where the supposed insult is covered up and the person sulks and hates and will not speak, tumors and cancer often occur. God sends love, but you only grouch and hug this hatred to yourself until it eats you up. There is no cure for real cancer, although often a benign tumor is diagnosed mistakenly as cancer. You have met the stiff-necked person who stubbornly will not listen to a new idea. He is always right, even in his parochial ignorance. Thus rheumatism, arthritis, or constipation is brought on by stubbornness. Opposition to ideas of others is always personalized. I often say that the difference between this kind of a person and myself is that I am firm while he is stubborn. Then there are the scare diseases: polio, the virus, and all sorts of epidemics. “Do you have the virus yet?” Every pain is called a symptom of the current fad in disease. Babies who have no sins fall ill because of the fog of fear surrounding them.

Now suppose you have a bad inheritance, are afraid, stupid, and a sinner of many varieties, what can you do about it? If you have already taken insulin for years, fasting will be of little help for you will be liable to go into a coma, but in the first stages fasting will help you. It may require several fasts of from 30 to 70 days before your body is in a condition of health. But if you go back to your evil habits you will get sick again. Do not try fasting at home where all oppose you. Go to some health home like that of Dr. Shelton’s.

Time magazine of 1-15-63 reports that Dr. Frederick R.C. Johnstone of Vancouver General Hospital tells that of those who were given antibiotics that infections were three times that of those who received none. He states that “antibiotics kill off the weaker germs and leave the field wide open for the more dangerous bacilli to multiply.” And in the San Francisco Examiner of Nov. 20, 1962, Dr. Philip Thorek of the Illinois Medical School says, “Many thousands of people are dying this year because of blood transfusions, often after the surgeon has done his work skillfully and without apparent complications.” “Transfusions could be lethal,” Doctor Thorek said, “because donor blood may be incompatible to the patient who receives it. Such incompatibility, the surgeon said, may occur for many reasons, including wrong composition, too much or too little of a given chemical in the donor’s blood; wrong concentratin, the content that the patient needs; and, wrong rate of administration, too much blood given too fast can put a deadly burden on the heart that must pump it, while too little given too slowly may fail to correct the deficiency. Also, Doctor Thorek said, blood given may be weaker or stronger in total chemical; donor blood may carry the invisible and unfilterable germs of debilitating or mortal diseases, including hepatitis, malaria and syphilis.”

The Associated Press of May 29, 1963 tells of Mrs. Elaine Johnson of Los Angeles who completed a supervised fast in Wadsworth Veterans Hospital where she fasted for 117 days and lost 136 of her 315 pounds. And during the previous winter we all read of the man and woman plane-wrecked in Alaska who went 43 days on snow watier and lived.

When I criticize churches and the state I do not infer that individual churchmen and politicians are knowingly wicked people, but as I have told judges when I am in court, they are in a bad business. Likewise with doctors, who many times are humane and self sacrificing, but who like the others, they have been brought up not to question the way they make a living. I have had mature doctors agree with nearly all of my ideas on medicine, but what can they do about it when people are so foolish and want to take poison to cure them instead of changing their way of life. The whole anarchist philosophy teaches the responsibility of the individual, and not dependance upon clergy, politicians, doctors, lawyers, etc.

I met a woman, now a member of The Order of Aaron, who, when much younger, had been taken to a hospital here in Salt Lake City for an operation. She was in great pain, and as the doctors assembled for the operation she asked them if there was not someone she could first call upon to pray and “lay on hands” for a successful operation. She did not belong to any church, but from reading the Bible in her youth she had this idea. They left the room and called some Mormon Elders in who prayed, and in a few minutes she was healed and did not need the operation. This was indeed faith. Then she commenced to read the Book of Mormon and joined their church. For over ten years she faithfully tried to be a good Mormon but the more she read in their books the more she saw that they did not practice the United Order and were lax in their fidelity to The Word of Wisdom. Finally she joined this new group which I describe in the chapter on Communities. Some hysterical people may be temporarily healed by such evangelists as Orel Roberts, but as he does not preach right living, but only faith, it is likely that those whom he has “cured” will again become ill, for the cause of their illness was not effected. Likewise at Lourdes a few healings occur each year. Mormon Elders are upon call to heal the sick and as I live here I will undoubtedly learn more of this part of their religion. Their Word of Wisdom stresses a clean life. Doubtless some Christian Scientists heal those whose illness is caused basically by fear, but as their church increaingly has been commercialized, along with all others, not much can be expected from them in the matter of health.

Moral Rearmament

I have referred previously in this book as to the Moral Rearmament group being the worst fraud in modern times. I refer to it again upon reading a full page ad in the New York Times in which they list sixteen ideas which they are for, and opposite them ideas which they are against. For instance they are for Intelligent National Security and against sexual deviates in high places who protect potential spies. They are for peace but against Pacifism. They claim to be absolutely pure and make this as an excuse to uphold rent, interest, profit, and armaments of the capitalist system, and boast of the labor leaders and Communists whom they have turned from their wrong way of life to the MRA which bolsters up capitalism. What makes them such a fraud is that they claim to be better than those outside of their belief, meanwhile their personal salvation that they boast so much about does not prevent them from supporting every evil of capitalism except race prejudice; yet we never heard of any of them leaving their lives of luxury and joining picket lines or freedom-riders.

First Customer

When Mary and I were picking cherries and before we had started this house we worked with a man who lived upstairs in the Japanese Hotel who was seldom sober. He thought we ought to be a financial success in our new “restaurant” and kept telling us that he would be our first customer, for unless we had a first customer we would never have any more and would not succeed. So my orders to all of the help is that any time the “first customer” comes in, drunk or sober, he is to be served what he wants. After his cup of coffee or soup he ceremoniously gives us a dime “so we won’t go broke,” and we take it in that spirit.

Carl, the cook who has been here the longest, has drank liquor all of his life and has no intentions of stopping now at the age of 79. He never gets loud. I tell him not to bring liquor in the house, so he has friends who buy him a drink at the tavern nearby. One night he had half of a glass of liquor under his bed and went to rejuvenate himself when he found a dead mouse in it. This news was too good to keep, and we all had a good laugh over his mousetrap. I will not buy any mousetraps, telling them that if they want to take their cigarette and liquor money and buy a trap they can do so.

One goodnatured man who stayed here all one winter and helped get food from the market, and who claimed to be an old time I.W.W., left and took with him anything that he could steal in order that he would not run short of liquor on the way. My gloves did not fit him but he stole them. A cook also stole my gloves, and others have stolen raincoats, shoes, cigarette lighters, and anything that they can pick up. One drunk whom I had put out a score of times for bringing in liquor was sobering up in the cooler, and hidden in his shirt was an alarm clock that we found missing, and hid under his pillow was a bottle partly full of liquor. I poured it out and made him leave, for he knew better. All of these men are bigger than I am but they seldom offer any opposition, except to blandly lie and say they are not drunk, when they can hardly stand up. One fellow was drinking from his bottle in the night and insisted that it was not his bottle. I told him shame for stealing someone else’s liquor, and poured it out and put him out. I do not snoop around searching for bottles, but when I step on them I empty them. The men take it good naturedly. I know it is a losing battle and I do not expect to win.

Christmas Message 1962

“Truth is forever on the scaffold; error forever on the throne” (but you don’t have to be a part of it). People are naturally good, if it doesn’t cost them anything, but in this mercenary larcenized age let nearly all professedly religious people think that they may not get a promotion, or someone else may get their jobs, then the primeval beast appears to defend the status quo.

They say that they are saved and that they believe in heaven, but they really don’t believe in the hereafter, for their religion teaches them that they cannot take it with them, so they hold on tight to their fortunes and consider that they are poor if they have to dig into their principal, because they do not receive enough dividends or interest.

Whether through inheritance of the example of beneficent friends or relatives many folks of any religion or of no religion are a fine example of ethical living. They may believe that St. Peter, Mohammed, Mrs. Eddy, or Joseph Smith received a special revelation superceding all others, and that their Church is the True One, and they may follow most of the rules laid down by their leaders, but, as Tolstoy says, this does not prevent them from being kind, considerate, self-sacrificing, and truly noble people. An outsider meeting them would tend to be attracted to their religion because of the good example they present. But the real truth is that if they changed religions or belonged to no religion they would still be the same fine people. Thus the anonymous woman who gave us a turkey one year and two hams last year belongs to no church and her husband is a former Catholic who belongs to the Japanese Buddhist Church. The Mormon Bishop who sent us 240 pints of syrup, and the Greek Orthodox who gives us a basket of candy once a week, as well as other Mormons who help us here at our mission are good examples of their religions, while the Catholics who boycott us are a bad example.

There are others, and I expect they are the great majority, who have had a bad physical and emotional inheritance and environment and who, whether they know it or not, are motivated by the fears which their religious or their material environment presents to them. So they go through the forms and ceremonies, or go to psychiatrists, and are forever in a state of frustrated doubt, which even to admit, frightens them into going through forms and ceremonies to ward off evil. No matter what they may say, their attitude is placating the devil rather than worshipping God. The mercenary leaders of these churches grow fat on the fears of their dupes—and they may themeslves be placating the Evil One (all in the name of God). They are not to be blamed overly much for they have been conditioned that to read or think of anything “controversial” is a sin, and with these blinders their religion is clearly what Marx said, an “opiate.” If they change religions they are no better for their whole pattern is based on fear of losing their souls.

Some can enter Orders, or on the outside blindly stress the virtue of obedience, and not being of an inquiring mind, but being of the “sheep mentality,” they are relatively happy in thinking that they will be saved. “Why give freedom to sheep? They only bleat,” says Max Stirner.

There are a number of others, no matter what their previous environment has been, who faintly see through all this fear and fraud but feel incompetent to deal with it, so they eat, drink, take the newest dope, and like to think that they are happy. They may be fine people who spread good cheer or they may be larceny-minded.

We find men elevated as leaders, or as leader of a religion who accept war, exploitation, capital punishment, and all the modern evils, and they see no contradiction between the wonderful ethics pronounced by the leaders of their religions and their denial of these ethics in their daily lives. Now at Christmas time they have a faint glimmering that comes through and they for the moment really mean what they say when they call for brotherhood, peace, kindliness, yet they are surrounded, and they consciously keep themselves surrounded, by yes men and lickspittles so that nothing is really ever done that will cripple their power or decrease their revenue.

A person is tempted to agree with Charles Erskine Scott Wood who years ago wrote the book, Heaveniy Discourse, in which God, St. Peter, Christ, etc. are discussing what is going on in this crazy world, and God is dodging the prayers that are sent up to Him. If one were to believe that the Jews were God’s chosen people and they would multiply as the sands of the sea, then they could also believe that He thought He would take another chance and send Christ to bring the people around to His ways. But the Orthodox killed him. Then when His Church continually denied Him after Constantine, killed millions in religious wars and massacres, and had their Inquisition in Spain and America, it is conceivable that God would find the Prophet Mohammed. But the Mohammedans did almost as bad as the others. Then it could be that when Joseph Smith prayed and asked God which was the real religion that he was told that none of them lived up to their function, and that he was told to start the real one; that there was progression in spirituality in this world and in other worlds besides this one, and that he was to collect the “saints” who would lead this life in their United Order with no rich or poor and in the agricultural simplicity in which all religions have had their origin. While Catholics had generally forgotten the healing of the sick which was done in the early days before they became dominant, the Mormons practiced it, and they still do.

Mrs. Eddy came along “divinely inspired and without human hypothesis” and founded her Church, and in the same time the Seventh Day Adventists thought the world was coming to an end and at a certain date and set up their religion as a “one and only” featuring Saturday as a Holy Day instead of Sunday. At this time Alexander Campbell felt that there should be One True Church, so he founded the Campbellite Church or Disciples Church which was to be that Church.

Looking over the world today it can easily be seen that no church, despite their protestations, has any intention of following the Sermon on the Mount. In fact, if you talk about it you will get into trouble with politicians who have been elevated to run the churches.

It could be that God also tried to bring His program across by inspiring individuals, rather than to start another church, and so brought forth Gandhi among the Hindus, Tolstoy among the Russians, and Schweitzer among the Protestants, and John Woolman and Rufus Jones among the Quakers, as he earlier tried to remind Catholics through St. Francis, St. Catherine, St. Joan, and the young girl at Lourdes.

What can an honest, sincere, and wide awake person do who belongs to any of these religions or none of them? All religions are a mockery of God no matter if they were once started by inspired Prophets. Truly the Catholic Lord Acton said that “power tends to corrupt, and absolute power corrupts absolutely.”

All that anyone who belongs to any church can do is to know that inspiration is not dead: that “all things work together for good to those who love God.” And as Thoreau said, to take one world at a time, and work within the groups where he is located, and those who are not too far corrupted will appreciate it. It would seem that organized religion is bound to be corrupted. When God plans to resurrect those of any or of no religion and start a new world is anyone’s guess. The billions spent on going to Venus or the Moon, when we can’t run our own world, is based on military domination of the world by the U.S. or Russia. All organized churches go along with this “my country right or wrong” and in this respect are most evil institutions (that is except the Quakers, Brethren, and Mennonites) who support taxes for war and obedience to governments, national and world. It would seem that the True Church is composed of those in all churches or in no church who courageously live up to the highest teachings of their Prophets. No new Church needs to be started or it would become as bad as the others. Stay in the Church of your choice, or remain outside, and be a witness by your life for Truth against the rulers of this world and the rulers of the Church who prefer Caesar to Christ.

Chapter 21

The Mormons

1961–present

Salt Lake City, Utah

“Are you going to be a Mormon now?” asked a Catholic friend when he heard that I was going to live in Salt Lake City.

“If it is the best I will: you wouldn’t want me to follow the second-best, would you?” And a Mormon asked me if I was on a mission. “Sure,” I replied.

It is with a friendly feeling toward Mormons that I came here. It is in the spirit of honest inquiry that I have attended Sacrament meetings nearly every Sunday at the University Ward, and I have read a score of books pro and con about the Mormons. I have also attended the Reorganized Church and the polygamous “Church of the First Born of The Fullness of Times.” I realize that it is presumptuous to write about the Mormons with less than three years in Salt Lake City, but I have done the best I could to understand their religion, studying The Book of Mormon and The Doctrine and Covenants and Pearl of Great Price. I will learn more and more as I continue to study and to meet Mormons.

Joseph Smith

If I believed in the revelations of Joseph Smith I would be a Mormon. My great-great-grand-parents on my mother’s side were Quakers and Baptists who lived not far from the uproar of the Kirtland, Ohio community. Alexander Campbell had belonged to the Achor Baptist church where I was baptized at the age of 11, and he left it and went to Brush Run, Pa. to start his Campbellite church, being inspired by God that one more true church was needed, he said. The Mormons and the Campbellites converted each other back and forth in and around Kirtland. If I had been a young man then it is possible that I might have followed Smith who was a radical who wanted a society without any rich or poor, all living together as brothers. He called in 1844 when he ran for President for the slaves to be bought off from their masters and freed, and for the prisons to be emptied and schools established in their place, although as it will be shown in this chapter later, Brigham Young and others were anti-Negro. Now, in 1963, Mormon missionaries are being sent to Negroid Africa. The cynical here say it is because they do not wish to alienate the Negro vote if and when George Romney, the Mormon Governor of Michigan, chooses to run for the Presidency. The Mormons succeeded in communal life for a longer time where the radical colonists, such as Robert Owen and the followers of Fourier failed.

I am not giving the history of the Golden Plates or of the persecutions of the Mormons. In the appendix I list books as references upon which I have based opinions which I give in this book. Others can read for themselves. Tolstoy told Ambassador White that “the Mormon people taught the American religion” and that “on the whole he preferred a religion which professed to have dug its sacred books out of the earth to one which pretended that they were let down from heaven.”[1] Although these plates were supposed to be sent from heaven to the Hill Cumorah.

When Smith was accused by members of his church of not being a good prophet because he had trusted in people who defaulted, he prayed to God and God told him that “Some revelations are of God; some revelations are of man; and some revelations are of the devil.” At another time some of his followers expected pious dignity from him and he told them that “a prophet is only a prophet when he is acting as such… at 4 in the afternoon I went out with my little Frederick to exercise myself by sliding on the ice.”[2] At another time he had healed many of the sick and told his followers not to bring any more for he I felt like wrestling. He would challenge any person and he usually won. It was likely that the faith folks had in him produced much of the healing. In fact he was astonished at his success. A Campbellite preacher came and wanted a sign, saying that he would believe and bring all of his congregation with him. Joseph explained his ideas but the pious fool insisted upon a miracle, so Joseph said, “What will you have done? Will you be struck dumb, blind? Will you be paralyzed, or will you have one hand withered? Take your choice, choose which you please, and in the name of the Lord Jesus Christ it shall be done.” The preacher replied that this was not the kind of miracle he wanted. Joseph answered, “Then sir, I can perform none. I am not going to bring trouble upon anyone else to convince you.”[3] One is reminded of Christ refusing to show off when the Devil tempted him to turn stones into bread, jump down from the Temple, or to be given charge of the whole material world. And by the way, it is just this charge that all Christian churches had succumbed to serving Caesar instead of God that provided the reason for a new religion.

A visiting English clergyman asked Joseph why he got drunk. His answer was so that his followers would not worship him too much. He said “I am not so much a Christian as many suppose I am. When a man undertakes to ride me for a horse, I feel disposed to kick up and throw him off, and ride him.” And he told the Englishman, “I love that man better who swears a stream as long as my arm, yet deals justice to his neighbors and mercifully deals his substance to the poor, than the long, smooth-faced hypocrite. I do not want you to think that I am very righteous for I am not.”[4] In his journal for March 13, 1843 he said, “I wrestled with William Wall, the most expert in Ramus, and threw him. In the afternoon held a church meeting.” When asked to say a blessing at a meal he said, “Lord we thank Thee for this johnny-cake, and ask Thee to send us something better. Amen.”[5] Those who have seen Burt Lancaster in the movie Elmer Gantry have met a likeable half-rogue, who, no matter what he did, was charming. I expect that Joseph Smith was an imaginative sort of Huck Finn, surrounded by religious excitement. When he said that the people on the Moon were six feet tall, were dressed like Quakers and lived a thousand years,” no one could prove that he was wrong. Werner says that “in his youth Joseph Smith was torn between the fear of not being saved eternally and the desire to have a good time from day to day. Fortunately for his peace of mind he was able to reconcile the two by having himself appointed to have a good time.”[6]

It is conceivable that he prayed to God to tell him what was the true religion and it would not take much honesty to see that all religions had long forgotten the Sermon on the Mount. Joseph must have had some rebellious feelings and he likely would have heard of his great-great-grand-father who was chairman of those who formed the Boston Tea Party.[7] If a person does not believe that Joseph found the Golden Plates, or if he found them, that the message was not the truth, or garbled truth, how can they be explained? I have read of the argument that he copied them from Spauding’s book, and I have read the parallels between Ethan Smith’s book printed in Putney, Vt. in 1823 and The Book of Mormon concerning the American Indians and I do not think the evidence is conclusive that Joseph ever heard of these books, for when he got his revelations there was no holding him back, and his wife and Oliver Cowdry and Martin Harris would nearly be worn out writing down what he told them while burying his face in his hat with the magic stone or stones which it is said produced The Book of Mormon. Oliver Cowdry may have helped in the grammar of The Book of Mormon and may have cut out a few hundred “verily”s and “It came to pass”es. The witnesses, most of whom apostasized later, still held to the fact that they had seen the plates, and that Heavenly Personages had spoken to Joseph Smith and to them, but Cowdry, David Whitmer, and Harris said later that these Heavenly Personages had appeared to them and told them to get out of the Mormon Church for it was corrupt. As Joseph himself said revelations came from three sources so his may have been a mixture. Perhaps the credulity of his followers pushed him on. He may have deluded himself without being consciously fraudalent. He did not pretend to be a man of the character of Gandhi or of St. Francis. But he did the thing they never tried to do: to establish a new religion. In Hiram, Ohio, where he was beaten and left for dead, the next morning he preached forgiveness to those who had beaten him, some of whom were in the audience, and he made three converts. He was here at his best. When he strutted in uniform before the Nauvoo Leglon and when he had Law’s and Bennett’s press destroyed he was at his worst. He was more realistic and much more of a likeable human being than the dour Alexander Campbell; than the Fox sisters who founded Spirituallsm in the New York area where he lived; than the fanatic Miller who expected the end of the world. He would seem more honest than Mrs. Eddy, who in 1866 got ideas from Quimby in Portland, Me. but who sald that these ideas were “uncontaminated by human hypothesis and divinely authorized.” She also said to follow her only inasmuch as she followed Christ and the Sermon on the Mount and that it was better to suffer death than to inflict it. Yet most minority religions make a great point also of obeying the law and of being super patriotic. This comes from a desire to be accepted, even though many of their other principles would tend to make them unacceptable. So it is that both the Christian Scientists and Joseph Smith when accused of being subversive could point to their patriotism and law obedience tenets. Mrs. Eddy, like Joseph Smith and the Mormons whocame after him, made changes in the “inspired” word, which if it was inspired ought not to need changes. He did not go as far as John Humphrey Noyes in the Oneida Community of free love. On the whole he was a charmmg man who brought happiness and hope to thousands. I do not think that he was a conscious imposter or rogue, except when his wife Emma heard about his sleepmg with Fannie Alger, the young girl who lived with them, and he produced the revelations on polygamy to placate her.

Kimball Young thinks that Joseph Smith was a parapath, that Is a person who cannot tell fact from fancy.[8]

Mrs. Brodie has written about Joseph Smith: “Tolerant of the foibles of his friends, since he could not easily forget his own, he provided a heaven where all men would be saved… Since his wife and children were dear to him, he made the marriage covenant eternal… Since power was sweet to him, he gave to every convert the promise of dominion over a star… He made the frontier evangelist seem by comparison all sound and fury… His people believed the best of him and thereby caused him to give his best.”[9] In the section on polygamy I will try to give a sympathetic account of his troubles and glories with the fair sex.

It could be that God told Joseph to start a new church for the previous ones had defaulted, but that power corrupted him as it has all other rellglous before and since.

Mormon Theology

M.R. Werner says, “If The Book of Mormon was inspired by God, it was his-second rate work.”[10] I have read it and I find more murder to the page than in the Old Testament, while some of the stories seem thinly disguised from similar incidents in the Bible. Although in Joseph Smlth’s version of that man being called to judgment who calls his brother “a fool,” he gives the spiritual translation which is also given in the Douay Version which the Catholic Church gives, as opposed to the materialistic version of the King James edition which says “without a cause,” which nullifies the whole idea that Christ is trying to bring out.

Werner further states, “The Book of Mormon is the story of the wanderings of three ancient peoples. One of them, the Jaradites, came directly from the Tower of Babel, and the other two came from Jerusalem or thereabouts. These people after prolonged sufferings, dissentions, and wars, finally arrived on the American continent. The two tribes from Jerusalem were headed by one Lehi, who led his people forth about the year 600 BC. He died in the wilderness and bequeathed the leadership of the expedition to his youngest son Nephi. But the other brothers disputed their father’s will, and the family split into the Nephites, advocates of the youngest son, and the Lamanites, followers of the oldest son, Laman. There was constant war between these two peoples, and finally the wicked Lamanites wiped out their righteous brother, after both tribes had arrived in America. In 420 AD the whole American continent was in the possession of the Lamanites, from whom the American Indians are descended. It was the task of Joseph Smith, Jr. to redeem the continent, which, by the way, is the Promised Land, for the righteous Nephites.”[11]

The Book of Mormon is uninteresting and dull. Even if all this story were true I see little reason for founding a new religion on it. For folks to live a communal life and according to the Word of Wisdom, to come out and be separate is the only way that a religion could stay pure. But the scores of revelations whereby Joseph tried to move people around and to serve his whims certainly came from anyone but divine origin. Their theology is not more far-fetched than others, for all religions have picked up myths and have accommodated themselves to current fetishes and superstitions.

“In the grand council called to ratify the Father’s plan, a great difference arose. The majority, led by the firstborn of the Father, our elder brother, Jesus the Christ, was ready to accept the plan with all its conditions. The minority, led by Lucifer, a ‘son of the morning,’ feared the isolation and the pains and ills of earth. For them Lucifer proposed that they should be sent to earth, but that provisions should be made by which they would suffer no pain and would not have to make any sacrifices. All of them would be restored with earthly bodies irrespective of their works on earth. Lucifer and his followers were thrown out of the council, and as opponents of God’s plan, became the devil and his angels, who strive ever to tempt men to disobey the laws of God… By the help of Adam, another great spirit in the council, Jesus organized the earth, and to atone for the act that brought man under the ban of death, he himself suffered death. Through Jesus the leader all men upon earth call upon for aid from the Father… our first parents chose life on earth with its inevitable death. That was the fall of man. All men, saints and sinners will be resurrected…”

“As the eternal intelligences were given a spirit body with which to explore the spiritual world, so this other body was needed as a tool in the exploration of the material world. Eternal progression requires contact and acquaintanceship with the whole universe… in conformity with the free agency bestowed upon all intelligent beings God called a council of the spirits to hear the plan… man must battle with the condltions of earth to whlch his body is subjected. That would foster faith, intelligence, and courage. The evil one would be allowed to range freely upon earth; and man would have to resist temptation. This would discipline the will and turn it into righteous paths. After a short period upon earth, man would be separated from the material body, in the experience called death. However, the body would later be restored to him in a purified state.”[12]

This explanation by Apostle Widstoe, more of a philosopher than most Mormon writers, is included here as being the clearest that I have found. In contrast to Brigham Young who continually talked about sending people who argued with him “cross lots to hell,” Widstoe says, “There can be no talk of hell… except for the very few sons of perdition, but undoubtedly the regret for lost opportunities will be keen among those in the lower degrees of glory.”[13] I have heard a Jesuit priest say that there was a hell but you couldn’t prove that any one was in it except the devil, and as far as heaven went we have the word of Christ that the Good Thief would see him that day in Paradise. Whether this was a preliminary entrance into heaven we will let the theologians discuss. Widstoe continues, “A religion without a hell seemed impossible to the misled preachers of Joseph’s day. The law of progress continues in full operation for every soul throughout eternity… all blemishes and imperfections will be corrected before the unending unity of body and spirit takes place… The dead retain in the spirit world the power to learn, to understand, and to choose. Did not Jesus say he was going to preach to the ‘spirits in prison?’” And it is this baptism for the dead, which like the prayers of Catholics for souls in purgatory that helps those who are dead.[14]

Adam-God Theory

“While Adam and Eve in Joseph Smith’s philosophy were raised to a foremost place among the children of men second only to the Savior. Their act was to be acclaimed.”[15] It remained for Brigham Young to bring the Adam-God theory forth, which is not mentioned by Mormons much today. Efforts have been made to explain it away, but on April 9, 1852 he gave his famous Adam-God sermon:

“When our father Adam came into the Garden of Eden, he came into it with a celestial body, and brought Eve, one of his wives, with him. He helped to make and organize this world… He is our Father and our God, and only God with whom we have to do.” This created quite a stir and in defending Brigham the headline in The Millenial Star of Dec. 10, 1853 had this assertion. “Adam Is Really God! And Why Not?”

This would seem bad enough but in his same April 9th, 1852 speech Brigham said: “When the Virgin Mary conceived the child Jesus, the Father had begotten him in his own likeness. He was not begotten by the Holy Ghost. And who is the Father? He is the first of the human family… Jesus, our elder brother, was begotten in the flesh by the same character that was in the Garden of Eden, and who is our Father in Heaven. Now let all who may hear these doctrines, pause before they make light of them, or treat them with indifference, for they will prove their salvation or damnation” (Journal of Discourses Vol. 1, Pages 50–51). Widstoe makes a distinction between the Holy Spirit and the Holy Ghost: “The Holy Spirit or ‘the light of truth’ is the spirit that proceeds from ‘the presence of God to fill the immensity of space.’ It is manifested in all natural phenomena. It penetrates all men. By its agency, the Lord may communicate with man, and may receive help from God. The Holy Ghost, on the other hand, is a Personage, the third member of the Godhead, to whom has been committed many important phases of the plan of salvation… prophecy, healing and the gift of tongues.”[16]

Werner says that “On Feb. 16, 1832 Smith and Rigdon saw Christ who told them that there were three orders of eternal bliss. The Celestial (Sun) order was conferred only on devout believers such as Smith, Rigdon, and their most faithful followers… the Terrestial (Moon) order, consisting of those who had received the testimony of Jesus after they had died… and the Telestial (Earth) order came one grade below and consisted of people who had never accepted the testimony of Jesus, such as the Jews, who would only be saved from eternal damnation in the resurrection.”[17] (Sun, Moon, Earth) inserted by author.

By 1844 Joseph had developed the idea of many gods which was not in The Book of Mormon. Neither was the cardinal principle of baptism for the dead in The Book of Mormon. Of course God could make new revelations, which is also a part of Mormon principle that He is an evolving God; that He was once man, and that we will come to be God, which is another mixture.

Here Brodie sums up Mormon theology by saying, “What Joseph had created was essentially an evangelical socialism, which made up in moral strength what it lacked in grandeur. Nearly every man had New Testament title—deacon, teacher, priest, elder, ‘seventy,’ or bishop. Each title carried a certain rank, progression from lower to higher being dependent upon a man’s faith, his zeal for the church, and the goodwill of his superiors in the hierarchy.”[18]

One of the most objective accounts of the Mormons was made by an Englishman, Richard Burton, who visited Salt Lake City in 1859 and wrote The City of Saints. He says: “The Mormons are like the Pythagorians in their procreation, transmigration, and exhaltation of souls; like the followers of Leucippus and Democratus in their atomic materialism; like the Epicurians in their pure atomic theories, their summum bonum, and their sensuous speculations; and like the Platonists and Gnostics in their belief of the Aeon, of ideas, and of moving principles in element. They are fetichists in their ghostly fancies, their evestra, which became souls and spirits. They are Jews in their theocracy, their ideas of angels, their hatred of Gentiles, and their utter segregation from their great brotherhood of mankind. They are Christians inasmuch as they base their faith upon the Bible, and hold to the divinity of Christ, the fall of man, the atonement, and regeneration. They are Arians inasmuch as they hold Christ to be ‘the first of God’s creatures’ a ‘perfect creature but still a creature.’ They are Moslems in their views of the inferior status of womankind, in their polygamy, and in their resurrection of the material body; like the followers of the Arabian prophet, they hardly fear death, because they have elaborated ‘continuation.’ They take no leap in the dark; they spring from this sublunary stage into a known, not into an unknown world.”[19]

As to the mechanics of Joseph’s revelations it is possible that he received word from God to start the real Church; but that prankster spirits gave him dimensions of buildings, advice as to whom to trust and whom to expel; that he had a gift to receive something similar to automatic writing, or even “hunches” as Edgar Cayce in our own generation received. And, as will be shown in the section on polygamy, it is plain that when Emma heard about his cohabitation with the two young girls in his household, that in defense he made up regulations to placate her, disguised as revelations from God. In contrast Brigham Young said that Joseph had had enough revelations and he did not need to give many, but when anyone contradicted him he said he was inspired and should be obeyed or, “I will unsheathe my bowie knife,” “we will slay them,” “cut their throats,” their heads chopped off…”[20] St. Paul at times said he was inspired and at other times spoke “of himself.” Mohammed had epileptic fits and it has been said that this was “mine infirmity” of St. Paul. Joseph’s grandfather Mack had them and it has been said that Joseph had them but outgrew them. This does not prove anything, except that it might have been that in some seizure he had visions.

I. Woodbridge Riley, in a scholarly work published by Dodd, Mead, Co. entitled The Founder of Mormonism in 1902 said that Joseph suffered from a form of epilepsy inherited from his grandfather but that he outgrew these “trances” by the time he was 30. He says, “Smith’s method was so far the commonplace method of the trance medium. The act of fixing the eyes on one particular point [as the peepstone in his hat. ―A.H.], supplimented by a state of quietitude through prayer, prepared the way for the influence of self-suggestion. His external acts are one thing, the subtle and self deceiving nature of his hallucinations another. He knew no more about the subconscious self and the law of association of ideas, than he did of the fact that his ‘Reformed Egyptian’ resembled the irregular and spasmodic writings of hypnotic subjects.” Riley also felt that in 1844 when he was at the height of his meglomania in military uniform his utterance as follows was psychotic: “I know more than all the world put together. I combat the error of ages.”

I also read the Biographical Sketches of his mother Lucy Mack Smith, published in Liverpool, England in 1853, which told of his digging for treasure. This has been edited out of recent editions of the life of Joseph Smith.

The effort of the Church historian Hugh Nibley in his booklet No Ma’am, That’s Not History, published in 1946 by Bookcraft in Salt Lake City is a pitiful attempt to answer Fawn Brodie’s book No Man Knows My History.

Brigham Young

His family was the poorest in the frontier town where he was born in New England, June 1, 1801. They did not have a horse, cow, or any land. His father made a living as a basket maker. His father had been in the revolutionary army and was very strict; “It was a word and a blow but the blow came first,”[21] Brigham said. Brigham had but 11 days of formal schooling; but he could take a clock apart and put it together again. He was very handy in many trades and made his living as a painter and glazier, but quit because it was a common practice to adulterate paint and cheat, and he wouldn’t do it. He was very independent and didn’t like to be pushed around. When his father wanted him to take the temperance pledge he said to him, “No sir, if I sign a temperance pledge I feel that I am bound, and I wish to do just right, without being bound to it; I want my liberty.”[22]

His sister and brother had read the Book of Mormon and accepted it, having received it as a gift from Joseph’s brother William, but it took him two years to make up his mind. He was baptized a Mormon April 14, 1832 at Mendon, N.Y. but he had not yet met Joseph Smith. When he did he commenced to speak in tongues. When he was young, two of his best friends were Henry Wells, the founder of Wells Fargo Express Company, and Isaac Singer, inventor of the Sewing machine.

He had married Miriam Works with whom he had two daughters, Vilate and Elizabeth. She was baptized into the Church shortly before she died of tuberculosis. Later he married thirty year old Mary Ann Angell. When he came to Kirtland, Ohio he turned over all of his property to the Church, and when five years later he was driven out he had nothing.

He was on a mission in Boston when Joseph was murdered, and he came back to Nauvoo just in time to prevent the dour and fanatical Sydney Rigdon from taking over the Church. When he was speaking to the Mormons, the story goes that he grew in stature and his voice changed so that he resembled the martyred Joseph. He persuaded those assembled to have the Council of 12 rule the Church, but he was not elected Prophet and second President until December 1847 in Salt Lake City. Emma never recognized him, saying that Joseph had said that his son was to rule the Church, but the boy was then too young. Brigham commenced to finish the Temple where he and others would be sealed to wives, and to prepare the emigrating to the west. He took over some of Joseph’s wives, but not Emma, the first being the poetess Eliza Snow. Emma later married a non-Mormon, Capt. Bideman, and they ran a tavern in Nauvoo.

Corning across the plains he was everywhere organizing families into tens and hundreds, planning singing and dances to keep up the spirit, planting seed for food at Winter Quarters, and going ahead with a smaller group to seek The Promised Land. One man grumbled a lot and Brigham announced that all who had complaints should bring them to this man and he would shout them forth as Chief Grumbler. This shut him up.

These Mormons were from the poorer classes in England, Scotland, and Wales and although they were called Latter-day Saints, it is obvious that many came to escape misery, and as the saying goes, “for the loaves and fishes,” except that these were scarce on the plains. Someone had to be the Moses to lead them and he had to feel that he was called by the Lord to do so. When the U.S. Government called for 500 soldiers to go to California, Brigham saw that the money they got would help the others so the 500 soon volunteered. It happened that his prophecy was fulfilled when he told them, “I promise you in the name of Israel’s God that not a man of you will fall in battle,”[23] for they did not get into the Mexican War. He told the men also, “If you are sick, live by faith, and let the surgeon’s medicine alone if you want to live.”[24] Saying he himself would rather die a natural death than be helped out by a Doctor.[25] He said, “Let the sick do without eating, take a little something to cleanse the stomach, bowels, and blood, and wait patiently, and let nature have time to gain the advantage over the disease.”[26] A Doctor had written to Brigham from the East asking what the prospects were. Brigham answered him. “The Mormons thought little of one who could not build his own house, irrigate his own land, and raise up a crop of wheat, corn, beans, peas, and potatoes. If the Doctor wanted to come under these conditions he would be made welcome, but if he had any thought of accumulating wealth, he would be wasting his time.”[27]

Just as he could organize the trek across the plains so could he organize the many wives and 56 children of his household. Anyone who was late missed the meal, as a warning bell rang 5 minutes before the meal. His children did not have to go to Church on Sunday but they couldn’t play games, ride horses, or sew doll clothing. True to his New England tradition he was against gambling. And he organized the women to glean the fields for wheat and corn for the poor. Naturally he was pestered by folks who asked his advice. He told them “not to ask for counsel when they were sure they were not going to take it.” He could hand it out but he could also take it, for when he had tongue lashed a Bishop in public he told him to keep his temper and not leave the Church. The Bishop answered, “Don’t worry brother Brigham, this is just as much my Church as it is yours.”[28] At that Brigham chuckled. Once a one-legged man asked him to pray for another leg for him. Brigham answered that he might do so but what was the use for when he was resurrected he would have to have three legs and be in a worse predlcament. The man hobbled away satisfied.[29] The English traveler Burton describes Brigham speaking at the Tabernacle: “He sat with his high hat on when he came to the platform. When he took his hat off that old man held his cough; that old lady awoke with a start; that child ceased to squall. Brigham bent over and expectorated in a spittoon, he took a slow drink of water, and commenced to speak powerfully and extemporaneously.”[30] He did not keep pigs and never ate pork. He told his wives to give the children milk and hard bread for breakfast, no meat, and plenty of fruits and vegetables.[31]

Tom Thumb visited Salt Lake City and met Brigham and said that he didn’t understand “about this here polygamy.” Brigham told him not to worry for when he was his size he couldn’t understand it either.”[32]

A woman came up to Brigham crying and said her husband told her to go to hell. He looked at her solemnly and said “Well, don’t go; don’t go.”[33] When his 51st child was born he rushed home from a trip to be present at the birth. She, Clarissa, tells of getting two pigeons each morning from the pigeon house, and turning her back while the overseer wrung their necks. This was for her father’s breakfast. He only ate two meals a day. This is the recipe for his only hot drink. It has been variously spoken of as Brigham tea or Mormon tea: 4 oz. each of ground bayberry, poplar bark and hemlock; 2 oz. each of ground ginger, cloves, and cinnamon; and one ounce of cayenne pepper. This would surely be a hot drink. He would not have his hair cut, but had it singed by barber Squires.[34] This is the grandfather of a Jack Mormon friend of mine here, who is also a barber. He reads the CW and the National Guardian. On December 9, 1850 the Territorial Legislature passed a blll giving Brigham Young control of City Creek and Canyon on the payment of $500. This was clearly a monoply.[35]

Water and wood were made public property when Salt Lake City was set up. Land was given by lot and the blocks were made large so that no one need be cramped; a bachelor got nothing, but a man with more than one wife could get land for an extra house. Brigham said: “We have no land to sell to the Saints in the Great Basin, but you are entitled to as much as you can till, or as you need for your support provided you pay the surveyor for his services, while he is laboring for you; and at a future day will receive your inheritances on the farming lands as well as in city lots; and none of you have any land to buy or sell more than ourselves; for the inheritance is of the Lord, and we are his servants, to see that everyone has his portion in due season.”[36] Brigham did not tarry but went east to Winter Quarters to help the next group get along. Once when religious services were being held, word came that emigrants were arriving. He at once dismissed the meeting and told the women to get hot food for them. They could always pray and sing but now was the time to feed the hungry.

After a few years there came a Reformation and a listening to the Word of Wisdom which said that no tobacco or liquor should be used and that men should not lead immoral lives. One of the leaders was Jedediah Grant, father of Heber Grant, who later became President of the Church. At a meeting Brigham arose, and asked all members present who had committed adultery to stand up. To his surprise and chagrin three fourths of them got to their feet. A Bishop arose and asked if the men had not misunderstood Brother Brigham’s question. He thought that the elders did not understand that the question referred only to the time since they had repented of sin and joined the Church… but when put to them again… the men all remained on their feet.”[37]

Captain Van Vliet said that Brigham kept his people captive so he offered to provide free transportation and the best of supplies to anyone who desired to leave Utah territory, on the condition that the government would provide similar means to all those in the East who wished to migrate to Utah. The Captain was won over and said he would resign from the Army rather than molest the Mormons.”[38] “Winter saints” were those who came with a stock of goods from the East and only stayed long enough to sell them and depart. A certain Mormon in another small town had a vacant lot that he was not using. One day he saw a man building a house on it and asked him “how come?” The man said the Bishop had told him to build there, for nothing could be held not in use or for speculation. The owner asked the Bishop by what authority he did this and he went away satisfied with the reply: “By the authority of the Priesthood of God.”[39] And a fellow who charged high prices for corn was told to refund the overcharge “or his head might roll in the snow.” He made the deal right.

In 1857, jealous politicians and clergy persuaded President Buchanan to send 2,500 troops to put down the “rebellious Mormons.” Brigham sent young Lot Smith with his guerillas to burn the fields, destroy everything in the path of the troops, scatter their cattle and horses, etc. Finally some Army Commissioners came to protest. Brigham had already moved nearly 40,000 people south to Provo, leaving only a skeleton crew to set fiire to the city if the troops entered. Before thousands in the Tabernacle he told the Commissioners: “What has the U.S. government permitted mobs to do to us in the past? Gentlemen, you can answer that question for yourselves… we have been plundered and whipped, and our houses have been burned, our fathers mothers, brothers, sisters, and children butchered and murdered by the score. We have been driven from our homes time and time again; but have troops ever been sent to stay or punish the mobs for their crimes? No. Have we ever received a dollar for the property that we have been compelled to leave behind? Not a dollar. Let the government of our country treat us as we deserve. That is all we ask of them. We have always been loyal and expect to continue so. But hands off! Do not send your armed mobs into our midst. If you do we will fight you, as the Lord lives… if you bring your troops here to disturb the people… Before the troops reach here, this city will be in ashes, every tree and shrub will be cut to the ground, and every blade of grass that will burn will be burned. Our wives and children will go into the canyons and take shelter in the mountains; while their husbands and sons will fight you to their last breath. And as God lives, we will hunt you by night and day til our army or yours is wasted away… if you want war you can have it; but if you wish peace, peace it is.”[40] Then the thousands of Mormons sang the rousing song “Zion.” Soon the army marched through the deserted town and 40 miles away set up a camp. Brigham used magnificent strategy and won.

In the sections on Blood Atonement and on Polygamy I will deal with aspects of Brigham’s character and of his beliefs which savor of Old Testament vengeance; and in the section on the United Order I will tell of his idea of the Kingdom of God on earth. Brigham held property as trustee in trust for the Church and also had business of his Own. Godbe, a merchant, left the Church because Brigham crowded him in business, and the four Walker brothers would not pay tithe and were also crowded by Brigham, and they left the Church and started the Walker Bank, which even today has a huge sign seen for miles. It was this attainment of power which made enemies for the Church and led to the oppressive laws from Washington, D.C. As in Nauvoo, the destruction of the press of the opponents of Joseph Smith brought the mob down on him, so here this monoply stirred up envy among the politicians and clergy. Brigham was not a theologian yet he came forth with some wild ideas that were not in the Book of Mormon. He was primarily an organizer and statesman; an honest and upright man in most of his dealings. The Church has produced no one since his death with a modicum of his fearlessness, or with a tenth of his ability. Despite his greatness he ordered that no monument be placed over his grave; just a flat stone. So north of where East Second Street South begins, off First Avenue there is an enclosed graveyard with Brigham’s grave and the graves of several of his Wives. However, when thousands of tourists come to see the Temple and the Square, the huge statue of Brigham Young stands with hand and arm stretched out to the Bank, and with his back to the Temple. This is joked about by Gentiles to suggest the worship of wealth by the Mormon Church today, but the members of other churches do not come with clean hands and they, as the Indians say, speak with forked tongues, for all churches worship Mammon, and do so not in the name of latter day prophets and martyrs, but in the name of that Christ who drove the money changers from the Temple.

Blood Atonement

From the 4th Chapter of First Nephi where Zoram slays Laban, through the whole Book of Mormon to the next to last chapter of Moroni there is more bloodshed, treachery, cannibalism, and ungodliness to the page than you can find in our Old Testament, notwithstanding that many of the words of Christ are paraphrased and His parables given in different settings, and He says that He comes to supercede the law of Moses and brings the Sermon on the Mount, and the people do live in peace and brotherhood for generations until they again become corrupted. Despite all these warnings of what comes to those of evil heart who seek vengeance, Brigham Young emphasized the necessity of the shedding of blood to atone for sins. It would seem that the death of Christ on the Cross was of no avail.

In 1893, William Smith, Joseph Smith’s brother, testified in court as follows: “I left Nauvoo in 1845 because my life was in danger if I remained there, because of my objections and protests against the doctrine of Blood Atonement.”[41] In a debate with George A. Smith, who advocated imprisonment rather than hanging, Joseph Smith says: “I was opposed to hanging, even if a man kill another. I will shoot him, or cut off his head, spill his blood on the ground, and let the smoke thereof ascend up to God; and if I ever have the privilege of making a law on that subject, I will have it so.”[42]

And Brigham said, “Suppose you found your brother in bed with your wife, and put a javelin through both of them, you would be justified, and they would atone for their sins, and be received into the kingdom of God. I would at once do so in such a case; and under such circumstances. I have no wife whom I love so well that I would not put a javelin through her heart, and I would do it with clean hands.” And “if you want to know what to do with a thief that you may find stealing, I say kill them on the spot, and never suffer him to commit another iniquity… I know this appears hard… if you will cause all those whom you know to be thieves to be placed in a line before the mouth of one of our largest cannon, well loaded with chain shot, I will prove by my works whether I can mete out justice to such persons, or not. I would consider it just as much my duty to do that, as to baptize a man for the remission of his sins. That is a short discourse on thieves, I acknowledge, but I tell you the truth as it is in my heart.” (Journal of Discourses, Vol. 1, pages 108–109)

And in the Temple, February 8, 1857, Brigham said: “This is loving our neighbor as ourselves; if he needs help, help him; and if he wants salvation and it is necessary to spill his blood on the earth in order that he may be saved, spill it… that is the way to love mankind.” And again Brigham said: “I could refer you to plenty of instances where men have been righteously slain, in order to atone for their sins.” (Journal of Discourses, Vol. 1, pages 108–109)

In 1857 troops of the U.S. Army were headed toward Utah. A migrant train of 150 well-armed and well-loaded folks from Arkansas came toward California. They were told to hurry westward and not to go the southern route. Attached to them were a few boisterous “Missouri Wildcats,” one of whom boasted that he had the very gun that killed “Old Joe Smith.” They would pass through towns and seeing chickens along the road would snap their heads off with their long snake-like whips. George A. Smith went ahead of them telling the Mormons not to sell any produce to this group. Finally they camped near Cedar City at a place called Mountain Meadows. Bishop Haight and Col. Dame met and as the ecclesiastical, and Army or Militia leaders, decided that the blood of the Prophet should be avenged. The Francher train was too well armed and could not be overcome without much loss of Mormon men, so it was decided to inflame the Indians to surprise them. This was done, but a few white men helped and the Mormon leaders did not want word to get out that they had had anything to do with it, so to cover up it was decided to bring a white flag and call for a truce, and then murder them all at a certain signal. John D. Lee, as farmer to the Indians, went along and he saw men, women, and children killed, but 17 children of tender age were saved and later sent back to Arkansas. The murderers took a solemn oath not to divulge their bloody deed. Brigham sent word not to harm the Francher party, but it was his bloodthirsty talk all these years that built up this episode. The Gentiles over the country made a great fuss about it. Warrants were made out for the leaders for years, but they hid away. John D. Lee had been at Nauvoo and was an adopted son of Brigham. He colonized southern Utah and Lee’s Ferry at the Colorado River was named after him. He had 19 wives and 64 children. Without a word and in the midst of his work for the Church he was excommunicated and most of his wives left him. Haight and Dame were out of the country and it is supposed that Brigham knew Lee would be caught in time and if he was to be the scapegoat then it were better that he not be a member of the Church when arrested. He was tried and offered immunity if he would implicate the Church but he would not do so, being true to his oath taken after the massacre. I read his two volume diary and the book about him by Juanita Brooks of the Utah Historical Society. When Lee was excommunicated, Brigham said that “under no circumstances should he ever be admitted as a member again.”[43]

To placate the Gentiles an all-Mormon jury found Lee guilty and sentenced him to be shot. He had been out on bail and a messenger from the Church, telling him to skip bail and it would be paid, did not reach him in time. Lee felt that he had spilled innocent blood and that the only way he could atone for it was by shedding his own blood, so I doubt if he would have fled if he had received the message in time. He was shot near his coffin and grave at Mountain Meadows on March 13, 1877. Before being executed he said, in part: “It seems that I have to be made a victim—a victm must be had, and I am the victim. I am a true believer in the gospel of Jesus Christ. I do not believe everything that is now being taught and practiced by Brigham Young. I do not care who hears it. I studied to make this man’s will my pleasure for thirty years. See, now, what I have come to this day! I have been sacrificed in a cowardly, dastardly manner. What confidence can I have in such a man (Brigham)! I have none, and I don’t think my father in heaven has any!”[43]

And five months and six days later Brigham was dead. The lawsuit of his last wife, Ann Eliza, coupled with the guilt he must have felt because the reputation of a Church must be secure even by the betrayal of a friend, must have lessened his will to live. It is a black mark upon his character.

But somehow truth comes out, so despite Brigham’s command, on Thursday, April 20, 1961, the First Presidency and the Quorum of Twelve met in a joint session and “It was the action of the Council after considering all the facts available that authorization be given for the re-instatement to membership and former blessings to John D. Lee.” “On May 8 and 9 following the necessary ordinances were performed in the Salt Lake Temple.”[44]

It only took the Mormons 85 years to admit their error; it took the Catholics 400 years to make Joan of Arc a saint. And no penitance has yet been shown for the St. Bartholomew Day massacre of thousands of Protestants by the Catholics, although the advent of the Worker Priests of unhappy memory was perhaps a gesture in the cosmic plan to be interpreted as always by mercenary clerics.

Brigham said “If a white man steals shoot him. If an Indian steals teach him better.” Brigham said of laws: “Strip a justice of all the legal mists and fog which surround him in this day and age; leave him no nook or corner of precedent, or common law ambiguous enactments, the accumulation of the ages, wherein to shelter, and it is my opinion that unrighteous decisions would seldom be given.”

The first murder trial in Utah was that of Howard Egan in 1851 for killing a man whom he caught in bed with his wife. His lawyer argued that if he had not done this he would have shared his wife’s guilt and by killing the man he wiped the slate clean. He was acquitted with honor, for had he not been an instrument in “blood atonement.”

The laws in early Utah were also bloody, the first four ordinances of the High Council providing 39 lashes for stealing, or being “disorderly or dangerous” and for adultry or fornication. The General Assembly on December 2, 1850, in Section 10 declared that in the case of murder, “he, she, or they shall suffer death, by being shot, hung, or beheaded.” None was ever beheaded, as each one sentenced could choose the method by which they were to be executed. A thief had to pay back fourfold, according to Section 28.[45]

Polygamy

“Wherefore, my brethern, hear me, and hearken to the word of the Lord; for there shall not any man among you have save it be one wife; and concubines he shall have none.” Jacob 2:27 Book of Mormon

“Inasmuch as this church of Christ has been reproached with the crime of fornication, and polygamy: we declare that we believe, that one man should have one wife; and one woman, one husband, except in the case of death, when either is at liberty to marry again.” First edition of Doctrine and Covenants section 101:4, printed in 1835, but taken out in 1876 and Sec. 132 on plurality of wives put in its place.

Revelation of Plural Marriage, July 12, 1843 in Nauvoo. Joseph’s secretary, Wm. Clayton states: “Joseph and Hyrum Smith came into the office… they were talking on the subject of plural marriage. Hyrum said to Joseph, ‘If you will write the revelation on celestial marriage, I will take it and read it to Emma, and I believe that I can convince her of its truth, and you will hereafter have peace.’ Joseph smiled and remarked. ‘You do not know Emma as well as I do.’ Joseph then said, ‘Well, I will write the revelation and we will see.’… Hyrum then took the revelation to read to Emma. Joseph remained with me in the office until Hyrum returned. When he came back, Joseph asked him how he had succeeded. Hyrum replied that he had never received a more severe talking to in his life.” (History of the Church, by Joseph Smith, Introduction to Vol. 5)

On August 29, 1852 Orson Pratt first publicly announced that the Mormon Church believed in plural marriage. This was in Salt Lake City.

Brigham Young said: “Now if any of you will deny the plurality of wives and continue to do so, I promise that you will be damned.”[46]

Wilford Woodruff said in June of 1879, “I will not desert my wives and children and disobey the commandments of God for the sake of accommodating the public clamor of a nation seeped in sin and ripened for the damnation of hell. I would rather go to prison and to death.”[47]

Lorenzo Snow, Fifth President of the Church, said, “The severest prosecutions have never been followed by revelations changing a divine law, obedience to which brought imprisonment or martrydom. Though I go to prison, God will not change his law of celestial marriage.”[48]

Polygamy renounced by President Woodruff, September 24, 1890, and ratified by the Church by the General Conference October 6th. “I Charles Penrose, wrote the Manifesto, with the assistance of Frank Cannon and John White, and it is no revelation from God, for I wrote it, and Wilford Woodruff signed it to beat the devil at his own game. Brethren God has not withdrawn this everlasting principle, or revoked it, for how can he revoke or withdraw an everlasting principle?” (This statement made at an Elders Conference, in London in 1908, and reprinted in the January 1929 issue of Truth.)

This is Woodruff’s revelation: “The Lord showed me by vision and revelation exactly what would happen if we did not stop this practice… all ordinances would be stopped… many men would be made prisoners… I went before the Lord, and I wrote what the Lord told me to write.” In part “Inasmuch as laws have been enacted by Congress forbidding plural marriages, which laws have been pronounced constitutional by the court of last resort, I hereby declare my intention to submit to those laws, and to use my influence with the members of the Church over which I preside to have them do likewise. There is nothing in my teachings to the Church or in those of my associates, during the time specified, which can be reasonably construed to inculcate or encourage polygamy; and when any Eider of the Church has used language which appeared to convey any such teaching he has been promptly reproved. And I now publicly declare that my advice to the Latter-day Saints is to refrain from contracting any marriage firbidden by the law of the land.”

On October 6, President Lorenzo Snow offered the following: “I move that, recognizing Wilford Woodruff as the President of the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints, and the only man on the earth at the present time who holds the keys of the sealing ordinances, we consider him fully authorized by virtue of his position to issue the Manifesto which has been read in our hearing, and which is dated September 24th, 1890, and that as a Church in General Conference assembled, we accept his declaration concerning plural marriages as authoritative and binding.” The vote to sustain the foregoing was unanimous. 10-6-1890. Page 257 Doctrine and Covenants.

The Second anti-polygamy Manifesto—April 3, 1904, by President Joseph F. Smith, prohibiting all plural marriages.

Verse 26 of the 132nd section of the Doctrine and Covenants teaches that only by the shedding of one’s blood may he atone for murder. It is no wonder that in the Mormon-dominated Legislature of 1962–63 a bill to abolish capital punishment did not get to first base. Seeking to be respectable the Mormon Church does not openly preach “blood atonement” these days any more than it advocates the old “Adam-God” theory, but these ancient bloodthirsty beliefs keep them from being true Christians.

The reader will now have a background to follow in detail—this story of deceit, bravery, and cowardice on the subject of polygamy. When the average person thinks of the Mormons he thinks of polygamy, and unless this subject is dealt with clearly and fully there is no understanding of the Mormons.

To begin with I should state that I have read the Booklet issued by the Reorganized Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints, Independence, Mo. entitled Joseph Smith Was Not a Polygamist. Because Emma would not admit anything about his wives or the revelation on polygamy shown to her by Hyrum Smith, and because there is not a court record of any marriages this Church denies that Joseph Smith ever thought of polygamy. A person either has to believe this flimsy evidence or that of scores of people who knew Joseph and his wives. I believe the latter.

Here is the evidence to prove that Joseph had many wives before he dared to tell Emma about it. In the testimony in the Temple, Lot Case page 320–321, Lorenzo Snow, Fifth President of the Mormon Church said that Joseph Smith sealed or married his sister Eliza in April of 1843 and the revelation on polygamy was July, 1843. Benjamin F. Johnson stated, “As I could not long be absent from my home and business, we soon returned to Ramus. On the 15th day of May some three weeks later the Prophet again came and at my home occupied the same room and bed, with my sister, that the month previous he had occupied with the daughter of the late Bishop Partridge as his wife.”[49] Emily Partridge relates as follows (from Historical Record, page 240) “The Prophet Joseph and his wife Emma offered us a home in their family, and they treated us with great kindness. We had been there about a year when the principle of plural marriage was made known to us, and I was married to Joseph Smith on the 4th of March 1843, Elder Heber C. Kimball performing the ceremony. My sister Eliza was also married to Joseph a few days later. This was done without the knowledge of Emma Smith. Two months afterwards she consented to give her husband two wives, providing he would give her the privilege of choosing them. She accordingly chose my sister Eliza and myself, and to save family trouble Brother Joseph thought it best to have another ceremony performed. Accordingly on the 11th of May, 1843 we were sealed to Joseph Smith a second time, in Emma’s presence… From that very hour, however, Emma was our bitter enemy. We remained in the family several months after this, but things went from bad to worse until we were obligated to leave the house and find another home.”

John D. Lee was many times a bodyguard of Smith when he went to sleep for a few hours with his young wives.[50] Records of the Nauvoo Temple show those women sealed to Joseph Smith. Lucinda Morgan Harris was the wife of William Morgan who was murdered for revealing Masonic secrets. Then she married George Harris but Joseph slept with her off and on for four years and Harris was present when she was sealed to Joseph in January 1846. Prescinda Buell visited Joseph twice at Far West jail. Her husband left the Church and she said she was not sure whether Buell or Joseph was the father of her son Oliver. Erastus Snow said that “my wife’s sister, Louisa Beman, was his (Joseph’s) first plural wife, she being sealed to him by my brother-in-law, Joseph B. Noble, April 5, 1841.” Zina Jacobs lived with Joseph while her husband was on a mission. After Joseph’s death she left Jacobs and married Brigham Young. Mary Lightner married a non-Mormon but gives a sworn statement that she was sealed to Joseph “in the Masonic Hall, over the old brick store by Brigham Young in February 1842 and then again in the Nauvoo Temple by Heber C. Kimball.” She bore Lightner ten children, although one of them might have been Joseph’s, and lived to be 95. Eliza Snow married Joseph at the age of 38, June 29, 1842, Brigham Young performing the ceremony. Later he married many single girls, but he seems to have picked on the wives of his friends. In Utah when polygamy was above board there does not seem to be any marrying to others than virgins. The above data is from Fawn Brodie’s No Man Knows My History, and from Tanner’s Mormonism.

I am not going into detail about Brigham’s wives other than to mention that he was a very busy man and romance did not seem to be a part of his nature, procreating being a part of his duty. Werner writes that Brigham Young, Jr. and his father both courted Lizzie Fenton but the boy got her.[51] But at the age of 61 he became passionately in love with Amelia Folsom, cousin to Grover Cleveland’s wife. She was 25 and when he married her she insisted on a house of her own, and until that was built she ate at a table alone with Brigham, and he escorted her all over town. She never had any children. He sent a rival on a mission. There were no lame, deformed or blind children among his 56 children. There were three sets of twins.[52]

One excuse for polygamy often given is that there were more females than males in Utah, but this is not true. For in those days one census showed 5,055 more males than females. George Bernard Shaw gives a better explanation: “Polygamy when tried under modern democratic conditions, as by the Mormons, is wrecked by the revolt of the mass of inferior men who are condemned to celibacy by it; for the maternal instinct leads a woman to prefer a tenth share in a first rate man to the exclusive possession of a third rate.” In fact it was only the more prosperous and more responsible men who attempted polygamy. At any time not more than 10% of the Mormons practiced it.

The one best book on the subject is Isn’t One Wife Enough? by Kimball Young, the grandson of Brigham Young. The only defect in it is that he told nothing of his own childhood in a polygamous family. He was head of the Department of Sociology at Northwestern University, and made a case history of 175 polygamous families and gives numerous illustrations of how it all worked out. He had doubts about the truth of Joseph’s revelations. He found 53% were successful, a fourth moderately successful, 23% had considerable conflict. Nearly half were in a high economic level, one third medium, and one-sixth were poor.

He tells of the first wife, who, if her husband was sleeping next door with his second wife, and did not get up early enough to suit her, would awaken him by throwing stones on the roof. In another family where they all lived in one house, as the children grew older all the boys would sleep in one big room and all the girls in another, no matter who the mother was. He tells of one family where the father and mother were much in love, and the two wives he married were a matter of duty to “live the principle.” These wives were engaged to young men but they liked the old man whom they wanted enough to live in polygamy. All these wives had the same ideas of desire for an education, a beautiful and peaceful home. The new wives were aggressive but the first wife didn’t mind it for she knew despite all that she was “first” in her husband’s affections. Another man’s wife had died and he wanted to marry two sisters but their mother wouldn’t allow it unless he married her too. This might be the perfect solution to the mother-in-law problem, for he married her first, and then the sisters. One sister didn’t have any children and she took care of the other sister’s children when needed, and it was a real happy family. Polygamy, if accepted by the wives made for unselfishness. With such a large family there had to be some system so each child had certain work to do. Today if sisters marry different husbands and live nearby they will help each other in child-birth, nurse the other’s baby if one has more milk than another, so in the days of polygamy, if sisters were married to one man they helped each other in the same way. If it happened that one was better at some function such as sewing, washing clothes, buying at the store, etc., then naturally that function devolved upon that certain wife. One could take care of the children while the rest went to Sacrament Meeting and there wouldn’t be the babble of children at the meeting, while in monogamy someone had to miss the sermons while the other partner took the squalling child outside. And if a woman was ill, some of the other wives could do her work and take care of her children and she need not worry. While Brigham Young had his favorite wife Amelia Folsom, and other men might have had any especial wife with whom he was deeply in love, with many it would seem that the women didn’t get much fun out of it, as the men procreated as a “duty” rather than with amorous intent.

Jonreed Lauritzen’s family pioneered the town of Short Creek, Arizona, in the “strip” north of the Grand Canyon, and he lived there for many years in this settlement of polygamists, although he, himself was not one of them. In his most recent novel, Everlasting Fire, deals of life in Nauvoo.

The description of the cooperation between the wives who all love the same husband given by the Indian wife Coziah is the best that I have read on this subject. Where life does not get dull for there was a chance of a new sister-wife coming along almost any day. The publisher would not permit any quotations from the book. Those interested can read for themselves: Doubleday Co., New York City, 1962. Price $5.95.

Kimball Young says that President John Taylor and Apostle Erastus Snow each had a segregated establishment for a wife, and the families had relatively little to do with each other except at reunions and special events. This limited both conflict and cooperation. Then there were some families that couldn’t take it. Another man had a freighting business and no one knew when he was coming or going. Once he came at night and his oldest girl wouldn’t allow him in her mother’s bedroom, saying there were too many children already.

The following is from The Journal of Discourses, Vol. 4, pages 55–57, by Brigham Young: To the women who were whining, “I am going to give you from this time (Sept. 21, 1856) to the 6th of October next, for reflection, that you may determine whether you wish to stay with your husbands or not, and then I am going to set every woman at liberty and say to them, now go your way, my women with the rest, go your way. And my wives have got to do one of two things: either round up their shoulders to endure the afflictions of this world, and live their religion, or they may leave, for I will not have them about me. I will go into heaven alone, rather than have scratching and fighting around me. I will set all at liberty. ‘What, first wife too?’ Yes, I will liberate you all.” None of them left.

Werner reports that someone asked, “How many wives have you Mr. Young? ‘Having wives is a secondary consideration; it is within the pale of duty, and consequently, it is all right. But to preach the Gospel, save the children of men, build up the kingdom of God, produce righteousness in the midst of the people; govern and control ourselves and our families and all we have influence over; make us of one heart and one mind; to clear the world from wickedness—this fighting and slaying, this mischievious spirit now (1871) so general, and subdue it and drive it from the face of the earth, and to usher in and establish the reign of universal peace, is our business, no matter how many wives a man has got, that makes no difference here or there.’”[53]

After the manifesto there were plural marriages, even in the Temple by Elder Lorine Woolley, but nothing could be proven. And during the preceding ten years when over a thousand men had gone to prison there was still many who felt that really no matter what was said in public that the Lord would not allow this law to be changed. One man had been in jail three times and said that he would live openly with his wives. He did so and was not bothered again. The two best books on this subject are The Family Kingdom, and I Have Six Wives, both by Samuel Woolley Taylor, grandson of President Taylor who died in exile. The first book is about his father John W. Taylor, an Apostle who married three more wives after the Manifesto and was finally excommunicated for it. He is quoted by his son as saying that the persecutions came “because we insist on competing for wealth and political advantage with the Gentiles. If we kept to ourselves and minded our own aflairs strictly, nobody would care how many wives we had.”[54] It is said that President Taylor had a revelation that the plural marriages should continue secretly and that he told Lorin Woolley definite instructions on this matter. This was given to President Taylor when he was in hiding at the Woolley home in Centerville on Sunday evening, September 26, 1886. Members of the Council had been pressing Taylor to issue a Manifesto rescinding polygamy. He told them to come back the next day and he would ask the Lord about it that night. He did so and the next day showed them the revelation given to him saying that the principle was everlasting and was not to be rescinded, but the Committee would not allow it to be promulgated for it would mean jail for all of them. So Taylor chose five of them and gave them orders to continue the priesthood secretly until the time would come when polygamy could be open again. Later when Taylor was dead and his son John had been excommunicated for taking on his four wives since Woodruff’s Manifesto rescinding polygamy and Joseph F. Smith’s second Manifesto in 1904, one of these five asked John W. Taylor to be head of a new Church. He refused to do so saying, “The Church has disowned me but I will never disown my Church. I will never join with any bitter group working for its downfall. I will never repudiate the Principle, but I here and now repudiate all men who try to use it in an attack on the Church.”[55]

Taylor says of his father: “When he was in town it was a gala occasion with a holiday aspect. It always meant a gathering of the clan with Mother, Aunt Nellie, Aunt Roxie, and Aunt Rhoda beamingly preparing the feast, a couple of dozen brothers and sisters on deck together with several dozen kids from the neighborhood.[56] Perhaps because he was away so much he was a heroic and legendary figure, not only to all his children but to all his wives… the stars never left the eyes of his wives, and its glow was reflected in the eyes of the children. If John W. Taylor sacrificed career, position, and opportunities for his families, he had the satisfaction of having his love for them returned in full. He never tasted the bitterness of having paid a great price for a bad bargain. His families were the all important thing to him in this world and the next, and to his family he was the all important man.”[57] On August 25, 1917, shortly after his death, the Mormon Church issued a statement that he had been “excommunicated from the Church… the excommunication has never been revoked, rescinded, nor in any way modified… Joseph F. Smith, Anthon H. Lund, Charles W. Penrose, Heber J. Grant,”[58] signed the statement. This story of a happy polygamous family is charming and ought to be read by all who want a fair picture of the subject. It is not many men who could have six wives and make each one feel that she was really the most special.

An equally charming book, but more critical of polygamy, for the author does not believe in it, is I Have Six Wives. It is a case history, the author having read the diaries of these wives, of a man now living in Salt Lake City with six wives, and having done time for it twice, but now he seems not be bothered by the authorities. I met him five years ago when I first visited and spoke in Salt Lake City, and I have since met him and some of his wives and children. Naturally the correct names are not given in this book, as the purpose was to explain how one polygamist of the thousands living in Utah, Idaho, and Arizona function in these modern ways. He says, “What were the stresses and strains of this type of life in the modern age? Golda was physically the largest wife and the most aggressive. She obviously was queen of this establishment, as befitted the senior wife. This was as it had been. There was outspoken Amy, small and dark; Faith, slender and gentle; Becky, with auburn hair and the spirit to go with it, serene with classic beauty; the sisters Pepita and Sybil, Pepita thin and intense, Sybil fair, calm and placid… Why? What led them there?”[59]

When the author was visiting the family one night the husband asked if it was not about bedtime. They all went to bed without a word, 26 of them. The author had only one child and it was a battle to get her to bed, he said. The polygamous father smiled and said, “With a family like mine there has to be order.” None of this family had ever been on relief, even when he was in prison.[60]

Mr. Taylor visited Short Creek, Arizona, in the strip north of the Grand Canyon several times. Over a million dollars has been poured into this desert community by polygamists from Salt Lake City and Los Angeles. The young men work in neighboring towns and turn their wages over to the leaders, but the older leaders seem to have a monopoly of young wives. This is called the United Effort rather than the United Order, for they are only “trying.” The first big raid was March 7, 1944, when polygamists were arrested in three states. In Salt Lake City, 15 men were sentenced up to five years on the charge of “unlawful cohabitation.” Their attorney presented a list of 886 caught-in-the-act sexual offenders on record in the city the previous year. All of them had been fined from $5 to $50 and released without publicity. The Mormon Church activated this persecution. The second raid was July 26, 1953 at Short Creek where Governor Pyle sought to build his political fences by sending 100 troops on a Sunday morning to arrest these terrible polygamists. (The whole thing backfired and he was defeated in the next election mainly because of this foolish self-righteous attack.) Byers, the hero of I Have Six Wives, had left a day and a half ahead of the raid. As in previous Mormon history, the reason for the raid was not polygamy; this was the excuse. The real reason being that the ranchers were being school-taxed to support all these kids, and the Mormons could outvote the ranchers if they took the idea.

When Governor Pyle’s troops arrived the children were lined up in their best clothes singing God Bless America. 385 in all were arrested, mostly children, and taken to Phoenix where Judge Lorna Lockwood promised that the children would not be taken from their mothers, but this was done anyway. I left Phoenix for New York City about that time and the last $5 I made I gave to the Catholic lawyer who was defending them in court. Two years later Taylor visited Short Creek and they had the schoolhouse over on the Utah side, and the families were living together again. I know of one woman of this group whose husband was a drunkard, who drove a truck to Mexico taking her children with her. Under the name of LeGrande King Taylor, writes about one of the worst frauds among Mormons, polygamous or regular. This man’s real name is Leroy Wilson and he wrote to me for years when I was in Phoenix trying to get me to persuade the Hopi to allow him to build some enormous earth covered area for the Hopis to hide in. He had got hold of a CW in Chicago and thought I might be added to his sucker list. He lived on a mountain west toward St. George, with all kinds of junk machinery and cars and trailers, the latter for his wives. He was a big bag of wind who made everyone else live on cracked wheat while he ate steaks on his trips over the country getting suckers to bite on his many inventions. Time magazine told a few years later of someone murdering him, and the sheriff figuring that a good deed had been done. Taylor says of him: “But to ask a question of LeGrande King was like fighting a pile of feathers, as I can certify. Brother LeGrande didn’t evade—he simply engulfed you in a torrent of words.”[61]

Jonreed Laurtizen, the writer, had left when one of his teen age daughters stood a good chance of getting engaged to a polygamous boy. This is likely the first time in America where hostages have been taken legally. Taylor asked these polygamous men why they didn’t go to Los Angeles where they wouldn’t be bothered by the law. They answered, “But that wouldn’t advance the cause. We will never win the fight with secret practice. Somebody has to keep the issue alive.” Frank E. Moss was the Federal D.A. in 1956 (he is now U.S. Senator) and his position was not to have big raids but only to take them to court upon complaint. He says, “The problem that confronts us is that these men have established families and have a great many minor children. They are supporting their children to the full extent of their ability. In that respect they are acting in accordance with the standards we apply to good citizenship. They don’t seem to bother their neighbors. They are not offensive and are not committing other crimes or carousing. They are quiet and sober citizens. We shouldn’t disturb them.”[62] This would seem to be a sane attitude, and much better than those puritans who bought a home for wives who wanted to escape polygamy in Brigham’s time, and all whom they got to live there was one non-Mormon prostitute. Uranium has been found at Short Creek. If they become prosperous that will be a greater test than persecution. The Short Creek case came to the Supreme Court and was decided against them, and queer as it may seem, the liberal Justice Douglas was against them while the Catholic Frank Murphy, and Justices Jackson and Black were for the Mormons. It is conceivable that if a case came up again the Supreme Court could declare polygamy legal. Then the Mormon Church, if it had nerve enough, could allow it to come up from the underground. It is difficult to get any statement on a controversial issue from the heads of the Mormon Church. John Stewart of Logan, Utah, in his small book, Brigham Young and His Wives, 1961, a Mormon writer, says, “Seven of our nine Church Presidents have lived plural marriage,[63] and that this principle still is and always will be a doctrine of the Church.” Taylor says that “No Mormon can denounce discarded practices without renouncing his heritage. Where can the line be drawn between the belief in and the practice of?”[64]

“…the restoration of the Church and Gospel of Jesus Christ, is to prepare for the second coming of the Savior, which is nigh at hand; to help usher in His great millenial reign, when the Gospel in its fulness, including plural marriage, will be lived by worthy members of the Church,”[65] said Prof. Stewart. And he further states, “…plural marriage is the patriarchal order of marriage lived by God and others who reign in the Celestial Kingdom. As well might the Church relinquish its claim to the Priesthood as the doctrine of plural marriage.”[66]

I have attended church meetings of the Church of the First Born of the Fulness of Times with a mailing address in El Paso, Texas, and a colony 200 miles south in Mexico. About a thousand polygamous live there, while Short Creek has about 300. The congregation are mostly young folks in the lower economic bracket, earnest and likeable. They talk about the consecration of worldly goods to the Church but feel that it can’t be asked of people much these days who seldom own anything clear, but have it in hock. I will continue to visit their meetings. Old timers with whom I have talked say that there are 18 groups of polygamous living, mostly in Utah. Nothing is done about it unless there is a complaint, and as with moonshiners in Kentucky, no one likes to be a “stoolie,” and it is difficult to get a conviction.

My friend John Marshall Day has completed a thesis on the Fundamentalists, and especially the Short Creek group whom he visited for two days, but by that time they refused to give him any more information. He states that the older men in the village who come from the most prominent polygamist heritage have the most wives and seem to have the pick of the young girls. For some strange reason more girls than boys are born there. When young men went to war and came back on furlough they were encouraged to marry; the reason being it is thought that the group wanted the allotment checks. This economic basis is also shown in that in the Depression in 1935 and Short Creek wives listed the same husband to get their relief checks. This awakened the authorities to the polygamous situation, and as more got on relief and as more children came of school age the Arizona ranchers were worried about the expense and put the heat on Governor Pyle to do something. There is a story of an Arizona official who came by chauffeur driven limousine the 400 dusty desert miles, and in a few minutes he said, “If I had to live here, I’d want more than one wife myself,” and he hurried back to civilization without another word.

The leaders assigned by President John Taylor to work in secret and keep the polygamous faith were in order, John W. Woolley, Lorin C. Woolley, Leslie Broadbent, John Y. Barlow, Joseph Musser. The current Apostle is Roy Johnson. The polygamists criticize the Mormon Church for sending missionaries in style instead of “without purse or script” as in the old days, and they say that no revelation has been given the heads of the church since they apostisized on polygamy. Mr. Day thinks that the fact that Short Creek is not sustaining and that the young men and girls go out in the world and work to bring money back to the colony will evenutally bring outside ideas there and the young folks will not so readily do as they are told.

Mr. Day points out that the Mormons, like the early Christians, started as a sect and developed into a church and gave up enough of their ideas to accommodate themselves to the outside world. They all started out dreaming of a utopia; the dimensions of which were determined what they lacked here. The religions founded in a desert country dreamed of a heaven or utopia like unto a Garden of Eden. The Eskimos thought of heaven as a nice warm place and their hell was a cold sky.

The fact that these fundamentalists accepted state aid is as much of a defeat of their ideal, as that of the Mormon Church in doing away with pglygamy. If they despised the Gentile government why did they try to live off it?

Negroes

Generally speaking the Mormon Church has denied Negroes membership of first class in their Church. There is not as much pressure for them to change as there was in the case of polygamy. As stated before the appearance of George Romney on the political scene may encourage the Church to ease up on the record of the Church on this subject. Joseph Smith has been quoted for and against slavery and while the latest he said on the subject was when he was running for President in 1844 to the effect that slaves should be bought from their masters, by money received from the sale of public lands, and freed. It is possible that this might have been a political plank, rather than a sincere expression of his thought.

However, it is a matter of church history that Elijah Able, a negro, was ordained an Elder March 3, 1836, and a Seventy, April 4, 1841. In 1883, as a member of the Third Quorum of Seventy, he left Salt Lake City on a mission to Canada. It was said that because he had labored in the construction of the Temple he was elevated to the Seventies.[67]

William E. Barrett, Vice President of Brigham Young University says in The Church and the Negro People: “It appears that one person of Negro blood had been ordained an Elder by William Smith while he was on his mission in New York State as evidenced by a letter appearing in Journal History, June 2, 1847, ‘At this place (Batavia, N.Y.) I found a colored brother by the name of Lewis, I am informed, has a son who is married to a white girl and both are members of the Church.’”[68]

Joseph F. Smith in a funeral service for a colored Mormon by the name of “Aunt Jane” said, “She would in the resurrection attain the longings of her soul and become a white and beautiful person.”[69] And in a letter from the First Presidency, July 17, 1947, to Dr. Lowry Nelson: “We are not unmindful of the fact that there is a growing tendency, particularly among some educators, as it manifests itself in this area, toward the breaking down of race barriers in the matter of intermarriage between whites and blacks, but it does not have the sanction of the Church and is contrary to Church doctrine.”[70] What egotism for Joseph F. Smith? How does he know that a fine looking colored person must of necessity prefer to be white?

In the History of the Church (Vol. 3, page 29) the question is asked of Joseph Smith, “Are the Mormons abolitionists?” The answer is “No, unless delivering the people from priestcraft, and the priests from the power of Satan, should be considered abolition. But we do not believe in setting the Negroes free.” Also, while an abolitionist spoke in the early 1830s in Kirtland, Ohio, Joseph in the Messenger and Advocate, and as quoted in his History ofthe Church (Vol. 2, pages 436–438) said that the attendance was very few, “the gentleman to hold forth his arguments to nearly naked walls… I do not believe that the people of the North have any more right to say that the South shall not hold slaves, than the South have to say the North shall… but I can say, the curse is not yet taken off from the sons of Canaan, neither will be until it is affected by as great a power as cause it to come; and the people who interfere the least with the purposes of God in this matter, will come under the least condemnation before Him.”

Brigham Young said, in Journal of Discourses (Vol. 7, p. 290), “The Lord put a mark upon him, which is the flat nose and black skin. Trace mankind down to after the flood, and then another curse is pronounced upon the same race—that they should be ‘the servant of servants;’ and they will be, until the curse is removed, and the abolitionists cannot help it, nor in the least alter that decree.” And again in Vol. 10, page 110, he says, “Shall I tell you the law of God in regard to the African race? If the white man who belongs to the chosen seed mixes his blood with the seed of Cain, the penalty, under the law of God, is death on the spot. This will always be so.”

Joseph Fielding Smith, next in line to the Presidency of the Mormon Church, and who is Church Historian, was asked about Negroes being allowed in the early Mormon Church as Elders. The reply dated June 10, 1960 said, “Negroes were not ordained in the early Church.” This is in contrast to the statement of David O. McKay, who is more liberal, and who is now President of the Mormon Church, who said in a letter of Nov. 3, 1947, “I know of no scriptural basis for denying the priesthood to Negroes other than one verse in the Book of Abraham (1:26)… The real reason dates back to our pre-existent life.” Note that he says nothing about the Old Testament, Cain and Ham, etc.

Orson Pratt gives the theory (Journal of Discourses, Vol. 1, page 63): “Among the Saints is the most likely place for the spirits to take their tabernacles, through a just and righteous parentage. They are to be sent to that people that are the most righteous of any other people on earth;… This is the reason why the Lord is sending them here, brethren and sisters;… The Lord has not kept them in store for five or six thousand years past, and kept them waiting for their bodies all this time to send them among the Hottentots, the African negroes, the idolatrous Hindoos, or any other of the fallen nations that dwell upon the face of the earth.”

Joseph Fielding Smith further explains the idea (Doctrines of Salvation Vol. 1, p. 61): “There is a reason why one man is born black and with other disadvantages, while another is born white with great advantages. The reason is that we once had an estate before we came here, and were obedient, more or less, to the laws that were given us there.”

James Boyd Christensen in his Masters Thesis, University of Utah, says, “In 1850 Utah was the only western territory that had Negro slaves. It was one of the few places in the United States where Negro and Indian slavery occurred in the same locale in the same period. It is interesting to draw a parallel between the attitudes of the Mormon colonizers toward Negro slavery and the Indian slave trade. In short, they countenanced slavery of Negroes among them while they abhorred the slave traffic among the Indians and legislated against it.”[71]

“The U.S. census for 1860 gives the number of colored persons in the Territory of Utah as 59: 30 free colored and 29 slaves.” And this from the Salt Lake Tribune of May 31, 1939: “Patrick Sullivan, employee of a Salt Lake Abstract firm, while searching the record for real estate information, came across the copy of a bill of sale for a Negro boy named ‘Dan’ in a book containing transactions for the year 1859. The slave was sold by Thomas S. Wllllams of ‘Great Salt Lake City’ to William H. Hooper, same address, for $800.”

Just as polygamy and the Adam-God theory were contrary to the Book of Mormon so is this degradation of the Negro, for in 2 Nephi 26:33 we read, “he inviteth them all to come unto Him and partake of his goodness; and he denieth none that come to him, black and white, bond and free, male and female; and he remembereth the heathen; and all are alike unto God, both Jew and Gentile.” Of course churches that accept capital punishment and war all in the name of God deny Christ and His New Testament, for Philip baptized an Ethiopian, and Jeremiah asks, “Can an Ethiopian change his skin?” Peter is told that God is no respector of persons for “God hath shewed me that I should not call any man common or unclean… But in every nation he that feareth him, and worketh righteousness, is accepted with him.”

In the 1963 session of the Utah legislature several hundred members of the NAACP and others demonstrated for civil rights legislation, and as a result one of the several bills were brought out of committee and passed and signed by the Governor, repealing laws which did not allow mixed marriages of different races. But Utah still remains the only state outside of the deep south that does not have laws of fair employment, fair housing, and of access to public accommodations for those of all races. This is no doubt because of the prejudice in Mormon theology against the Negro. However, the speakers at the Civil Rights meeting at the Unitarian Church were nearly all liberal Mormons from the University who were not afraid to thus go counter to the teaching of their Church and Lowell Bennion spoke against capital punishment at the Senate Hearing. He is a prominent Mormon educator. Catholics do not seem to be interested in this subject in Utah, although some priests belong to the NAACP. The Catholic idea of refusing to mix with other denominations, even for a good cause, seems to have prevented them from attending Civil Rights meetings with the Unitarians. In May 1963, upon motion of non-Mormon Mayor “Brack” Lee, the City Commissioners passed a resolution unanimously favoring the serving of Negroes in all restaurants and public places. This was taken because a Negro reported that he had been refused service in a restaurant, but this is a recommendation, not a law.

Mormons Weigh Stand on Negro—May End Ban on Complete Membership in Church

by Wallace Turner. Special to the New York Times. Salt Lake City, June 3 (1963).

The top leadership of the Mormon Church is seriously considering the abandonment of its historic policy of discrimination against Negroes. Because the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints has a lay priesthood to which almost every adult male member belongs, the effect has been to limit Negroes to second-class membership. “We are in the midst of a survey looking toward the possibility of admitting Negroes,” said Hugh B. Brown, one of the two counselors serving President David O. McKay in the First Presidency of the Mormon Church. “Believing as we do in divine revelation through the President of the church, we all await his decision,” Mr. Brown said.

Mr. Brown, a 79-year—old former attorney, said he believed that if the change were made, it would be a doctrinal revision for Mormonism of a magnitude matching the abandonment of polygamy in 1890. The whole problem of the Negro is being considered by the leaders of the church in the light of racial relationships everywhere,” Mr. Brown said. “We don’t want to go too fast in this matter. We want to be fair.” Under Mormon doctrine, the President is the chairman of the prophets. He is always the senior member of the Council of Twelve Apostles, each of whom is considered to be a prophet, a seer and a revelator. A major doctrinal change would be discussed with high church councils before its enunciation by President McKay.

There are now about 2,000,000 Mormons, and only a few hundred of these are Negroes. Members of all races, except the Negro, are in the priesthood. The church also has forbidden Negroes the right of marriage in a Mormon temple. In addition, the marriage of Negroes to members of other races is forbidden by the church.

Throughout Mormon writings is the hint that the ban might someday be removed. Brigham Young once asked himself how long Negroes were to endure the curse of Cain. He thought it would be “until all the other descendants of Adam have received the promises and enjoyed the blessings of priesthood and keys thereof.” More positive hope was held out by President Wilford Woodruff, who led the church when polygamy was abandoned. He said: “The day will come when all of that (Negro) race will be redeemed and possess all the blessings which we now have.” The Mormon church, Mr. Brown emphasized today, has never closed the door to Negroes, nor to the possibility of removing the limitation on their participation in church affairs.

In a telephone conversation June 8th, Hugh B. Brown told Jerald Tanner that he was misquoted in the part concerning the change of policy, however, he expressed his approval of the article by saying that it was “on the whole very fair.”

Within a few hours after the New York Times containing this article had been on the stands or public containers downtown, all copies were gone. Mr. Tanner reprinted the article in a one page leaflet.

The Word of Wisdom

The Word of Wisdom was given by Joseph Smith, February 27, 1833, and it forbids the use of tea, coffee, strong drinks, and tobacco. The Church authorities today have changed the records trying to prove that Joseph and Brigham were strict on this matter. Joseph himself admitted that he often became drunk, and in Nauvoo he installed a bar in the Nauvoo House only to have Emma tell him that either she would move across the street or the bar had to go. Emma stayed. Elder Clark preached against drinking and Joseph publicly reproved him saying that Noah got drunk and yet he was counted by God to be a righteous man. Joseph had a pious sober clerk by the name of Robert Thompson. To wake him up Joseph told him one day, “Robert, I want you to go out and get on a bus, go and get drunk and have a good Spree. If you don’t you will die.”[72] In less than two weeks he was still sober but by that time he was dead and buried. In Carthage jail soon before they were kllled, all, including Joseph drank wine that the guard brought. John D. Lee tells of many times when working on the Nauvoo Temple they got a barrel of wine and drank all they wanted. Brigham Young, on October 8, 1859, spoke against drinking “until you really need it.” When his Discourses were printed this sentence was left out. At first the Utah Hotel which is owned by the Church did not sell tobacco or liquor. Now it sells tobacco and all who bring their own liquor can get accommodation of the extras that go with it. And KSL, which is owned by the Church, advertises tobacco, coffee, and beer.

I have heard Mormon leaders at their Sacrament Meeting at the University declare that while they obeyed the Word of Wisdom that a person could do all this and be selfish and greedy and miss the real meaning of the Gospel. As stated elsewhere when I came to Utah I ceased drinking tea and coffee as a courtesy to the true Mormon way of life and Mary ceased smoking Cigarettes. There are jokes told of Mormons who put their beer cans in their neighbor’s garbage.

Tithing as practiced in the Mormon Church is something that Mormons pride themselves on, and Gentiles are generally envious of the ease with which they get money. As given by Joseph Smith, “The celestial law requires one-tenth part of all a man’s substance which he possesses at the time he comes into the Church, and one-tenth part of his annual increase ever after. If it requires all that a man can earn to support himself and family, he is not tithed at all.” (Millennial Star, Vol. 9, page 12)

The Mormon Welfare Plan in its present state was inaugurated during the 1930 Depression. At 7th South and 7th West they have a huge elevator full of wheat, a milk processing plant where milk from a dozen stake farms is brought and made into evaporated milk, powdered milk, butter, cottage cheese, and cheese, and a cannery that any can use, paying only for the tin cans. Those Mormon families that would ordinarily be on county aid can come here and get canned food, milk, meat, clothing, or whatever they need. No money is exchanged. Those who are not able to come to the warehouse have it delivered daily or weekly in plain trucks. There is a weaving department, furniture repair, shoe repair, and a barber shop. Many men from our Joe Hill House go there and work a day or two and get what they need. The Mormons pay taxes to the county and state for the aid given to Gentiles but they tithe themselves to help their poorer brethren. On the first Sunday of each month all good Mormons fast for two meals and turn this money over to their Bishop to pay for rent, utilities, etc. for the poor. When this fast is broken they have their monthly testimony meeting where any member can get up and tell of the blessings of his or her religion. I have attended many of these fast meetings, even when on my 45 day fast, and the Bishop generally had some of the congregation drive me home. It was all down hill going home but I appreciated their thoughtfulness. As at Quaker meetings, Christian Science Wednesday evening meetings, and service club, and sales meetings there is a lot of mutual backslapping, and some very monotuous conversation, but at times a sincere and eloquent note does come through.

Perhaps half a dozen wards will get together and have a stake farm to produce milk, or produce, or have a chicken ranch, cattle ranch, or, as near Mesa, Arizona, a cotton ranch. In Houston, Texas, they produce peanut butter. They have a 240,000 acre cattle ranch in Florida, and citrus juice is canned in Florida, Arizona, and California and sent in exchange for applesauce, etc. from Utah. Some years ago when there was a big flood in upper California the Mormon Relief was days ahead of the Red Cross or any other help. Many elderly folks work at the warehouse to pass the time away or because they want to help. All this is in the old Mormon pioneer tradition and is something that those who depend upon the Welfare State could also do if they were not spoiled by the handout system of public relief. Mormons who got help when they are handicapped are encouraged to work to pay back if they are able to do so later.

The United Order

Reference has been made in this chapter to the United Order. This was tried out in Kirtland, Far West, Nauvoo, Salt Lake City, Brigham City, Orderville, and other Utah towns. The idea was that upon joining the Mormon Church each one should consecrate all that he had and turn it over to the Bishop. He in turn would judge how much was needed to keep the family going and if the man did not have enough he was given back enough to keep him in necessities. All surplus wealth was meant to be given over for the Church to administrate to those in need. The panic of 1837 toppled over the Kirtland economy, and persecution in Far West and Nauvoo prevented this plan from working. Brigham Young saw “winter saints” coming to Utah with a stock of goods and after selling them go away, or he saw Gentiles getting a lot of business. He then started the ZCMI (Zions Cooperative Mercantile Institution) which nearly bankrupted the Gentiles. Now a $17,000,000 business is done in their two stores in Salt Lake City. The idea was a good one for the Mormon economy, for scores of industries were started and people were helped. But eventually in Brigham City the cooperatives got into the hands of a clique, and in Orderville the big wages to be made in the nearby mines weaned away the members. The increasing secularization of life in this century has made nearly all other cooperative effort into being that in name only, or as in the case of the Amana Community, they went directly into the capitalistic way of life. The inertia of most people tends to allow the direction of community life to get into the hands of the few, and while the leaders may be unselfish, it is seldom that their children inherit ideals. In 1880, the 50th anniversary of the founding of their church, a jubilee was declared, and tithes owed were cancelled, and all debts were supposed to be forgiven. In 1980 such clemency would break up the banker clique that controls the church.

Mormons Evaluated

Joseph Smith when he was young, Saw a golden censer swung…

A Moses or an Abraham Felt that nations in him swam…

He spun-the world four thousand years Back to Jacob and his steers…

And the new age caught them up, Stilled the psaltery, drained the cup… [73]

―Robert P. Tristram Coffin

V.F. Calverton, who wrote Where Angels Fear To Tread, concerning many communities, gave this report on the Mormons: “The Book of Mormon was founded upon theories no more fantastic than those of the Bible; it was interspersed with the doctrine of the day, rife with paradoxes and contradictions, and shot full of irrational and incredible supposition and conceptions.”[74]

William Mulder and A. Russell Mortensen, in their Among the Mormons, a sympathetic anthology of their beliefs, say in the introduction, “Joseph Smith’s unfolding theology seemed tuned to all the reform fiddles of the times. He filled the breathless years with experiments in theocracy and communitarianism and temperance and polygamy, with expectations of millennium and the Second Coming, with world evangelism and practical programs of emigration and colonization, with aspirations and nonconformities which the frontier, despite its vaunted individualism could not abide.”[75]

Kimball Young, grandson of Brigham Young, feels that a score of prominent families control the Mormon Church and that they have lost that purity and desire to be different according to their faith, and have succumbed to the secular way of life.

Prof. Richard T. Ely of the University of Wisconsin, wrote, “The organization of the Mormons is the most nearly perfect piece of social mechanism with which I have ever, in any way, come in contact, excepting the German Army alone.”[76]

The Mormon Prof. Leonard Arrington in his Great Basin Kingdom, said, “Church policy broke with the past by actively soliciting financial assistance from outsiders. And the concessions made to those outside financial interests paved the way for absentee ownership and control. Eventually, the levithan of American finance capitalism finally ruled Utah as it had long ruled Montana and other western states and territories."[77] “The self sufficient kingdom may be said to have been brought to an end. A more acceptable adjustment between spiritual and seculiar interests was attained. And with this adjustment, the church no longer offered a geographic and institutional alternative to Babylon. Faith became increasingly separated from community policy, and religion from society. Individualism, speculation, and inequality—once thought to be characteristics of Babylon—were woven into the fabric of Mormon life.”[78]

Dr. Robert Dwyer wrote as his doctrinal thesis at Catholic University of America A Gentile Comes to Utah. He is now the Catholic Bishop in Nevada, and formerly lived in Salt Lake City. He says, “There seems to be less profanity, rowdyism, rampant and noisy wickedness among the young Mormons than among the youth of any other town or city where I have been."[79]

Roy B. West, Jr., a former Mormon missionary in Germany, but now out of the Church, writes a sympathetic book: Kingdom of the Saints. He concludes, “Heber Grant was President from 1918 to 1945. He was a member of or chairman of so many boards of directors that skeptical members of the church often asked themselves how much time President Grant had for spiritual affairs. His administration gave rise to fears that the Church had become an organization destined to be administered by aged patriarchs of an ultra-conservative cast—men whose judgments were too likely to be affected by the least lively minds among their subordinates. David O. McKay, President from 1951 to the present. His first actions showed him to be a more vigorous and strongminded administrator than most of his followers had anticipated. He curbed the authority of some of Grant’s most conservative leaders, whose business interests and political bias had much to do with determining church policy… the member who once had a voice in advising his superiors through the priesthood quorums finds his way barred by men in the lower ranks of authority who are too afraid of the men above them to risk carrying criticism up the ladder of leadership.”[80]

M.R. Werner wrote a critical life of Brigham Young. He says of Joseph Smith, “It is impossible to determine exactly whether the golden plates of the Book of Mormon were an imaginative delusion ofJoseph Smith’s, or whether they were a piece of conscious fakery instituted at first for fun and later developed for their financial possibilities. His later acts seem to favor the opinion that he had succeeded in deluding himself, however much he may have been interested at first in deceiving other people.”[81] It is my conviction that Joseph Smith wrote the Book of Mormon without the aid of God, and that the book itself shows evidence of beinga product of Smith’s environment.[82] The important question is not whether Joseph Smith was divinely inspired, but whether he thought he was divinely inspired.”[83]

Prof. Thomas F. O’Dea, a Catholic teaching sociology at the University of Utah writes on The Mormons, and concludes, “The conservative, literalist, fundamentalist group seems now to control the church, and these principles of church organization—lay leadership, seniority as the basis of promotion, selection on other bases than theological learning, and control of appointments by conservative elements—make the advancement of liberals into church leadership very unlikely in the next several years. Yet it is these very liberals, shut out from leadership, who in the church’s educational system are saving many of the youth from apostasy. President McKay, while a man generally respected by all groups within the church, is not unfriendly to the liberals.[84] Moreover, it would seem a grave mistake for a religious movement to concentrate its attention on this—worldly activities, since it is precisely this—worldliness and activism that modern man appears to find inadequate. For organized religion to offer competition in spheres of life in which non-religious organizations do better—spheres themselves inadequate to the facing of deeper human problems—is to be found wanting. The basic need of Mormonism may well become a search for more contemplative understanding of the problem of God and man. And it is precisely here that the intellectuals—the products of Mormonism’s great vale of education—may make important contributions. It is a tremendous presumption to attempt to judge the future of a movement like Mormonism, yet it is my suspicion that those who emphasize the obsolescence of Mormonism, those who see the end of them in a stereotyped lack of creativity and a routine running down, who believe that this Mormon world will end not with a bang but a whimper, are wrong. There is still too much vitality—the characteristic Mormon vitality—remaining for such a prognosis to be likely.”[85]

Now after reading these books and studying their conclusions, and after asking questions of my many Mormon friends, I will venture the following opinions. Bear in mind that the preceding pages of quotations from authors who evaluate are thoughts that I can in part agree with, or I would not have selected them.

But first let me describe for non-Mormons what the Sacrament Meetings of the Mormons are like. In cities where there are few Mormons, the meetings begin at 7 or 8 o’clock p.m. and last for about an hour. The Bishop announces who will take part and then calls upon, say, a young man to open the meeting with prayer. Then about half a dozen young men distribute the bread after some such prayer as, “Oh God, Eternal Father, bless this bread taken in remembrance of the body of thy son Jesus Christ that we may partake of it in remembrance of Him.” And likewise when the water is distributed in small cups. Then a song is sung before and after, and perhaps a young girl reads from a piece of paper or recites from memory a four-minute talk on some Biblical hero. Then maybe a young couple play a duet or sing a song. Then perhaps two returned missionaries tell of their experiences, after which there is a song and a prayer. If there is any business it is conducted first, such as voting by hands to “sustain” an appointee to some church function. No one ever votes not to “sustain” any person. Here in Salt Lake City at the University Ward where I attend there are at times musical selections, but as the membership is composed mostly of students there are no young folks taking part. At times there will be but one speaker as when a Dr. burned a cigarette and put nicotine on a mouse causing its instant death, in a talk against smoking. Or when the Chaplain at the state prison spoke of affairs there. He did not tell of the tear-gassing of inmates and afterward I chided him about it. Speakers have read from Tolstoy’s Kingdom of God Is Within You, quoted from Thoreau and Gandhi, and one of them said that if Christ was speaking today across the tracks none of them would hear Him for they were respectable folks and wouldn’t go across the tracks, shame them! Also about a Mormon who kept the Word of Wisdom and paid his full tithe, but needed humanizing as he was unsociable and greedy. Then on the first Sunday of the month is a Fast Meeting where those present have missed two meals and turn the money over to the Bishop to pay rent, utilities, etc. for the poor. The Bishop said some members must live very frugally for the price of their meals were only eight cents each. These meetings, after the sacraments and songs, are testimony meetings where anyone can get up and speak, being similar to the Wednesday evening meetings of the Christian Scientists. At times these testimonies are tiresome and one gets the feeling of being at a Rotary Club or Fuller Brush salesmen pep meeting, but at other times very sincere thoughts are given. Each talk in all of the meetings is ended with the expression “I bear testimony in the name of Jesus Christ that the Gospel is true.” And most of the congregation concurs by saying “amen.” A scribe sits on the platform and takes an account of what goes on and the number of those present, both Mormons and Gentiles. Unless the usher who passes by me knows me I am offered communion and I whisper to him “I am Gentile.” In towns where the Mormons are few, or I am told in Mormon towns out in the state, there is a spontaneous welcome of a stranger, but here in Salt Lake City the Bishop may welcome you but most others pay little attention. Of course now that I have been attending for two years, many of the folks know me and speak to me. On a rainy day some of them have driven me downtown.

On days when I attend the Greek Orthodox I seldom see a blonde there, but here at LDS (the Mormons seldom call themselves “Mormons,” but use the abbreviation “LDS”) most people are blondes, as the converts have come from the north of Europe. The Bishop announced one day that during the past year there had been 26 marriages in the ward, and 20 of them had been in the Temple “for time and eternity.” At another time he called for three volunteers on a Saturday to work on the Stake Farm. There is Sunday School in the morning and MIA (Mutual Improvement Association) on Tuesday nights at the Mormon Institute. The latter is attended by hundreds and consists of talks given by noted Mormons. At all of these meetings, parents bring their small children, but if there is too much noise they are taken outside for a time. The whole atmosphere at the Sacrament Meetings is informal, announcements being made of births and deaths. A speaker generally prefaces his remarks by saying “Dear Brothers and Sisters.”

In Catholic Churches you very seldom hear a good sermon. It is usually a call for money or a denunciation of Communism or birth control, or at the best a dreary lot of hellfire theology. At the Greek Orthodox Church the sermon is short and tends to be ethical instead of commercial. At the Japanese Buddhist Church the sermons are in Japanese, but are translated into English. They are primarily directed to the children, but adults can get the idea. Both the Buddhists and the Mormons are happy people, as contrasted to the dreary fear of hell or of the Communists that one generally hears in Catholic and Protestant churches. As I have said before the Unitarian Church tends to be a good, or a bad, book review, although you are sure to get a social message there, instead of theology. The attendance at the Mormon Church is interesting and not dull, and I always look forward to going there. I attend the Catholic Church to receive the Sacraments, and only occasionally in the poor churches across the tracks do I hear a sermon worth listening to.

Around the time of Joseph Smith, an Indian chief asked a missionary why, if God had caused a Bible to be written, had He not written it so it could be understood; that he would wait a year and see if the new brand of Christian just arrived was as tricky and bloodthirsty as the previous one.

It is possible that the boy Joseph, sensing the bankruptcy of all existing religions, had prayed to God and did receive a vision from on high. It is obvious that there is little that is heavenly in the Book of Mormon, filled as it is with tales of murder and deceit, and paraphrased from Biblical stories. Even if it were true as history it is not important enough for a guide in these tempestuous days. Something more is needed than the old “eye for an eye” philosophy. It is obvious that midst his digging for buried treasure and his playing around with peep-stones young Joseph found that he could put across as bonafide whatever he fancied. It is also obvious that his revelation on polygamy, however it resulted in building up Utah, came to cover up his affairs with young girls and with the wives of those sent away on a mission. Whether prankster spirits or imps or his own bubbling imagination was the cause of his continued revelations is something that can only be guessed at. Certainly power corrupted him and led to his death, for there was nothing holy or inspired in his strutting around in uniform and driving out of the Church and out of Nauvoo any who questioned his secret wives or his open delusions of grandeur.

Out of equalitarian dreams of Robert Owen and Fourier and the ferment of new religious thought of the times he did evolve his Word of Wisdom, which even today is worthwhile and which is something where the Mormons excel other religions. Their attempt at the United Order is also praiseworthy and could be even approximated today if it were believed enough. Perhaps because they chickened out on polygamy, they unconsciously emphasize the Word of Wisdom to cancel their guilt.

Brigham Young did not pretend to be holy. He was a great organizer and without him the Mormons would likely have been no more than a tiny sect split into warring factions. He gathered from afar, not Saints, but varied kinds of people, and welded them into communities of cooperative effort. His threat to burn Salt Lake City was a masterly strategy, keeping the U.S. Army at bay. He dealt with kindness toward the Indians which was something new in those days. But, like Joseph, his assumption of dictatorial power brought on the crisis whereby the Mormons had to cease their open polygamy, and control of the economics was limited. The expulsion of those who dared not “sustain” his policies, or who opposed his monopoly of sugar and salt and other business ventures, and the handing over to Porter Rockwell or Bill Hickman and their Danites for punishment those who opposed him, is no more to be approved than the modern tyranny of a Hitler, a Stalin, or a Franco. If polygamy was directed by God then to chicken out on it under persecution was cowardly. The assertion of the Church that the Constitution was divinely inspired, in lieu of the studies of Beard, the historian, is silly, and its adherence to man made law rather than that of God, as nearly all other churches teach, is part of their worship of Mammon.

“The Constitution had been drafted by men representing special economic interest. Four-fifths of them were public creditors, one-third were land speculators, and one-fifth represented interests in shipping, manufacturing, and merchandising. Most of them were lawyers. The old Articles of Confederation, to which the States had subscribed in good faith as a working agreement, made all the provision for their own amendment; and now these men had ignored these provisions, simply putting the Articles of Confederation in the waste-basket and bringing forth an entirely new document of their own devising. Jefferson had criticized it because it had no Bill of Rights and did not provide against indefinite tenure of office.” From pages 176, 177 of Jefferson, by Albert Jay Nock, Harcourt, Brace Co., N.Y. 1926.

The Mormons often say that the Constitution was divinely inspired and opened by prayer. The truth is that Franklin, no especially religious or moral man himself, suggested this prayer daily, but the motion was not passed, Alexander Hamilton saying they were not in need of “foreign aid.” And the fact is that those who called the Convention lied about its purpose, for they intended to form an entirely new centralized government to keep the farmers and the poor from ever overriding the rich and powerful. The Articles of Confederation were only to be changed by unanimous vote, but they changed it to a two-thirds vote and had to use many tricks to get that accord. Rhode Island and North Carolina let the new Constitution become a law without ratifying it. Beard says it was as much by accident as intent that we did not have a parliamentry form of government like England. The proceedings were secret and it was only by the fact that Madison kept notes that 50 years later we really knew what went on.

The mechanics of church government whereby conservative old men elect each other to rule is something which the Catholic Church has been doing for nearly two thousand years, resulting in their stagnation spiritually. The Mormons have had less time to become corrupt but they have done very well at it.

Since the time of Brigham Young, Mormon leaders have tended to be business men, as Catholic Bishops and Cardinals are also chosen, without much pretension of being holy men, and with little vision beyond the collecting of tithes and the expansion of their political and industrial power.

On the positive side there is a Mormon tradition of self-help, rather than looking to the government, which is as counter to the this welfare-state age as was the original Mormon teaching to orthodoxy. They pay taxes for the relief of the poor Gentiles, but do not moan about it, and feed their own people by their fasting and self denial. This is in contrast to most Catholics who cry because they pay taxes for public schools and have to support their own parochial schools, so now that a Catholic President is in power they ask for federal aid. If Catholics disciplined themselves as the Mormons do in not using liquor and tobacco, and not depend upon gambling for an income, they could support their own schools. This emphasis upon a clean life on the part of the Mormons is their greatest asset. There is also an occasional healing by the “laying on of hands,” perhaps practiced with the old sincerity of the Christian Scientists, or of the early days at Lourdes. There is also the emphasis upon inquiry and there is no index of the books which Mormons must not read. When I have attended Buddhist services twice a month I have often met young Mormons there.

Individual polygamists whom I have met, and those called “fundamentalists” whose literature I have read or whose clandestine meetings I have attended, predict the destruction of “Anti-Christ” who is in control of the official Mormon Church, somewhat like the Jehovah’s Witnesses and some Protestants call the Catholic Church “the whore of Babylon” and predict the destruction of all but the select few—the 144,000 who have kept the faith. These folks accept the debasement of the Negro, support of war, obedience to the government, except in the case of polygamy. They seem as bad as regular Mormons in their denial of civil rights to minority races. But, as stated previously, I have met a few radical pacifistic and anarchistic polygamous who do not belong to any group. As Prof. O’Dea states, there is still much of the old time Mormon vitality and integrity, which calls for those who are not afraid to make their church something like it was supposed to be. Here they are predominant. All they have to do is to be rebels. I am interested in the polygamous because they are a minority group, not because I favor polygamy, but they have their rights to practice their religion, if they take the punishment, that comes with it.

It has been said that if a person is a good Mormon he doesn’t have time to do much else. Their praying for the dead in the Temple is as sensible and authentic as the Masses for those in purgatory by which Catholics keep their priests busy. Their theory of a pre-existent life coincides with the Hindu, Rosicrucian, and Hopi Indian teachings, and would seem to be more reasonable and just as Biblical as the “hell and damnation” of the orthodox Christians. But their emphasis upon “blood atonement,” the degradation of the Negro, and their emphasis upon worldly success as a proof of the favor of God leaves the Mormons no better than other religions which worship the Golden Calf in the Name of Christ.

Because of the pressure of Communism, and the inroads which the Jehovah’s Witnesses are making upon orthodox religions; and also the storefront churches which “Bible-bang” the old time religion, that the fashionable churches have replaced with their social worker attitude to life, there is room for those millions who have not heard of Mormonism to be converted to this strange theology. They could have 20 million members instead of two million and their influence would not be as great politically and economically, outside of Utah, as the Catholic Church, the Mohammedans, the Buddhists, or Hindu religions in those countries where they are dominant, or even the Baptists in the “deep south.”

The future lies, not with any of the organized religions, all of which have gone to seed, but with that spirit abroad in the world which typifiies Gandhi, Martin Luther King, and Albert Schweitzer, men who escaped from the restrictive bands of their religions, and who present a positive message of hope, self-sacrifice, and joy, rather than the piling up of money and the building of new religious edifices. Who will be the Gandhi of America? This is the challenge!

A speaker at one of the Sacrament Meetings of the Mormons which I attended told of the Christian who asked God to guide his foosteps, but the fellow, like most church members, never moved. He was content to mumble prayers.

Let young Catholics listen to the theologian Father Hans Kung, who, at the Vatican Council, calls for the abolition of the Index, the freedom of worship for Protestants in Spain and Portugal, and the right of the individual priest to obey his conscience rather than the medieval closed mind of his superior, and who quotes the “Grand Inquisitor.” Let them listen to the criticism of the Jesuit Father George Dunne who has told off stuffed shirt superiors all of his life and has insisted in speaking “controversally.” Let them listen to Dorothy Day who visited Pope John XXIII asking him to allow a Catholic to be a conscientious objector, instead of, like most Popes, asking for peace, but always supporting war. And let them listen to Pope John who tried to “get out of the bag” into which the conservative Curia bureaucrats had placed him. Let them listen to Pope Paul VI who it is hoped will continue Pope John’s ideas.

Let young Mormons have the courage to refuse to sustain ancient bureaucrats among their leaders. (The Danites won’t get you now.) Let them believe what they like about “the Gospel of Joseph Smith being true,” but, as Tolstoy says, let not this belief keep them from pioneering spiritually as their forefathers did materially. Let them know that Negroes are also their brothers; let them know that there is something higher than “obeying the law of the land.” Let them be courageous in helping to remove their state of Utah from the ideology of the deep south on the subject of civil rights. Let them stay in their Church, for a new one would in time become just as corrupt; let them have the courage of Joseph Smith and Brigham Young in searching for truth and in living it against many odds. They have the heritage of good bodies from their Word of Wisdom; let them be a leaven instead of an indigestible lump in the body politic.

Acknowledgments

From page 87 of Autobiography of Andrew White, N.Y. 1907. ↩
From page 94 of Brigham Young, by M.P. Werner, Harcourt, Brace Co., N.Y. 1925. ↩
From page 12 of Kingdom of the Saints, by Roy B. West, Jr., Viking Press, N.Y. 1957. ↩
From page 153, Werner. ↩
From page 353 of Joseph Smith, by John A. Widtsoe, Deseret News Press, Salt Lake City 1951. ↩
From page 63, Werner. ↩
From page 100, Widtsoe. ↩
From Isn’t One Wife Enough, by Kimball Young, Henry Holt Co., N.Y. 1954. Direct quotations not allowed. ↩
From page 404 of No Man Knows My History, by Fawn M. Brodie, Knopf, N.Y. 1946. ↩
From page 47, Werner. ↩
From page 47, Werner. ↩
From pages 155, 156, 157, 159, 165, 169, 171, Widtsoe. ↩
From pages 155, 156, 157, 159, 165, 169, 171, Widtsoe. ↩
From pages 155, 156, 157, 159, 165, 169, 171, Widtsoe. ↩
From pages 155, 156, 157, 159, 165, 169, 171, Widtsoe. ↩
From pages 155, 156, 157, 159, 165, 169, 171, Widtsoe. ↩
From page 84 Werner. ↩
From page 100 Brodie. ↩
From page xx, West. ↩
From pages 83, Vol. I, Journal ofDisoourses and Vol. 2, pages 186, 311, 322. ↩
From page 2 of Life Story of Brigham Young, by Susa Young Gates and Leah D. Widstoe, Macmillan Co., N.Y. 1930. ↩
From page 8, Werner. ↩
From page 73, Gates and Widtsoe. ↩
From page 23, Werner. ↩
From page 279, Werner. ↩
From page 220, 227, Vol. 15, Journal of Disoourses. ↩
From page 213, West. ↩
From pages 261, 329,318, 338, Young and Gates. ↩
From page 462, Werner. ↩
From page 278, West. ↩
From pages 307, 323, Gates and Widtsoe. ↩
From page 390 of Desert Saints, by Nels Anderson, U. of Chicago 1942. Special permission of the author. ↩
From page 265, Werner. ↩
From pages 16, 19, 48, 72 of One Who Was Valiant, by Clarissa Y. Spencer and Mabel Hamer. Published by the Caxton Printers, Ltd., Caldwell, Idaho. Used by special permission of the copyright owners. ↩
From page 578 of The Story of the Mormons, by Wm. A. Linn, Macmillan Co., N.Y. 1902. ↩
From page 195, West. ↩
From page 220, West. ↩
From page 257, West. ↩
From page 91 of The Great Basin Kingdom, by Leonard Arrington. This and following qoutations used by special permission of Harvard University Press. Book printed in 1958. ↩
From page 190, Gates and Widtsoe. ↩
From page 98, Temple Lot Case court record in Missouri. ↩
From page 296 of Vol. 5, History of the Church, by Joseph Smith. ↩
From pages 208, 209 of Mountain Meadows Massacre, by Juanita Brooks. This and following quotation quoted by special permission of The U. of Oklahoma Press, Norman, Oklahoma. Book printed in 1962. ↩
From page 223, Brooks. ↩
From pages 94, 146, 147, Anderson. ↩
From Deseret News, November 1, 1855. ↩
From page 504, Arrimgton. ↩
From page 114, Historical Record. ↩
From letter of Benjamin F. Johnson to George S. Gibbs, noted from page 153 of a mimeographed book entitled Mormonism, by Jerald Tanner, 566 Center St., Salt Lake City 16, Utah, 1963. Price $3.00. ↩
From page 149, Werner. ↩
From page 355, Werner. ↩
From page 56, Werner. ↩
From page ix, Werner. ↩
From page 33 of The Family Kingdom, by Samuel Woolley Taylor, McGraw Hill, N.Y. 1951. ↩
From pages 274, 279, Taylor. ↩
From page 251, Taylor. ↩
From page 262, Taylor. ↩
From page after page 262, Taylor. ↩
From page 19 of I Have Six Wives, by Samuel Woolley Taylor, Greenberg, N.Y. 1956. ↩
From page 20, Taylor in above book. ↩
From page 150, Taylor in above book. ↩
From page 271, Taylor in above book. ↩
From page 22 of Brigham Young and His Wives. Quotations reprinted by special permission of the author, Prof. John Stewart, and Mercury Publishing Co., Salt Lake City. Book printed in 1962. ↩
From page 167, Taylor in above book. ↩
From page 73, Stewart. ↩
From page 47, Stewart. ↩
From page 577 of L.D.S. Biographical Encyclopedia, edited by Andrew Jensen, Assistant Church Historian. ↩
From page 7, 2nd section of Mormonism and the Negro, Wm. E. Barrett, Vice President of Brigham Young University. ↩
From page 15, 2nd section, by Barrett. ↩
From page 47, Stewart in 1st section above book. ↩
From page 171, Tanner. ↩
From page 166 of Vol. 2, Journal of Oliver B. Huntington, typed copy at the Utah Historical Society, quoted on page 188, Tanner. ↩
Reprinted from a poem by Robert P. Tristam Coffin, by special permission of Macmillan Co., N.Y. City. ↩
From page 133 by V.F. Calverton from Where Angels Fear To Tread Bobbs Merrill, N.Y. 1941. ↩
From page 9 by William Mulder and A. Russell Mortensen in Among the Mormons, Knopf, N.Y. 1958. ↩
From page 185 of The Mormons, by Prof. Thomas F. O’Dea, U. of Chicago Press, 1957. ↩
From page 386, Arrington. ↩
From page 40 of The Gentile Comes to Utah, by Fr. Robert Dwyer. Special permission for quotation by Catholic University of America Washington, D.C. The book was printed in 1941. ↩
From page 409, Arrington. ↩
From page 361, West. ↩
From page 31, Werner. ↩
From page 60, Werner. ↩
From page 64, Werner. ↩
From pages 230, 231, O’Dea. ↩
From page 262, O’Dea. ↩

The Church of Christ, Temple Lot, also called the Hendrickites, composed of 12 churches and 3,000 members in the vicinity of Independence, Mo. contrived to buy the two and three-fourths acres which Joseph Smith dedicated as the place for a temple in Zion. All Mormons would like to have this lot. The poor who own it won’t sell it to the prosperous Utah Mormons, yet they can’t build anything themselves on it. The Bickertonites have 45 churches and 2,000 members and have published the Book of Mormon in Italian. They edit a paper called Gospel News. Bickerton was baptized by Sydney Rigdon in 1845. The followers ofJames J. Strang, who was once King of Beaver Island in Wisconsm, number about 250 with 6 churches. Their high priest lives in Artesia, N.M. There are also 100 followers in Burlington, Wis. of the original Strang group.

Bibliography

Brigham Young, by M.R. Werner, Harcourt, Brace Co., N.Y. City 1925.
Diaries of John D. Lee—1846–1876, Edited and annotated by Robert G. Cleland and Juanita Brooks, Huntington Library, San Marino, Calif. 1955.
John D. Lee, Pioneer Builder, Scapegoat, by Juanita Broks, Arthur H. Clark Co., Glendale, Calif. 1962.
The Mountain Meadows Massacre, by Juanita Brooks, U. of Oklahoma Press, Norman Oklahoma 1962.
No Man Knows My History, by Fawn Brodie, Knopf, N.Y. City 1946.
The Mormons, by Prof. Thomas F. O’Dea, U. of Chicago Press, 1957.
Joseph Smith, by John A. Widtsoe, Deseret News Press, Salt Lake City 1951.
Arizona Pioneer Mormon, David King Udall, by Pearl Udall Nelson, Arizona Silhouettes, Tucson, Arizona 1959.
One Who Was Valiant, by Clarissa Young Spencer and Mabel Harmer, Caxton Printers, Caldwell, Idaho 1940.
Kingdom of the Saints, by Roy B. West, Jr., Viking Press, N.Y. City 1957.
Under the Prophet in Utah, by Frank J. Cannon and Harvey O’Higgins, C.M. Clark Pub. Co., Boston, Mass. 1911.
The Everlasting Fire, by Jonreed Lauritzen, Doubleday Co., N.Y. 1962.
The Gentile Comes to Utah, by Fr. Robert Dwyer, Catholic University of America, Washington, D.C. 1941.
Joseph Smith, by John Henry Evans, Deseret News Press, Salt Lake City 1946.
The Great Basin Kingdom, by Leonard Arrington, Harvard University Press 1958.
Isn’t One Wife Enough? by Kimball Young, Henry Holt Co., N.Y. 1954
The Family Kingdom, by Samuel Woolley Taylor, McGraw Hill Co., N.Y. 1951.
I Have Six Wives, by Samuel Woolley Taylor, Greenberg, N.Y. 1956.
Where Angels Fear To Tread, by V.F. Calverton, Bobbs Merrill Co., N.Y. 1941.
Among the Mormons, by Wm. Mulder and A. Russell Mortensen, Knopf, N.Y. 1958.
Deseret Saints, by Nels Anderson, U. of Chicago Press, 1942.
The Story of the Mormons, by Wm. Alexander Linn, Macmillan Co., N.Y. 1902.
Joseph Smith and His Mormon Empire, by Harry M. Beardsley, Houghton Mifflin Co., Boston 1931.
Life Story of Brigham Young, by Susa Young Gates and Leah D. Widtsoe, Macmillan, 1930.

Chapter 22

I Leave the Catholic Church

Salt Lake City, Utah

1965–1968

Some friends say I never was a Catholic. Whether I left the Church or the Church left me depends upon how you look at the question. Now after fifteen years in the Catholic Church I find that any increase in spiritual emphasis that I have gained has been in spite of and not because of attendance at Mass and taking Communion. So I do not think it worthwhile to call myself a Catholic. In solitary in 1918–19 I made my real conversion. This was the important event of my life. All since then, as may be said, is only on the surface.

This book being the story of my life it would not be worthwhile writing it if I remained in the same groove into which I was born. Great changes have been made in the world and to meet those changes I have had to revalue what is important to me. These changes have not been to accommodate myself to the current, but as always to fight upstream against the current.

In Chapter 12 of this book entitled “I Become A Catholic” I discuss in detail how this came about. I have often said that a person living in India would naturally be attracted by Gandhi. In this country the person with the most integrity as a pacifist and anarchist, as well as a Christian, is Dorothy Day. If she had been a Quaker or a Mormon and edited a Quaker Worker or a Mormon Worker I would have been attracted to those religions. I quoted Dorothy as saying that I should not become a Catholic because I loved her and the CW. The reasons why I became a Catholic and was quickly baptized in 1952 (too quickly I think all concerned would agree), are still legitimate, taking my development at that time. I got along for 33 years as a Christian Anarchist without belonging to any church.

God
I believe in everything I said on this subject in 1953, but I would add on the subject of the Devil that I do not think he is a person but is only the name for that which is the opposite of good.
Hell
might be called what the Christians have made of this earth, in Christ’s name. If there is such a place, as some priests say, you can’t prove there is anyone in it but the Devil. So I am not afraid of going to a place I do not believe exists.
Purgatory
is logical, but just how it works I will find out when I die. I am not worrying about it.
The Bible
I believe on this subject the same as I did in 1953. There may be some words from God in it, but most of it is folklore. Outside of what Christ said on divorce, and the usual interpretation of “Give to him that asked of thee,” I believe in all that Christ said. I think that He meant that we should not be selfish. I would not give a bum money to spend on booze but I do give the bum a place to sleep and something to eat in my Joe Hill House. I do not agree with the old Jewish idea of a divorced person not (being) allowed to be remarried. The Greek Orthodox Church allows two remarriages, but not three. I think that a person can make a mistake on every other decision in life, so why cannot they make a mistake in being married? Former Mayor O’Dwyer of New York City, Jackie’s sister, Henry Luce, and the President of Peru were allowed to be married after being divorced. The 16 rules of annulment of marriage by the Catholic Church seem to me not to be based on the saying(s) of Christ, but upon pull and expediency. I asked the Chancery office to annul my common law marriage, and they wouldn’t think of it.
The Early Christians
I agree with what I wrote on the subject in 1953, although I see little hope of the Catholic Church or any other church in trying to live like the early Christians.
Paul and the Churches
I believe on this subject what I said in 1955, that Paul spoiled the message of Christ.
Prayer
There can be spiritual power when spiritual people recite the Rosary, as I wrote in 1953, but today, for me, there is no meaning in praying to Mary or the saints, but only to Christ and God. I revere St. Francis, Joan of Arc, and Bernadette of Lourdes and get lessons and inspiration from them, but but I do not believe in the legend of Fatima and Guadaloupe. Each person can choose their own saints.
The Catholic Church
A Christian Anarchist has no business belonging to such a reactionary organization. I do not believe in original sin, indulgences, the infallibility of the Pope or obedience to any church official if it is against my conscience. I am not interested in earning “merit” or in being saved by priestly incantation. Of course I do not believe in confessing to a priest. Many Catholics can never forgive themselves because of the sense of fear and guilt taught them, and they go to priests again and again in a useless round. I believe in the virgin birth of Christ and in personal immortality, in all of Christ’s miracles, and in the resurrection. That we can be “saved” from sin by following Him, whether we belong to any church or not. I believe in God the Father and that the real members of any church are those who follow Christ, and also those outside of any church. I consider myself a member of this real church along with St. Joan of Arc, who was burned as a heretic by the Catholic Church. I made a will some years ago in which I desired to be cremated and my ashes put on the graves of the Haymarket anarchists in Waldheim Cemetery in Chicago. Later the Catholic Church allowed cremation.
Communion
The supposed effect of this sacrament has seldom changed Catholics into desiring to follow Christ, or there would not be this wholesale denying of Christ daily.
Freedom
exists as a theory in the Catholic Church. Let priests and nuns picket for strikers and Negroes and supposedly liberal bishops like Bishop Lucey of San Antonio are just as quick to punish them as Cardinal McIntyre of Los Angeles. Here in Salt Lake City I know priests who read The Catholic Worker and the liberal National Catholic Reporter and who really know better than to support war and the conservative system of society around them, but the fear they have makes them subservient to their conservative bishop.
Love
is a word used without meaning by the clergy. From the Pope down to the layman the emphasis upon pomp and wealth and prosperity while the world starves and wars go on is a denial of Christ.
Heresy
is a word that has no meaning to me now, for I renounce the whole system of Catholic or other theology which is based upon the fear of hell and the hope of getting into heaven by all sorts of dubious bargains.
Reincarnation
I think that this idea is the most logical, but really there is no answer to the problem of evil. If I don’t believe in reincarnation and it is true I’ll be reincarnated whether I believe in it or not. If it isn’t true, believing in it will not make it true. It is how you live that counts.

There are others “not of this fold” who remain followers of Christ. I choose to be among them. There is no reason for joining any other church for they all support exploitation, and mostly they support war. And I sure don’t want any Ammonites following me around!

In Chapter 15 I mentioned that I was asked if I was an anarchist or a Catholic first. I said that I was first a Catholic, and being an anarchist came sixth. Now I would rephrase my emphasis as follows:

To be an anarchist-pacifist and oppose as much as I can all war and violence, and the state which lives by these methods.
This also means to be a Christian, a follower of Christ. Outside any church.
To seek to understand and to love your enemy.
Not to expect to make the world see this now, but to continue my one-man-revolution, no matter what the result is to me personally.
To help the poor, especially the transients, for this is where the state leaves off and the anarchist begins.
Not to smoke, drink, eat meat, or take medicine, and to approximate the life of the poor among whom I live.
As stated in the following paragraph I recently married out of the Church, so in addition my personal emphasis is:

To make my wife, Joan, happy, and help her and myself to grow in every way.
To continue to be awake enough to oppose war and exploitation in this crazy world; not to chicken out.
To search for more truth as to what is best for myself and the world.

Two and a half years ago, soon after this book was published, I married a young lady, Joan Thomas, to whom I especially dedicated this book. The priests in Salt Lake City who knew about it forbad us to ever take communion. Although other priests over the country who knew the circumstances, said that the Church would change its mind some day on divorced persons remarrying, and offered to give us communion. As an anarchist I know it was not logical to get a divorce and be married by a justice of the peace in Nevada. As I was running the Joe Hill House I did not find it possible to go to Idaho, the only state in the west where Common-law is legal. If I was a polygamous I would not mind doing time for it, but I had no desire to interrupt the Joe Hill House by doing time for bigamy or cohabitation. The latter is a law made here to catch the polygamous. I have found Joan to be a very courageous woman, and the best, as far as character is concerned, of anyone I have met. Also, in all fairness to her I should add that she does not agree with nme in all things, although she is a pacifist and an anarchist. She uses both these terms non-politically and on the spiritual plane which commences with St. John of the Cross’s “the just man is above the law.” We both consider it a mark of genuine love that two persons with such divergent views are able to get along so well. She promised in so far as our marriage is concerned not to be wife as such, but to be my best friend as she holds friendship to be far more important than marriage. She is a believing Catholic and has not left the Church. She does not believe that our marriage is valid, but believes our friendship is.

I value the friendship of many priests, nuns, and laymen in the CW movement, and others whom I have met in my travels, and I list Dorothy Day among the fifteen great people in American history. Although her statement in the CW that she would obey Cardinal Spellman if he told her to keep quiet on the war is not a part of her real philosophy, but just a pious exclamation, uttered, I think, because most liberal Catholics were then condemning him because Fr. Berrigan had been sent to South America for his opposition to the war. Dorothy always is for the underdog. I doubt if she would obey Spellman if it came to a showdown.

We have all helped each other. And of course I regret to have to cause them pain in leaving the Church. I have attended Mass here in Salt Lake City daily for years. With very few exceptions I have never met a Catholic here who had any conception of the social message of Christ. Catholics are not to be blamed, for their bishop never speaks on these problems and is only in print to praise something military or commercial, always in pious terms. If I had lived in a community like Milwaukee, where Bishop Cousins allows Father Groppi and priests and nuns to picket against closed housing, or in Oklahoma City, where Bishop Reed allows the open parish that meets informally in homes, I might possibly have tried a little longer to remain in the church. But here all that is mentioned is the Legion of Mary, Boy Scouts, Fatima, bingo parties, attacks on Communism and birth control, and of course always praise of the military.

While my becoming a Christian, a pacifist, and an anarchist in prison in 1918–19 was gradual and without any outside influence, except the Bible and Tolstoy, my becoming a Catholic took fifteen years of association with the Catholic Worker and was a sort of osmosis, although the direct cause, as given in Chapter 12, was a culmination of the CW atmosphere. The fifteen years from 1952 to 1967 allowed me to speak in scores of seminaries and hundreds of Catholic churches and schools and to meet the most liberal Catholics. I met French Worker priests and looked forward with hope to the efforts of Pope John XXIII and Pope Paul VI. I finally had to realize that only surface changes would ever come to the Vatican or the Pentagon, for they are built upon the basis of unlimited power and they are afraid of truth, not realizing as someone has said that, “truth has nothing to fear from truth.” They both will move only so far as they are pushed. When an especially obnoxious prelate dies there is always one trained by him to take his place.

In the past 49 years I have changed my mind regarding religion three times and each time many of my friends decried these changes. I have tried life in the largest church and found it wanting. I can till sign myself, “In Christ the Rebel” without belonging to any church. I am still a rebel in my 75th year, against war, exploitation, capital punishment, and race hatred. I still look forward to the day when there will be more Christian Anarchists. I am not discouraged to be nearly alone in my one-man-revolution. Young folks will come along, perhaps some whom I have helped awaken, and they may do much better than I have done.

Readers of my book in this country and in other countries of course are familiar with the conservatism of the Catholic Church and it is no news to them that in the Mormon state of Utah that church should run true to form. During the six years that I have been here I have written to the Bishop mildly at first, and then with more spirit, thinking that at least when the two Catholics, Garcia and Rivenburg, were to be executed he might say something. He wrote a short note saying he was opposed to my activities. I have twice been asked to speak to Catholic audiences here and the meetings have been cancelled. As a matter of record and as a challenge to those Catholics who continue to obey a Bishop who continually refuses to accept the social teachings of Christ, I include the last letter that I sent to him, dated August 29, 1967.

Dear Bishop Federal:

I am puzzled about how to reach your conscience. In the past I have first asked you gently to take a stand against the death penalty involving two Catholics. When you paid no attention I got a little rough in order to wake you up, but you still hide away from expressing yourself on social problems. The Boy Scouts and the Salt Lake Palace receive your attention, but the war in Viet Nam against which half a dozen bishops have expressed themselves does not stir you. When I lef 150 people on April 15 asking why you did not follow the lead for peace given by Pope Paul, the only answer was a sermon the next day giving the Bishop’s approval of the war. You do not have a warmonger over you as Bishop Sheen has in Cardinal Spellman, yet he was not afraid.

President McKay and Joseph Fielding Smith are in their 90s and they may not change in their very conservative views of their time. It seems that for the Catholics in Utah you have determined to stand 100 years behind the times and allow no change in your remaining term, which should be longer than that of McKay and Smith. Why should any liberal Mormon convert to such a Catholic Church as you present in this state? As I have asked before, what does it take to wake you up? I doubt if Joseph Smith or Moroni came back they would be able to change the Mormon Apostles, I also doubt if Christ came you would know it, for He would likely be on the other side of the tracks and be dressed poorly, and if He came to the Cathedral He would be ejedted as a bum. He has said to forgive and to love. He would likely overturn the bingo tables in your churches. By your silence you emphasize gambling, the worship of money, and the execution of Poulsen, and the war in Viet Nam.

I respect the testimony of Msgr. Moreton, who was formerly chaplain of the state prison. He always opposed capital punishment. But when I attended hearings of the Board of Pardons in Poulsen’s case the Catholic Chaplain sat their cowardly and said not a word. Surely he knew better. Why are priests under your jurisdiction afraid to speak up? The Protestant Chaplain and the head of the Council of Churches, a Mormon professor, and a Jew, and the Episcopal Dean spoke for clemency. I repeat, why are Catholic priests afraid or not interested?

A Professor at the U sent out a questionnaire on capital punishment to 500 people. He was surprised to find many Catholics against it. He asked if any member of the legislature would pull the trigger to execute a prisoner. None of them would. You and they elect others to do it for you. Peter and all of the Apostles said to obey God rather than man. Why do you deny God and obey man?

Whenever we are picketing downtown against capital punishment and war we will come up to the Cathedral for a minute in protest against your docility.

Many people have come from out of town and phoned your office asking where the Joe Hill House of Hospitality for Transients is located, and have not been told. We are at 3462 S. 4. W. (2 blocks south of the Vitro smokestack.) Poulsen’s 7th execution date is set for Tuesday, September 5.

Sincerely in Christ
Ammon Hennacy

A couple of years ago a young man interviewed me. He was writing a book about people of the right and of the left. This week I received his book, The Farther Shores of Politics by George Thayer, Simon and Schuster. In his chapter on The Peace Movement he discusses my anarchist and vegetarian ideas especially and says that I have “actually renounced his Catholicism.”

Editor’s Note

“I pay no attention to rules of grammar but go by the sound and feeling of what I write.” ―Ammon Hennacy

In assembling this ebook, I relied first on the work I had already done to create the ebook version of Hennacy’s earlier work, Autobiography of a Catholic Anarchist, which duplicates most of the first eleven chapters of this book. In doing so, I may have inadvertently missed some changes that were made between the two works. The material that went into that first book, and the material that was added to make this one, came from various sources that themselves were composed with a variety of styles and standards. They were only coarsely edited for the books. I have made what I believe to be improvements to the original text for this edition. For example:

I corrected typos and misprints when I found them.
I modernized spelling.
I used italics instead of all-caps to denote titles of publications, and made other typographical improvements of this sort.
I improved and standardized the punctuation, in particular ameliorating somewhat Hennacy’s over-reliance on the semi-colon.

There is no chapter nine. What had been chapter nine of Autobiography of a Catholic Anarchist was incorporated in abbreviated form into chapter eighteen of The Book of Ammon, and so the chapters go from eight directly to ten in the original of this book. I decided not to correct this oddity so that references to particular chapters that might be found elsewhere would not lead people astray.

The epilogue really does sit correctly between chapters 21 and 22. Chapter 22 was a late addition to the book. Earlier printings ended with the epilogue after chapter 21.

―David M. Gross

A Final Word from the Author

I had received several notices from the health department to close down the Joe Hill House. An article in the paper said that I was not allowed to sleep more than ten people on the floor. I asked the inspector what he would do if I had eleven. He said he would padlock the door. I told him I would break the padlock and beat him like Brigham Young beat the army, and in mock anger I led him to the door and told him to “get the hell out of here.” I spoke to Commissioner Smart and he asked me to present my appeal to the City Commissioners. I did so and Smart said I was saving the city money by putting up tramps. And Mayor Brack Lee said that they would go easy on the regulations for I was doing good work; they didn’t want to put me in jail for disobeying their regulations, and he said facetiously that they would have to make an ordinance allowing me to do just what I was doing. A few days later I spoke to a group of social workers meeting at the Salvation Army and I was asked by a minister if I rehabilitated derelicts. In effect I said, “Hell, I haven’t rehabilitated myself yet.” I did this to scorn their Bible-banging. The next day I received a notice from my landlady to vacate the place. Whether the pious or the law, or between them, had pressured the landlord to chase me I do not know. I tried to rent another place but the inspector told the landlord to give me back my money unless he wanted to spend money fixing the place up. When the inspector found that I was really moving he smilingly said that he would be around to help me when I came back. He could afford to smile for I was on the move. I told him he would try to screw me for I knew his kind. I stored my belongings in three different places and on February 10th went on a speaking trip.

First I went to California, then a week at Cornell University, being invited by a Jew, a Mormon, and a Catholic priest. Then, with a friend, I made the $99 bus trip from Minneapolis to Seattle, San Diego, El Paso, Washington, D.C., New York City, Buffalo, and back to Minneapolis. Then my friend drove me in half a dozen states in the Middle West. As Poulsen was to be executed May, 13 I began a 25-day fast in Madison, Wisconsin, cutting my trip short to get in Salt Lake City three days before the execution. Fasting, speaking several times a day, and talking to folks nearly all the time was very difficult, and I will not do it again. I also spoke in Vancouver and Toronto. Poulsen’s lawyer got him a reprieve and on November 16th made his oral appeal to the state supreme court. Within 60 days they will make an answer, and within another 60 days the judge in Provo will set another execution date if the appeal has failed. So I will be picketing again for him.

I found that renting a place would only be more trouble, so two people sent me money and I paid $900 down on this $9,000 brick house this side of the tracks. My payments are $80 a month. I am four blocks from a tavern and few town bums walk the mile or more from downtown. It is, as it should be, a place for transients. About 35 is the limit I can handle.

I wish to thank the following who have helped me financially to get this first printing of The Book of Ammon off the press: Janet Burwash, Bob Callagy, Dorothy Day, Helen Ford, and Peter Lumsden; to my daughter Carmen who suggested the title, and to Lynn Birkinshaw, my Mormon printer of the Sun Lithographing Company, and to his brother Bill who successfully produced the cuts in the book from old scratched pictures. To my co-workers and fellow Catholic conscientious objectors who are helping me until they are called to prison: Murphy Dowois (the Cajun) and Paul Mann. Also to the merchants, mostly Mormon, who give me food. The paragraph at the end of my citations in the chapter on the Mormons is from my friend William J. Whalen of Purdue University, gathered from his The Latter Day Saints in the Modern Day World, John Day Co. 1964.

This book has been written, first in the turmoil of the Catholic Worker in New York City, then at the Old Pioneer’s farm near Phoenix by oil lamp light, and the last eight chapters at the Joe Hill House here. All this amidst my fasting and picketing so there are typos, and grammatical mistakes that would make a pedant shiver, but I submit that, taken as a whole, as our lives will be judged by God finally, the book is authentic.

To the orthodox Catholic who may be scandalized by the tone of the book, and especially by the Epilogue, and to the orthodox radical who looks askance at my religious emphasis, I will say that this terribly acute conscience of mine accepts the basis of what Jesus taught; that I feel at home with the Spirit of St. Francis, St. Martin of Tours, and Pope John XXIII and consider myself a good Catholic, although critical of some Church rules, many of which eventually will be changed. To the seeming paradox of being a Catholic Anarchist I will add that my favorite saint is St. Joan of Arc, for she fought the English and the Church and didn’t chicken out. It is not what you believe but if you are willing to die for your belief. And to live for it. To the radical I will say that Christ, Buddha, and Gandhi are essentially more radical than Marx and Bakunin.

To the reader who will see a repetition of thoughts and quotations, I have done this for emphasis. I neglected to say that the picture on page 32 [pictures not included in this ebook] is that of a passport of my wife and myself taken in 1923. And the picture on page 42 is that of Carmen and myself, and our cow, June, at Bisanakee in 1928. To my Mormon friends, regular and polygamous; to the transients with whom I live, I say that I am happy to live in Salt Lake City. At the nominal price of $3 for this book little money will be made, but any profits will go for this lasting memorial to Joe Hill, rebel tramp and poet.

A final word on the recent election. Many radicals voted for Johnson for fear of Goldwater. Hannah Arendt has given them the answer: “He who chooses the lesser of two evils, quickly forgets that he chose evil.” Johnson did not need the votes of radicals. They should remember the story of Chicken Little who led herself and small-brained fowl into the den of the fox because she was afraid of something that never happened. Those who voted for Johnson have asked in advance for war in Viet Nam and Cuba, and the protection of capitalism in Brazil, Formosa, and wherever it weakens.

The Vatican Council has adjourned again. It began with glowing hopes under Pope John, and it has now proven, through its bypassing of important subjects, and its emphasis on Mary. that deeds and not words are required. As saints have said: “The Church is Christ in the world and it must needs be crucified as He was.” The sad part is that Christ was innocent of evil and was killed because He was a friend of the poor and disposed, while the Church is guilty, being an apologist for the rich and powerful.

Poulsen lost his appeal to the state supreme court.

In Christ the Rebel,
Ammon Hennacy

1131 South 1st West. Salt Lake City, Utah
(Mailing address P.O. Box 655).
December 11. 1964.

Epilogue

The following excerpts from Dostoevsky’s “Grand Inquisitor” seem to me timely today as when they were written many years ago. The underscored sentences are in part my emphasis. I am a Catholic who remains in the Church, but criticizes it.

He came down to the “hot pavements” of the southern town in which on the day before almost a hundred heretics had, ad majorem gloriam Dei, been burned by the cardinal the Grand Inquisitor, in a magnificant auto da fé, in the presence of the king, the court, the knights, the cardinals, the most charming ladies of the court, and the whole population of Seville.

He came softly, unobserved, and yet, strange to say, everyone recognised Him. … The crowd weeps and kisses the earth under His feet. … He stops at the steps of the Seville cathedral at the moment when the weeping mourners are bringing in a little open white coffin. In it lies a child of seven, the only daughter of a prominent citizen. The dead child lies hidden in flowers: “He will raise your child,” the crowd shouts to the weeping mother. The priest, coming to meet the coffin, looks perplexed and frowns but the mother of the dead child throws herself at His feet with a wail, “If it is Thou, raise my child!” she cries, holding out her hands to Him. The procession halts, the coffin is laid on the steps at his feet. He looks with compassion, and His lips once more softly pronounce, “Maiden, arise!” And the maiden arises …

There are cries, sobs, confusion among the people, and at that moment the cardinal himself, the Grand Inquisitor, passes by the cathedral. He is an old man, almost ninety, tall and erect, with a withered face and sunken eyes, in which there is still a gleam of light. He is not dressed in his gorgeous cardinal’s robes, as he was the day before, when he was burning the enemies of the Roman Church—at the moment he was wearing his coarse, old, monk’s cassock. At a distance behind him come his gloomy assistants and slaves and the “holy guard.” He stops at the sight of the crowd and watches it from a distance. He sees everything; he sees them set the coffin down at His feet, sees the child rise up, and his face darkens. He knits his thick gray brows and his eyes gleam with sinister fire. He holds out his finger and bids the guards take him. And such is his power, so completely are the people cowed into submission and trembling obedience to him, that the crowd immediately make way for the guards, and in the midst of deathlike silence they lay hands on Him and lead Him away. The crowd instantly bows down to earth, like one man, before the old inquisitor. He blesses the people in silence and passes on. The guards lead their prisoner to the close, gloomy vaulted prison in the ancient palace of the Holy Inquisition and shut Him in it … [T]he Grand Inquisitor himself comes in with a light in his hand …

“Is it Thou? Thou?… I know too well what Thou wouldst say … Why then art Thou come to hinder us? For Thou hast come to hinder us, and Thou knowest that. … [T]omorrow I shall condemn Thee and burn Thee at the stake as the worst of heretics. And the very people who have today kissed Thy feet, tomorrow at the faintest sign from me will rush to heap up the embers of Thy fire …”

The old man has told Him he hasn’t any right to add anything to what He has said of old. One may say it is the most fundamental feature of Roman Catholicism … “All has been given by Thee to the Pope,” they say, “and all, therefore, is still in the Pope’s hands, and there is no need for Thee to come now at all. Thou must not meddle for the time, at least.” … Thou hast given us the right to bind and unbind, and now, of course, Thou canst not think of taking it away. …

[Christ’s temptations after fasting 40 days:] “But seest Thou these stones in this parched and barren wilderness? Turn them into bread, and mankind will run after Thee like a flock of sheep, grateful and obedient, though forever trembling lest Thou withdraw Thy hand and deny them Thy bread.” But Thou wouldst not deprive men of freedom and didst reject the offer, thinking, what is that freedom worth, if obedience is bought by bread? … And we alone shall feed them in Thy name, declaring falsely that it is in Thy name. Oh, never, never can they feed themselves without us! … Thou didst promise them the bread of Heaven, but, I repeat again, can it compare with earthly bread in the eyes of the weak, ever sinful and ignoble race of man? And for the sake of the bread of Heaven thousands and tens of thousands shall follow Thee, what is to become of the millions and tens of thousands of millions of creatures who will not have the strength to forgo the earthly bread for the sake of heavenly? … But we shall tell them that we are Thy servants and rule them in Thy name. We shall deceive them again, for we will not let Thee come to us again. That deception will be our suffering, for we shall be forced to lie.

[If Thou wouldst have given them bread they would have worshiped Thou] …Thou wouldst have satisfied the universal and everlasting craving of humanity—to find someone to worship … these pitiful creatures … what is essential is that all may be together in it. This craving for community of worship is the chief misery of every man individually and of all humanity from the beginning of time. For the sake of common worship they’ve slain each other with the sword. They have set up gods and challenged one another, “Put away your gods and come and worship ours, or we shall kill you and your gods!” …

…There are three powers, three powers alone, able to conquer and hold captive forever the conscience of these impotent rebels for their happiness—those forces are miracle, mystery, and authority. Thou hast rejected all three and hast set the example for doing so. …

[Second Temptation of Christ—Cast Thyself down from the pinnacle of the Temple.] …And couldst Thou believe for one moment that men, too, could face such a temptation? Is the nature of men such, that they can reject miracle, and at the great moments of their lives, the moments of their deepest, most agonizing spiritual difficulties, cling only to the free verdict of the heart? … Thou didst not come down from the cross … for again, Thou wouldst not enslave man by a miracle. … Thou didst crave for free love and not the base raptures of the slave before the might that has overawed him forever. But Thou didst think too highly of men therein, for they are slaves, of course, though rebellious by nature. … Canst Thou have simply come to the elect and for the elect? … We have corrected Thy work and have founded it upon miracle, mystery, and authority. And men rejoiced that they were again led like sheep … Be angry. I don’t want Thy love, for I love Thee not. … Listen, then. We are not working with Thee, but with him—that is our mystery. It’s long—eight centuries—since we have been on his side and not Thine … We took from him Rome and the sword of Caesar, and proclaimed ourselves sole rulers of the earth … [W]e shall triumph and shall be Caesars, and then we shall plan the universal happiness of man. But Thou mightest have taken even then the sword of Caesar. Why didst Thou reject that last gift? Hadst Thou accepted that last counsel of the mighty spirit, Thou wouldst have accomplished all that man seeks on earth—that is, someone to worship, someone to keep his conscience, and some means of uniting all in one unanimous and harmonious ant-heap … Hadst Thou taken the world and Caesar’s purple, Thou wouldst have founded the universal state and have given universal peace … We have taken the sword of Caesar, and in taking it, of course, have rejected Thee and followed him… Thou art proud of Thine elect, but Thou hast only the elect, while we give rest to all. … [H]ow many of those elect … have grown weary waiting for Thee … [S]ome of them, the fierce and rebellious, will destroy themselves, others, rebellious but weak, will destroy one another, while the rest, weak and unhappy, will crawl fawning to our feet and whine to us, “Yes, you were right, you alone possess His mystery, and we come back to you, save us from ourselves!”

…Oh, we shall allow them even sin, they are weak and helpless, and they will love us like children because we allow them to sin. We shall tell them that every sin shall be expiated, if it is done with our permission, that we allow them to sin because we love them, and the punishment for these sins we take upon ourselves. … And all will be happy, all the millions of creatures except the hundred thousand who rule over them. For only we, we who guard the mystery, shall be unhappy. … the curse of the knowledge of good and evil. Peacefully they will die, peacefully they will expire in Thy name, and beyond the grave they will find nothing but death. But we shall keep the secret, and for their happiness we shall allure them with the reward of heaven and eternity. … And we who have taken their sins upon us for their happiness will stand up before Thee and say: “Judge us if Thou canst and darest.” Know that I fear Thee not. Know that I too have been in the wilderness, I too have lived on roots and locusts, I too prized the freedom with which Thou hast blessed men, and I too was striving to stand among Thy elect, among the strong and powerful, thirsting “to make up the number.” But I awakened and would not serve madness. I turned back and joined the ranks of those who have corrected Thy work. I left the proud and went back to the humble, for the happiness of the humble. … [T]omorrow Thou shalt see that obedient flock who at a sign from me will hasten to heap up the hot cinders about the pile on which I shall burn Thee for coming to hinder us. For if anyone has ever deserved our fires, it is Thou. Tomorrow I shall burn Thee. Dixi.

The Grand Inquisitor does not believe in God but as he says has long worshiped the devil, so he suffers as must those who “accept lying and deception, and lead men consciously to death and destruction, and yet deceive them all the way so that they may not notice where they are being led, that the poor blind creatures may at least on the way think themselves happy.”

He saw that the Prisoner had listened intently all the time, looking gently in his face and evidently not wishing to reply. The old man longed for Him to say something, however bitter and terrible. But He suddenly approached the old man in silence and softly kissed him on his bloodless aged lips. That was all his answer. The old man shuddered. His lips moved. He went to the door, opened it, and said to Him: “Go, and come no more … come not at all, never, never!” And he let Him out into the dark alleys of the town. The Prisoner went away.

“And the old man?”

“The kiss glows in his heart, but the old man adheres to his idea.”

All Christian churches deny Christ, and the worst is the Catholic. Most church leaders have been so brainwashed that they do not know this, so they are not to be blamed when they kill or silence what they call heresy, for they do not know any better. They are not to be feared or obeyed though by real Christians when they follow the Grand Inquisitor and his master the devil to found the “universal state and universal peace” based on executions, excommunications, exploitation, and war, we Christian anarchists who know better will not follow them. We shall continue to insist upon the primacy of the individual conscience; upon a reliance on the Sermon on the Mount rather than ecclesiastical pomp and power. We know that we are following Him, rather than denying Him in His name. Neither should we who know all this punish folks like the Grand Inquisitor, for Christ did not punish him, even when he was going to burn Him, as they did St. Joan of Arc later, but returned good for evil and kissed him.